Where are you from Neko?
I am from a territory called Akualü
Although the elders call it Manaure
Ah, you come from the Wild West and now you are here.
In Nazareth or corregimiento de Nazareth as they call it
We are in the territory of Usijou´, in Alewalü.
I don't know if you've heard that it's a sacred place.
Yes, it is the only one with some characteristics
different natural
Yes of course. My grandmother and my mother's grandmother were from here.
Where is the sea? yes, over there, from here you can see the sea
Yes it's true.
yes they lived here
But the sea is far from here? Yes, you are far.
They said they moved, they had left their
things as you can see
There where the pieces of amuchi (ceramic) are,
are their ancestral remains (bone)
They decided to go to the seashore because
They say that they were already bored here.
So they left, but they came back again. Yeah. right here
This was what you were talking about, right? Yeah.
I can touch it? No. It is forbidden
You can't touch it, you can only see it. if you touch it
you can get sick
When you touch it you take the energies of the dead
that can cause you harm
Same with your arrival here
TRUE. You must harmonize with the territory because we
surround the souls of those who lived here
This belongs to them right? Yes, that's why their souls
they are here because those are their belongings
This was their territory and they said that no one can.
take part of this sand
Then we Pausayu arrived to inhabit it
I understand. And what did they bring from the sea?
The sand, they threw it here so that it would stay that way.
That is to say, they brought the sand from the beach in
this piece of desert
The old say that through a dream they were told
to bring the sand from there
I'm telling you so you can say it, this part
then they cut it
Guille said that in the dream they were told
the next
That, if they loved this land so much, it could bring the
earth to here
and that they did. This is how this place originates
You could say that. that started from a dream
and so on
So they brought him here, right? Yeah.
They brought it little by little until it spread
As you can see this before this was small, but after
they were expanding it up there
Yes, now I understand. How nice to know the story
behind this
Yes of course, in fact, all this that is here
it is also beautiful
Yeah. It is very good to make known what
We have it because it is part of our Wayuu culture.
You already know that in La Guajira there is this place, Alewalü
will be recognized by the world
Through stories like these they will know not only
the place but its spirituality
Since there are also many jewels of
the deceased
That is why it is a sacred place because here are the
things of those who created it
People say that here in the north is where
are the most sacred places
And that is why it is important to make them known. Yes of course.
Well, thank you very much for what you shared with us.
Thank you anyway for coming
For coming from so far to know our territory.
After winter it doesn't bloom here? No,
Does it stay like this? Yes of course, it gets wet and that's it
the animals walk and do not get their feet wet.
You see there is no grass. No.
And if it rains a lot? It may rain a lot but still.
it does not bloom because it is a sacred place
the territory is sacred
That was destined. Yes, that's why they were created
ancestors who saw here
The people who come to Nazareth say that their
ancestors son of here too
Those from Dusakawi (health association) said that their
grandmothers told them that they have ancestors here
They say they will come back here again.
Yes, that's OK
It seems good to me that they come again so that
know more, we make them climb the mountains
Yes, we have to arrive earlier, look how they are rushing us. Yes, it is true, it is complex.
Because it is already getting dark and we already have
to leave because of how sacred it is
You are in Alewalü in the Alewalü Dunes
Smile smile. Stretch your hands.