baba: discussing something to someone else
baba: har har
yes, Mahadev
interviewer: Baba, Namaskar
Baba: Namaskar, brother.
interviewer: please tell us something about yourself in a brief introduction that what is your name...
baba: my name is Kashi Baba
interviewer: we will
talk in Hindi Baba: Ok
Baba: My name is Kashi Baba, I live in Manikarnika Maha Shamshan (cemetery) and that is my job.
people who comes to me, I explain all the things related to this place about what happens here and why it happens and that this place is known as Manikarnika Maha Shamshan (cemetery)
People come here to attain salvation, but only one who has done his karma attains salvation.
Interviewer: What is the meaning of salvation
baba:This is a great crematorium, karma is worshiped here.
If the karma is not pure then will one attain salvation? Where will it come from?
Karma is the most important thing in this crematorium.
If the karma is not pure, then how can one attain salvation, it has to come and go again.
have to wander in the births and deaths
Interviewer: Brother, please calm down for two minutes, I have to take a small interview, just for two minutes.
Baba: you can go from here
Interviewer: You were telling about karma, how should we do karma?
baba: Means keep the soul pure
This karma is born from here, not from Maya and material.
To keep our karma pure, we have to do good deeds, and the more good deeds we do, the more results we will get.
Interviewer: But people keep running after Maya.
baba: Maya is because it is an illusion, it will get heavier, and as it gets heavier, the more the effect of Kaliyuga will fall on it.
That is why four eras have been created - Satyayuga, Dwaparayuga, Tretayuga, Kaliyuga, why were they created, that is why you can wander in them.
Gave 94 to you, kept 6 with himself, why he kept 6?  so that you remain lost in it
And the one who attains those 6 attains salvation, but not everyone attains those 6.
One has to enter inside it, one has to meet the soul and God.
Interviewer: But the illusion pulls us towards itself.
baba: That is why the mind is fickle, why the mind has been created, the mind is fickle, just like a monkey, it wanders, jumps and jumps, just like this the mind is fickle.
The mind also runs, so both the mind and Maya are the same, it pulls towards itself.
But to control it, we have to struggle with it, we have to fight with it.
Even if he goes somewhere and overcomes it, he does not get everything.
Interviewer: Baba,like this is Hindu religion, what is the specialty of Banaras in this Hindu religion?
baba: Whatever is in Banaras is juice, everything is juice here, that is why it is called Banaras.
When Lord Shankar came here, when Lord Vishnu came here, they did penance here for 60 thousand years.
60 thousand years
And with his Chakra he created that Chakrapushkarni, Manikarnika Kund, and that Kund is filled with the sweat of Lord Vishnu.
So when Mother Parvati and Lord Shankar came for a visit, they saw that there was a pond here, but there was nothing in it.
So when Lord Shankar and Mother Parvati go to meditate, then Lord Shankar's gem falls, and along with it the earring of Mother Parvati also fell.
When they started searching and did not find it, then Lord Vishnu says, it is cursed, keep something here which will make a big place in the belief of Hindu religion.
Which is the biggest pilgrimage site among the pilgrimage sites, then Lord Shankar named it Manikarnika Ghat.
Mani-Karnika and Ghat, then the name of Chakrapushkarni changed to Manikarnika.
So whenever any pilgrimage site comes here, the biggest pilgrimage is Manikarnika.
Interviewer: It is said that Manikarnika is the biggest pilgrimage center of India.
Baba: Yes, the pilgrimage among pilgrimages.
Interviewer: Because salvation is attained here
baba: People come here for religious activities, that is why people perform body rites, people who come here to die.
to attain salvation
But what about many people that they have come here to die, and are lying in old age ashram, Moksh Bhawan or Mukti Bhawan, but it is not written there that they have to die in Kashi.
This is because if their soul is not pure, then how will they attain salvation?  Where will one attain salvation?
From here people go somewhere else, it was found out that after going there and leaving the body, it was not written  that you will get salvation in Kashi.
Interviewer: Living people come here to attain salvation.  Tell us about how important it is to attain salvation in Hindu religion and people want to spend their last days in Banaras and die here only.
baba: But not everyone can come, people come, those who believe, those who know that we will attain salvation in Kashi.
So people come here from all over, some are in Mukti Bhawan, some are in Moksh Bhawan, some are in Sadhu Bela Ashram, there are many ashrams built like this.
People come, months, fifteen days, twenty days, thinking that now it is our last time, let's go to Kashi.
But if it is not written here, then they get worried for two months and think that it is not written for them, take them somewhere else, then they come to know that after picking them up from Kashi, they took them somewhere else, and there their soul left their body.
So it is also written in Kashi
Interviewer: Only the one who has purity of mind
baba: Not everyone is written in Kashi, if you keep the whole world in Kashi, then only he whose death is written will remain, the person living in Kashi goes and dies in a foreign country.
Why?  Because its name is not written in Kashi, Manikarnika pilgrimage site is not for everyone.
Those who are very lucky people, for them there is Manikarnika, the great crematorium of Kashi.
Interviewer: What is this process?
baba: This process has been going on for centuries, since ancient times.
When 51 body parts of Mata Sati fell at 51 different places, all of them are Shaktipeeths, which are called Disha Lakshi.
He is in the Manikarnika pilgrimage site, today he has become Meera ghat, but this entire pilgrimage is Manikarnika.
This is an entire area from Meera ghat to Manikarnika and this is the entire Manikarnika.
So the kings and emperors made something out of something, some made meera ghat, some made a pilgrimage ghat, some made a maan temple.
But the area of ​​Manikarnika, you are seeing Scindia Ghat, Dattatreya, Mir Ghat, you are seeing the temple of Brahimdevi, this is the entire area of ​​Manikarnika.
Interviewer: Baba, when our soul attains salvation and leaves the body, then what is the time of life after that, what is that life?
baba: This is explained by one's deeds, however, this soul never dies.
This soul never dies, it leaves one body and attains another body immediately.
interviewer: how
baba: As soon as we leave our body, the soul appears in someone else's body.
Just like someone became pregnant at the same time, took birth immediately, even if you give it a different name, it doesn't matter, but the body is the same, only the name is different.
So the soul never dies, the soul leaves one body and immediately joins another body, then those who attain salvation
that is the only body that goes to Lord Vishnu
Attainment of salvation comes directly from Lord Vishnu.
Interviewer: Baba, how should we live the normal life that has been taught in Hindu religion?  We are not talking about the life of a saint.
baba: It is not necessary, a saint may be a great saint, but unless he is pure in soul, he is not a saint.
they are only for fun
So you can become a Sadhu, it is not necessary, there is no ashram greater than the Grihasthi Ashram of living within a family.
While living in a household, seeing all the things, seeing all the actions, how they should run, how they should run, if you move along observing everything, then your life will always be truthful.
And karma will always be pure
come this way
So for this it is not necessary that one has to disguise himself and become a saint.
We also live in a householder's ashram, we too are householders, it is not necessary that we become saints and show illusion here and there or that we are after collecting illusion only
Interviewer: What is the process of becoming a Sadhu, who can become a Sadhu?
baba: A saint has to give up illusion, material things, home and family.
And after renouncing whatever is there, you go to some forest, doing penance, you have no connection with anyone, there is no Maya.
So not everyone is able to do it, the first course is of 12 years, which is called Hat Tapasya.
One who is an ascetic will do severe penance for the first 12 years and then after going somewhere he will get one anna.
Second course is 24 years
Third course is 42 years
So who does it?
Satguru are such people
There was Swami Shankaracharya ji, there was Vivekananda ji, there are such people who used to do all this.
Now all the saints are there just for money, just keep coming.
You have sounded the trumpet, you have sounded the boat, keep moving.
So Sadhu's name is devil, Baba's name is chaos.
So one should not do such deeds, if one has become a saint then one should also have the thoughts of a saint.
Interviewer: But how do one become a saint?  They also have to go to their own last rites
baba: One has to sacrifice oneself completely, those sanskars, tenth, thirteenth, all are done immediately, they will be bald.
And those who have, their gurus speak in their ears, those mantras are not told to everyone, only they can do that mantra.
The knowledge that the Guru has given, the mantra that the Guru has given, that mantra is not told to anyone, it is the knowledge of the Guru.
Now some do one guru, some do five gurus, some do eleven gurus.
But when there is a Guru's work then only one is made a Guru, till now I have not made anyone a Guru, I have not found anyone like that.
Still the Guru is searching for us, and we are still searching for the Guru
It is not necessary that we are searching with the body, we are searching with the eyes, we are searching from here
Interviewer: What is your age?
baba: My, at this time it is 55 years
Interviewer: You have been searching for your guru for 55 years.
baba: Where have we not gone, we have visited Uttarakhand, Kedarnath, Badrinath, Amarnath, Amarkantha, Kailash and everywhere else, but till now we have not found any Guru.
Will see when we get it
This is that we are searching for the Guru, the Guru is searching for us, and no one knows where we will find him, neither do I know nor do they know.
we meet many saints
I kept walking in Uttarakhand for seven months and twenty-eight days, on foot, and in this disguise.
Not in any other clothes or anything, in the same disguise as we are here.
I have gone till Shillong, I have gone till Brahmakamal
At that time I found 5365 sadhus
abbot people
But among them I understood only three people, that three are right and the rest are useless.
Interviewer: How did you shortlist these guys?
We have seen them, we just sit while talking.
Wherever satsang is going on, sadhus are sitting there, we also sit in the middle, listening.
I asked anyone, whatever my soul said and I did not get the right answer.
Later I saw that he was lying somewhere after drinking alcohol, someone was lying here after consuming cannabis and was saying that you give us something, I will order this, I will order that.
so what is all this
We found such and such people, but I found three saints, who were a little good, and even those were not complete.
Means the one with half paisa, the same form of 12 year old that was mentioned in the beginning.
Look, in front of us was an indifferent Indradev, he was doing penance for 12 years at the doorstep of Vishwanath temple in Uttarkashi.
From 12 years, only one day was left, just 12 hours and in 12 hours his 12 years of penance was broken
He was fascinated by a girl
Maya got into his head, she was a girl from Germany, he got fascinated, he married her.
After a week she returned from Germany after selling her entire property,
And the moment he saw that Maya had taken over his head, he killed her, tied her in a bundle and threw her in the Ganga.
so there are such saints
We came face to face with him, where the sages live, where ever the place is set, there is smoke and the smoke should keep burning for 24 hours.
If one belongs to Naga sect then the incense stick should be kept burning for 24 hours.
We saw that the smoke was cold, we said Maharaj, tell us one thing.
Your age is around 50-62. He said yes, I said how long have you been a saint?  They said it's been 42 years for me
And  have done penance for 12 years, I said ok you have done penance for 12 years but for how many days has this ashram been your hut?
He said that the hut has been there for 22 years, I said why is it so cold?
Then he started looking up and down, must have thought that he has asked something very high.
I said, Maharaj, from where you became a saint, I said, I am the guru of that Akhara, I am from Khadakhara Akhara.
Find where is Khadakhada Akhara
search search worldwide
nothing will be found
And later when he got worried, he started asking, Maharaj, where is this Kharakha Akhara?
We said, this is a cremation ground, this is a crematorium, Harishchandra was sitting in the ghat and said, look, this is a ghat, it runs 24 hours, this is a crematorium, you are blind.
You have not opened the eyes here, you have just kept this one open.
from which only illusion is visible
only illusion is visible
The truth is not visible, and it is a permanent arena that runs 24 hours a day.
I belong to that arena
He started looking at me from top to bottom, I said go have fun, go, ask, eat and have fun but don't fool me.
Interviewer: Baba, there are some sadhus who worship dead bodies. What is the difference between them and sadhus?
baba: Now they are Aghori, those who are Aghori are Kapalik.
Those who are Kapalikas worship the dead and awaken them.
interviewer: why
baba: For some Tantra Vidya, which is called magic power, black magic.
Like I embezzled something of yours and gave it to them, embezzled theirs and gave it to them, embezzled theirs and gave it to them, so what is all this black magic?
exorcising, soaking, burdening, burdensome work
So this used to be their job but not everyone does it, some are such wise that they follow the truth.
But here it is mostly untrue, the truth is not visible, it just dominates.
Interviewer: Is it all a pretense?
baba: Yes, Keenaram was a person
His last generation was Yavdutram
If Yavdutram had followed the rules then this yavdutram would have been the 21st generation of Keenaram.
Interviewer: Can an Aghori hurt anyone?
baba: yes
Interviewer: What would be the motive of Aghori, what would be his aim to hurt someone?
baba: It is like that if someone has done such a deed to him then he can hurt him, that too through his Tantra Kriya.
whatever he says will happen
Interviewer: They have so much power
baba: But not everyone, maybe one in a million is like this.
Interviewer: How different are they from saints?
These people live 10 miles apart from the saints, 10 miles
Because Avaguni Tantra is the 44th part of Lord Shankar.
Like Lord Shankar always stays in the crematorium
The 44th part is Aghor Tantra, not everyone does that.
There are 44 types of Aghoris also.
Some people perform the cremation rituals, some people perform the rituals while sitting in the graveyard, some people perform the rituals while sitting in water, all the rituals are of the crematorium only.
So these are the three ways
The fourth one is where people are buried in the cemetery.
So all these are the same rituals of cremation but all are different.
Everyone's work is divided that you have to do this, you have to do this, you have to do this
Interviewer: Whom do these Aghori worship?
baba: Worship Mahakaal, worship Kali, worship Mahakali, that's it, nothing else, worship skeleton Kali.
Interviewer: Baba, now let's finish, you too must be tired, but I will just ask one question on Mother Ganga and a small message
that you want to send to the world.  What is the relevance of Mother Ganga here in Banaras and what is its belief in Hindu religion?
baba: This is Uttarayani Ganga in Kashi, Uttarayani Ganga which is in Kashi is very important.
This is not everywhere, that's why people come to Kashi, to take bath in Uttarayani Ganga.
And to have darshan of Lord Shankar, that is why people take bath in Kashi and have darshan of Vishwanath, Baba Mrityunjaynath is present here.
And Kaal Bhairav ​​is the Kotwal of Kashi, the protector of Ganga and the protector of Vishwanath, so after having darshan of all, Kaal Bhairav ​​is seen.
This is the importance of Kashi
Interviewer: Baba, if we look with our naked eyes, we have polluted Mother Ganga a lot but still people come.
baba: All these people see it with the mind's eye
We see with our mind's eye that Ganga is polluted.
Who has the power to pollute the Ganga?
Who has the power?  Ganga is flowing
And the water that flows never gets polluted, even today keep Ganga water in one bottle and water from somewhere else in the other bottle.
Be it Yamuna, Mandakini, Godavari, or any other water, collect water from a tap and keep it.
collect water from a well anywhere
You will find bacteria in it but bacteria are still not found in the water of Ganga.
Even now, bacteria are not found in the water of Ganga, but if you see it with your mind's eye, it is polluted.
Look with the eyes here, open your third eye, then you will understand whether Ganga is there.
People are cleaning the filth of the world in the Ganga.
The filth of the world is being cleaned in the Ganga and who is born to pollute the Ganga?
Interviewer: Baba, just one last question, if you want to give any message to people about how to live, or want to say something about Hindu religion because the whole world will listen to you, then you have to give any message about how to  Live by or do something?
baba: Keep your karma pure, you will always be happy, live anywhere in the world and if it is pure
So there will development and only development everywhere, and if it is dirty you will not find clean anywhere
it is my opinion
Live in Manikarnika Mahashamshan, Burning for Learning Cremation for Education, here people come to learn a life of education, because this is a spiritual place only one in the world
for the Hindu religion, to burn and to die here
So when people come here after death they forget all the attachment, all the illusion all the materials, they look for reality needs to get into spirituality of this place
when people do meditation here, they know what does it mean by they will get it, what they want. Har Har Mahadev