Silence
interview: Baba Namaste, Har Har Mahadev
Mahadev baba: Har Har Mahadev
Interview: Baba, will you introduce yourself a little, what is your name, where do you belong from, what work do you do?
baba: Yes, my name is Pradeep Puri.
We have been Naga Sadhus for 14 years
And I was born in Haryana, Rohtak district
interview: wait a second
phone rang and the interviewer speaks about some issue with something
How to become a saint?
You can share your experience
baba: There is no point in
becoming a saint as some say.
Interview: Hey aunty, take it easy, take it easy, please give me two minutes of silence.
Yes
baba: So as if becoming a saint is not such a difficult task.
Sadhu is a sadhana
like meditating on god
to worship them
Sadhus perform puja according to rules and regulations
And as it has been 14 years since I became saint
I am a Naga saint
from Junakhada
Pradeep Puri is my name
Our Guruji's name is Raman Puri Ji Maharaj.
We belong to Haridwar
Our birth place is Haryana, Rohtak
we are in parikrama now
Interview: Take me to your early days, what did you do?
baba: We will tell you 14 years from today
we used to do readymade work
means private job
I have mother, father
and we are four brothers
I am the second one , I have one brother elder than me and two brothers younger than me.
He is also busy with his work
Interview: Tell us about everyone, who does what?  What does dad do?
Like dad is in gurgaon
Maruti is an agency company, a very old company of our country.
So my father has a small business there
like a sweet shop
And my younger brother also gets the work done by helping father.
And there is one brother younger than me, he is also in Gurgaon.
Like there is a bookshop, he works there
That is, family life is also good and life without family  is also good.
It depends on the person which life he chooses and which he does not choose.
Interview: Why did you choose this?
baba: I chose this because I am fond of listening to God's hymns since childhood.
To sit in the Aarti, to wake up on time in the morning, to meditate, to worship God, to offer obeisance to God in the morning, to light a lamp.
This is the work of a saint, means do not think that only a saint can do this work, a common man can also do this work.
What is the point of this, our religion, our tradition should remain forever.
And may we continue to call God face to face like this, and may our work continue to be successful like this.
I pray to God to do good to everyone, and  God also says, if you do good things then good things comes to you, his glory is limitless.
Now as we have come here to Kashi, we are enjoying a lot here.
We are happy in our life and we have been here for at least two weeks now
We were having body problems since last three-four days.
We had fever so we took tablets and got injections.
And now I have come out of the fever a little, I am feeling a little better now.
Interview: When you thought of becoming a saint at the age of 22, what was the attitude of your family?
Baba: What about the family members, as I tell you there is a tradition in our family.
We follow the Jogi tradition, which means we are Joginath, both through our actions and through our religion.
So our uncle
We give him the status of father, right from childhood.
So he was more attached with me
And I also loved him more since childhood.
He used to get me up early in the morning and take bath
used to get me dressed with  clean and beautiful clothes
They used to say, let's go to the temple and light a lamp in front of God.
So I use to wake up with them in the morning at 6:30 am, 5:50 am, 6:00 am
After taking bath regularly, he used to go to the temple for prayer and worship.
So  we used to listen to Aarti Bhajans there, we used to get a different kind of peace in our mind.
It means that there is a separate world, and everyone else is different from us, we are not like them.
As we sit in the Aarti, we start meditating, we concentrate on God.
There is so much joy in it, means that whatever work you do, you will get joy in it.
One who meditates, worships and worships God in the morning, makes the whole day blissful.
Interview: So tell us from the beginning what is the process of becoming a saint?  First step, second step, we have heard that to become a saint one has to donate one's own body?
Baba: Yes, the last rites are performed.
Interview: Tell me from the beginning, what is the first step when you take a decision for the first time?
baba: Yes, fourteen years ago we were in Haridwar.
So our uncle had given up his clothes.
So after that we talked to our family that we wanted to become saints.
So see, it is not so easy to become a saint.
Parents, siblings, uncles, maternal aunts
I don't know how many relatives there are who will know us or not, I don't know whether that time will come or not.
So we completely lost our attachment to those things.
As they say, we have given up attachment to everything - money, wealth, property.
So I am telling you, fourteen years ago our last rites were held in Haridwar, Har Ki Pauri.
So first of all when one becomes a saint, his last rites are performed.
Last rites ​​like whether a person dies or whether he lives.
Meaning that it is the second birth of a saint, he is freed from his previous life.
A resolution is taken for  God, the resolution is made to take place
So in the resolution itself one renounces everything, that is, all attachment and attachment are left behind
Meaning, you should stick to one rule that you become God's child for every birth.
that is a saint
So there are 108 Pandits or those who are our great saints from whom these traditions are continuing and will continue.
So those saints are served with food
definitely
And they are honored with abundant Dakshina(donation)
So only after that one gets the robe of a saint.
Interview: How does it feel to donate one's own body?  Seeing your own funeral?
baba: See, this is just a feeling, what we think, what we understand.
But the feelings of a saint are different, he hardens his mind so much.
Like a stone lying in one place weighs more.
This means that a stone lying on one side is heavier.
Similarly, the mind of a saint is like that, that is, we make it so tough, so powerful.
That those saints do not get attracted or emotional after seeing anything
They are attracted only by love and emotions, be it a devotee or a saint or any servant.
So as I told you, 108 Pandit Maharajs are served with food and given Dakshina (donation)
After that, Mundan (head shaving) takes place, meaning the head is shaved and the resolution is taken sitting on the banks of Ganga.
Our Guruji makes us take resolutions and Havan-Pooja, Path-Pooja, everything is done.
After that we are clothed in robes
And after wearing the chola, Guru's bell is given.
Which always reminds us, we are saints, our work and religion is different.
So this is how the life of a saint goes.
and saint in his life
At any time there is any sorrow, any problem, then the saint bears those things by remembering God through mantra.
And the duty of a saint is only one, to do good and not to do bad.
Like these days, these hypocrites have become saints.
They do not even know what the Guru Mantra is, that the Guru gives.
whatever they are practicing
Our Shiv Shankar, our Kali Mata, our Balaji Maharaj who is our Bajrangbali Ji.
So see, every guru has some mantra.
Be it of practice, or of meditation, or of distress, or of the wrath of some alien wind.
So the saint has a solution to every problem
so like his whole life
His life ends in his bhajans, meditation, whatever he is working on while travelling.
interview: inaudible due to background noise
Interview: Okay, leave all this and tell us about sacrifice, how difficult was it for you to sacrifice, how difficult was it to move away from attachment and things?
baba: Yes, it is not so, attachment is not a very powerful thing.
It's not like, humans think we can't live without it.
What does a human being need properly in the morning - food, tea, water
What his body needs, that is what a saint needs, a human being needs.
If a person is not satisfied with food
So I don't know how many different routes he takes.
baba clearing his throat
According to me, I mean this is what I have seen
We have spent a lot of our parents' money, and we have also earned a lot of money.
means we still stayed away from all the attachments
Meaning in life, suppose we took 500 rupees from someone and told him that we will return it tomorrow.
That's an attachment, it's called attachment
Which leads a person towards attachment, and then he is unable to come back to this side.
Our work is not like that, if we are taking money from someone then we pay it on time.
So we have no attachment to that thing
And see, it is nothing like that, my father also has a shop, I have my own plot, we have also built a nice house.
We were satisfied with everything in our life
But one night there came a time, I was sleeping and was in a very deep sleep
So as soon as I woke up, sweat appeared on My forehead, and I felt shivers all over my hands and feet.
At that time it was around two or quarter past two.
I got scared, I was alone in my room
So I chanted Lord Shiva, I chanted the name Om.
And as we continued chanting, our problems became easier, as if our body was in some problem, in some pain, we did not know what overpowered us and what did not.
When we chanted Om name of Lord Shiv Shankar, gradually our body also got cured.
Our mind became clear, our meditation also became better, and our praise also became better.
So whenever I sit alone, I keep singing praises of God and chanting their name.
I use to keep chanting Om, this is the duty and religion of a saint.
nterviewer:And if we know about the deeds of a sadhu, then what is a real sadhu?
baba: A real saint is one who does not step back from his work and his religion.
Saint is one who gives knowledge
We do not consider the one who does not give knowledge as a saint.
nterviewer: How does a saint attain knowledge?
baba: See the attainment of knowledge is like..., our sadhana is also like when a child goes to school.
He learns there, first of all he is taught discipline there, like getting up and sitting down, yes no
So like this only, this is our rule, our tradition.
Like our mantras are in Sanskrit as well as in Hindi.
So
The saint keeps those mantras with him forever
So whenever a bad time comes
Someone comes to the saint having some trouble
Then the real saint will show him the right path and not the wrong one.
Neither is a saint attached to money, nor is he attached to anything.
Saint only does his duty and he will show that person the path which is good and not the wrong one
So the man tells him that Baba Ji, a ghost or an evil sprit resides inside him.
I have nightmares at night
So look, it's just a misconception
For which no medicine has been found till date, nor will it ever be found in my opinion.
It's all human confusion
Man thinks that this will happen to me right now, that will happen to me right now, but in reality nothing happens.
That is just a thought of a person, negative thoughts, means negative feelings.
Nothing like this happens in real life, but still we give him mantra.
Sankat Mantra is given that you should chant this mantra, no dilemma will dominate you after this.
that is the real saint
Sadhu is not the one who will tell him that you bring coconut from the market, you bring these sweets, you bring the box of ghee of this company.
You can bring any material of this company, he is not a saint.
They work just to fill their stomachs
If he is a real saint then he will not talk to you about money.
will not ask you to bring anything
By remembering only God and praising God - Oh Supreme Father Supreme Soul
Whatever mistake this child has committed knowingly or unknowingly, forgive him and let him go.
they cure it with mantra
Interviewer:What is the place of Sadhu in Hindu religion?
baba: See, Sadhu has a very important place in Hinduism.
that is our present day Hindus, our brothers, mothers, sisters, our small children.
They are shy in adopting their Hindu religion, that is, they are hesitant.
they are not coming forward properly
why are they not coming
What is the meaning of today's generation that the world is only concerned with its own interests and not with the interests of others?
They say that if one's work is done then other people can go to hell, that is why today's man is so behind and so busy.
do you agree
If a person respects time, time will respect him, if it doesn't do it today, it will do it tomorrow.
Look, we only have time, if we respect time then time will respect us.
Have you ever heard that clapping is done with one hand?
So if you see, unless our two hands and fingers touch, then where will the clapping come from, where will the sound come from?
So this is how humans are, like the lines on hands, man is moving away from man.
So that's why the position of Hindu is going backwards and more backward
Interviewer: No no, what is the importance of Sadhu in Hindu religion?
baba: What is the religion of a sadhu?
Interviewer: What is the recognition of a Sadhu in Hindu religion?  What is the place of a sadhu in Hindu religion?
See as far as our Guruji has told us
Look at the place of Sadhu, this whole tradition which has been going on since the time of our great saints and sages.
Looking at the place, the Sadhu does not need any place, any spot, any property, he only needs a quiet environment, within a small space.
You can take it in any form, you can take it on the banks of Mother Ganga or somewhere in the middle of the mountains, or there is some clean and neat place on the side, you can consider that place.
He has no attachment to that thing, no greed with that, which means that if I am doing penance at this place then we should take over this place, or we will grab it from the public by chanting mantras, there is nothing like that.
A sadhu only wants to remain engrossed in his sadhana and that is the religion of a sadhu and that is his karma.
And to believe what is the place of a saint.
that is
Like we have temples, we have places of Lord Shankar, Mother Parvati, whatever our Gods and Goddesses, our ancestors, they have their places, the saints like to stay there only.
So that is also why the present day human being is also a little distanced from the saints.
Interviewer: Can a normal person give up those things which he does not want?
How to be saved from the attachments that exists?  How can one set out on the true path?
baba: See, following the true path is not such a difficult task.
Now it's as if you just start considering  from your home.
If we are fearless of anything, we can do anything and overcome anything
So
like what is
Man is not able to complete that task with his emotions, his actions, his religion.
Interviewer: Like Baba, we saw that here in Banaras there is no concept of life and death, here even death is celebrated with great enthusiasm, people are living life, so should we be afraid of death or should we live life with full enjoyment.  And because death is also a decision of God
baba: See, life is too long to accept, it is too big.
But
We consider a sleeping person to be dead.
We believe that a sleeping person is already dead.
Let me tell you why
Look, as long as a person gets up, sits, eats, does his work during the day, his life is going on.
he is successful
And just as a man sleeps at night after eating, drinking and doing his work, he is dead because there is no trust for a second, not even for a moment.
At what time does heart failure can occur?
do you agree
that's a happy death
The person who takes care of someone's expenses or has medical problems gets sidelined.
like untimely death
Like dying due to illness, dying due to an accident, dying after being hit by a train, that is an untimely death.
If we do good deeds in our life, we will do righteous deeds of God.
So this life is very beautiful and this is a very long path to God, which man cannot achieve.
Interviewer: Do you ever remember old things and feel like going back?
baba: No, sometimes we sit alone, then meditate...
someone came in background so interviewer asked him to move out of the frame and asked baba to start again
Interviewer: Sometimes I feel like going
back to my life, meaning all this.
baba: See, when we are lonely, for some time
we think, what we were and what we did.
And what are we doing now and what have we become
See, for some time a saint also feels and he just feels but is unable to reach there.
He comes back to his path, comes back to his karma and dharma, comes back to his place.
We can only feel them a little bit, nothing more can be done.
Interviewer: Do you want to get something?
baba: Look, there is a lot to gain and we have lost a lot of ours.
So we have lived this entire life in the name of God only.
So what are we getting?  We are getting only the praise of God, we are getting only His hymns and Kirtans.
And we pray to God that O God, please keep everyone good in our Hindu religion.
There should not be any kind of disturbance in our Hindu religion.
And our Hindu religion continues to progress like this.
Interviewer: Will ask you one last question
baba: yes
Interviewer: Would like to ask one last question, do you want to convey any message to the youth of the country today or tell them how to follow the true path, or want to give some advice about religion?
baba: Look, karma is human's, according to us karma is the first thing.
If a person does not work then how will he progress?
We don't believe this is how life works
there is no life without karma
If we do good deeds then God gives us real results.
do you agree
So we see, whenever someone comes to us, be it someone younger, someone older, someone a sister, someone a mother, someone a father, we just tell them that look.
Stay home, stay healthy, take care of your parents and move on with your life
Whatever you want to achieve in your life, you will achieve it and your life will always be good.
So we tell everyone to praise God, do their work as per rules and always be happy in life.
Interviewer: Is there anything in you that you regret?  It means that you have done some wrong thing and such a feeling is coming inside you which bothers you?
baba: No see, till date we have not felt anything like this inside us or inside our mind or inside our body.
If there is anything inside then only God's name is there.
Interviewer: Don't you ever feel like getting married?
Baba: Look, there was time for us to get married, but we never thought of getting married.
I don't know why that thought has not come to our mind since childhood that why are we a little different from the world, why are our thoughts different.
a little
People had created problems with us that because of this you have become a saint, your friends have separated from you.
Look, no one walks with anyone, there comes a time when even your own shadow leaves you.
do you agree
So parents, brothers and sisters, you know that everything is an attachment
so
Till date, if I have felt anything like this, I have only felt meditation on God's name and we praise Him only.
and take care of them only