Well Neko, you are entering the Macuira mountain range.
These are land of the Arpushana (family lineage)
The story of Wolunka, happened in the land of the Arpushana.
Here is the stone where Wolunka was that
Day, as I told you.
TRUE. In fact, in our culture it is necessary
let us know these stories
So that we continue to value these wonders that we have now
Since this is what our ancestors have left
and our grandparents
That's why I'm here in your territory Magalys.
See I come from the west and now I'm here
in the north. Yeah.
Where the Wayuu people originated.
I am glad to know the place where Wolunka was.
We can talk a little more about that.
I am going to tell you then the story of Wolunka.
This here
It is the stone of Wolunka, where he used to sit
Wolunka was a very beautiful woman
Who used to sit there while taking a bath in the afternoons
And back then there were also two brothers
They were twins as they call it now.
But when they saw her bathe in the afternoons
they were scared and did not want to bathe near her
because of the teeth they saw in her vagina.
And they said "what could we do" because we won't have
descendants for her.
Since the men were afraid of him and of course,
she did have teeth in her vagina
None of the men wanted to get close to him for fear of
his teeth
One day.
Before, I clarified that Wolunka was Juya's daughter.
So, one day they sat down to think about what they should do.
Since they were worried about not leaving descendants, but with
Wolunka like that, you couldn't
Said the twin brothers
As they talked.
They decided then that they should knock out his teeth,
those of the vagina
And they went looking for the arrow
It was from up there where they shot the arrow
while bathing
In fact, there you can see his footprints when he
they shot the arrow
Too bad we can't go up there
Because there you can see the footprints of his Kou'su (shoes)
The arrow that was thrown at him was right in his intimate part
Which caused a great bleeding that
came to the lake
Making the water red.
Wolunka, for his part, left bleeding
and tormented by pain
He went to his father Juya (rain)
I told him what they did to him
Then Juya got angry and went in search of the brothers
But they fled immediately, they had
hidden in a cave
They hid from Father Juya because they knew
that he would be angry
by Wolunka
While they hid in the cave they were looking for them
Juya divided the stones in two from the rage he had
They called at
Birds
So that they pecked at the cave where they were
That explains why some birds have
It has a short beak, an example of which is
The bird Utta (bridged boob) Utta, yes Utta.
He
utta and the other
That it's called
This, the woodpecker too
From there, they chose utta, fuel that won out of all
To stipulate the matrilineal lineage, by which
we are organized now. Yeah.
Because it was not only for the woman but for everyone
So yeah, it was utta that won
he organized everything
And of course I win out of all the birds
I give the name to each one, he said this is Uriana,
This is Pausayu
He was
Who won. He was in charge of distributing the eirüku
(family lineages) according to the accounts of the elders
That's why I remain engraved in the stone of destiny
as they say, there, at sword point
Where now
They all go
And those who enter or the one who enters
must pass
Does the one who manages to pass the cave have a long life?
Yes, live for many years
Whoever gets stuck won't live many years
This is the story of wolunka
And after they knocked out his teeth
What happened to wolunka?
We have our families, now
we have our lineages
She bled a lot right? Yeah. Well, that's where it comes from.
menstruation in women so that we can ovulate
We already have children and we have multiplied on earth
If she hadn't knocked out her teeth
We did not have ancestors, we did not exist, we would not multiply on earth
This is how our ancestors have told us about the
Wolunka's story
That is, our origin as a people is from Wolunka,
yes it was thanks to her
It is very important to talk about it since many are unaware
of this story, yes.
It is not so common to talk about these stories, as
Wolunka's, yes.
About the culture of us Wayuu. Even so, I know
Speak, the story is told
They come to see it.
has your name
The water was red, it turned red
It was very reddish, where
Blood was spilled, yes, where I spill blood,
because I bleed a lot
This is the story of wolunka, so that we
we existed and multiplied on earth
Juya's daughter (rain)
the beautiful wolunka
From which we originate, from which we exist, yes.
What else do you want to know.
It is very interesting to hear everything you have told me
If I am correct
Yes of course.
Now.
I am here in the north zone, to know about Wolunka,
To know
yes, how interesting
To know our origin. Yes, of us the Wayuu,
since ancient times.
The thing related to wolunka, like that stone where he sat, right? If he sat there.
Well, I used to see the images on sheets, too
I also saw it on the phone until now
I was like, I wish I could go there, but you're already here,
You already know it, you already saw it, we are already here and it is very good
There's always water, that's good, it's always cold
They say that when people get close
It's like,
They felt the spiritual atmosphere of the place,
when someone arrives, a lot of spiritual energy is revived
in the place
If the environment is heavy, even some people
her spirit appears
You hear sounds of her washing, at night, if you pass
around here, you hear as if bathing or swimming
She manifests herself like this, with whoever wants to listen to her
Some like it and others don't.
This place is sacred, right.
They call it sacred
Or sacred site
Yes, and with this
I say that I have learned, but just as I was there
many who still don't know
And they need to know stories like this
So that they recognize their value and importance within
of our culture
So that they say and share what their lineage is,
how is represented
Since we all have a lineage, yes.
For example, this is the territory of the Arpushana
Instead, my territory is there, now we are going there
in Alewalu, where my grandmother is from
It still has mangoes, where my grandmother has mangoes.
I always went to look for mangoes
And Kayushipuna is my father's territory
AND
One day. When we arrived, my mom told me
“There are still mangoes from my grandmother here”
And my mom showed them to me
They came by donkey, sometimes 5 or 6 donkeys.
To take mango from here
Although it is far away, we always come and suffer a lot
Sometimes the mangoes fall on the road, yes.
There are still mangoes from my grandmother.
we are Pausayu from Usijouje´
same now let's
To see. That is, to see more places for them
learn more about our culture
and that also
It remains engraved, for the new generation
Also for, children, yes children
So we will continue exploring, of course, we must train
to the children and tell them what life was like for our ancestors
So that they keep what we are, that they are not ashamed
of culture when they go to the city
Totally true
They don't want to wear our clothes anymore, it embarrasses them,
they are going to wear pants when they leave
That is why it is necessary to preserve what we are
we shouldn't be ashamed
Rather, rather, the arijunas are more interested
(person who is not wayuu)
We don't care sometimes
We don't give it importance, if we are the ones
selfless and our children
Because? Because of the technology, yes.
That is the cause, as you already know the technology
children are no longer interested in anything
They no longer want to put on the blanket but pants, they are
cell phone earring
That is why it is necessary to talk to the children, train them
and instill in them
Values such as solidarity, because now being supportive
it is very necessary
Solidarity is our greatest wealth
Can't see a bit
Yes, you can see it, but it is prohibited
There are Maaiku's footprints when he injured Wolunka
where is it?
It's on the other side, up there? No, it's from the other side
for that rubble
I thought it was from this side, how it came out of the water
Not because it came from there and I threw it there
She was there, yes she was bathing
So I throw it to her there, and she woke up with the wound, yes.
And He sat there, yes.
She went crying to father Juya,
bled out right there
Yes, she got to the water and of course, if they hurt her
right there that's why the blood reached the water
On that side, just below you can see the blood
They threw the date there, and the tracks can still be seen
So it happened with Wolunka
this is mayo
The mayo is like the soursop, with which juice is made
wild mayo
That is wild guanaba
What do they say? Where are we going now?
For there, we continue, by car or walking, of course by car.
What's the name of the place? alewalu