Well, you can say
first of all his name and
Where we are?
Where are we today?
My name is Arregocés Councilor
I am Council Governor of the Kogui people
xxxx 's site ,
there next to it.
xxxx , and the one here is called xxxx
what is called in Spanish,
It is called Villa Lucia.
So we are on my farm.
Very good. And well
can you tell me a little about
the conservation project,
what they are doing in recovering territory.
We have seen a lot, we have already gone to the river,
there at xxxx , also Domingueca and all that journey.
And I don't know, can you tell a little bit of the story.
Where are they now?
Well,
the process
We have about 35 years of the struggle process,
the recovery of ancestral territory on the black line.
The objective of the territory,
The objective was four objectives, one
The objective is to recover the ancestral territory.
The second objective was
recover
At that time they called the lost city.
When they said the lost city they were all Tuma,
all stones up and down.
That was the strategy.
The third strategy,
They talked about going out to sea,
but that wasn't the point.
No, it wasn't that, that problem, but
It's all upstream and downstream.
Everything found on the coast was
the strategy and the fourth strategy is
governability, govern
both internal and external, governance, governing.
That's the great strategy.
In the 5th and 6th they asked for support, education, health
And we have already advanced.
But that is no longer a cultural part, but an external one.
So I believe
that this strategy,
I think that
we have advanced,
imagine from here
More or less on foot eight hours from here eight hours
In a few years, to where your town was,
Until xxxx we have recovered it.
It's a fight.
Recovery first,
The sacred site was more punctual,
because the sacred site is
territorial planning is order
both environmental, social, human,
Spiritual, it is everything we want to aim for.
They are under him,
the sites under sacred space and site.
I think we have made progress,
With that of the recovery of sacred sites,
since that is almost as we would say, it is the principle of order,
the principle of order.
And of course we can talk about it as a life plan
you can also talk,
and I think that
we have bet, advanced...
and which one is it
that recovery from that,
which
As a result to leave them
In the Spanish name we have said seventy percent leave regeneration,
seventy percent
and thirty percent light.
Where are you
here,
When I came here, this was pure pasture.
a hill,
It was a hill. It's a hill.
you what you see
That was a hill.
Look what we have regenerated.
We have regenerated it.
This entire area that
You see, it was pure hill.
But from this, through this
We have regenerated and we can demonstrate it.
It is not an invention, but reality.
Yeah.
So those are, that's what we put it in.
mathematically to see the
results,
to formulate projects, to manage new things.
We can show it with that,
with this regeneration that we have done.
This regeneration not only
the tree regenerates
the species is regenerated
the birds, the species of reptiles,
species many species.
They also recover
some wetlands,
some wetlands recover, other wetlands
suddenly they are also leaving.
But I have to explain this, the reason why,
because underground
there was the water bank,
It is what the world remembers, it is said gold, gold
wrist, snake gold,
that was the bank of what was here
artificial, it is what maintains, sustains it,
the blood of the earth.
These areas are guaqueado, this
They put the area in shape ,
They brought many golden dolls,
many and many graves.
That today those many tombs
you find in the gold museum
and is international,
you find them for the outside world
It is an element to see, an element to life,
the indigenous people are life
of the soul, of diversity,
the life of the species, the life of the earth,
the heart of the lands.
So little of it has remained,
we have come
strengthening.
Also many
They made a mess, the road, look at this road.
On the road it is nice to walk well,
but it also leaves a consequence for the future,
a future.
So
I think the story is
That's the story.
AND
when we talk about one's own education, one's own health,
because it is under the sacred site,
the order of the sacred site.
And when we talk about handling
or education, or diversity control management,
The management is under the order of the Sacred Site.
For this reason today
indigenous, that of the people
we do not live only in thinking
in book, think about hospitals.
No, still today the XXX town
Live with your own health.
The university with territory, that is, with territory.
And yet
we believe 90%.
That is, not living like here,
This is a land, this is a stick, right?
That is 90%.
Have, have as a full heart
in life and we live it with it.
That is why I believe that the Kogi people's culture still
and this is lived, exercised, practiced,
it is, it is done,
but with this majority of the outside system
If the Kogi people fall asleep they absorb it.
That's why I think pay attention to those.
So I think the process
has occurred in that
and not only this area
but the entire area of the mountains.
We have made progress in those directions
and
I think that
we keep moving forward.
But imagine one
live in three apartment
almost more than
22 - 24 municipalities more or less.
Imagine the three corporations
and different, different laws
What a National Park, imagine living within those systems
and since that law is for it, that law
It is above the origin law.
I mean,
why they discovered us, they say,
They discovered us, that's what they believe about the Constitution
that is, the Constitution, is that these people are
that we found him dying
and we saved him.
For that very reason
We don't believe that they saved us,
but we are thousands of years old.
We are native, we are from a nation,
We are native and we are from some natives there,
of a nation, that is, born from there, a nation
and that nation has a complete command structure.
But of course
than most outside
just since '91, it's just that
They say that they are recognizing us as we are.
It's not right, you have to listen to it
and most of them have to be listened to,
but with these laws that are being reformed
in different governments in power,
well we are going to be
inside, living together.
It's time to live together, and time to live together and time to learn it.
Learn from it to get by or else they will swallow you
alive.
Big megaprojects, look at the megaprojects
and that is to be very careful
Or it would lead us to the indigenous division,
because it is convenient for the government to create divisions.
Sure, totally.
That party, different parties,
Well, that is injected into our heads,
Well, in Colombia they have already broken up many indigenous people.
In the mountains we are also already
is messing, breaking that balance
and that leads us to lose governability.
So I trust humans
that this is not going to be lost, because we have to face it,
That is, you have to have it permanent.
That must be continued.
The people, the woman, the child, follow
in training, training, permanently follow
that it is not a speech, but it is an experience
live it, execute it, practice it.
So I think that
the struggles we have achieved.
The Constitution
recognizes something paragraphite , they have barely developed,
They only say the right to ethnic diversity.
But that's one point,
It is a number, but how is it developed, how is it implemented?
that's what suddenly
we wanted to implement,
but the outside model is already built.
No, that has to be like that, it has to be like that, it has to
And if it is more with a weight sign,
It's your turn to enter that box.
If you don't agree, there's nothing.
So
I think that makes things clear.
That's why
I think the Kogi people
we keep thinking
recover the territory
and to recover the territory
we need to make visible and make visible.
We have done more in documents, in writing,
we have written it.
There will be lots of documents.
That's why I think
of the last few years
of those documents that we have written
becomes a visualization,
that visualization, since it is required
what some of us have come to document,
which we are going to do with you as a start,
as a start on this, let's rehearse it
Let's see if this documentary turns out much better, and
We can continue making a documentary from the wasteland
Downwards, levels in stops for further down,
So I believe that the world outside
go with visibility,
If you have regenerated, good, but prove it.
Thank goodness we
We don't have a photograph when we received that,
Suddenly there must be one there, here we don't have it.
So I think that today
We have to start proving.
In documentary what was, what is
very difficult, it was.
Know
what today, more or less we can believe that
But if that is a mountain, no, what you were.
I think that's what we haven't bet on.
So
I think the message is,
The message is for everyone
,the message is from the ancestral territory.
The message of the XXX organization,
is to make visible.
Let's start doing the documentary exercise.
So, if you talk about the documentary,
we can make the documentary in several things, some
as sacred spaces
or some we can see
like in the upper part
that does not have a forest, others that have a forest,
others what we have recovered
and another on the black line,
I think that more or less you were doing the exercise.
I think since he's new to new things
What we are going to do is not going to be complete.
And what we lack. I know that has a continuation
and I think that this documentation is going to take us a memory,
because the youth, the young people,
If memory or history does not know it,
In the outside world it is said that,
he who does not know his history
It is repeated, as they call that.
So I do believe that
here in the mountains
we present the heart of the world
we signed it there a few years ago
20 years, 25 years or so,
we made a heart of the world.
The second we made the Moon
but that's almost what we command,
We do not lead it,
If not, someone took it and it stayed there.
The same thing can happen, you take it and it stays there.
I think that on my part it is time to continue following up
how far we want to go,
What do we want to achieve with that?
So
I think that
It is important.
Then he was telling the story, more
at least, bone
my dad told me that when he was little above
He found this virgin mountain, the beach.
My dad tells me, that was like the year 40, the year 50.
Well then the dream is
It's like that. Finally
with this documentary that
It's what we want,
start as
evidence, make visible
and
the same ancestral territory.
The same documentary will talk
so that other countries start exchanging and
And I believe that the oxygen, the breezes,
the breeze,
I think the breeze is in the Sierra Nevada, in one place,
They already said XXX, then the breeze
I think that the force of the breeze, the snow,
and the sea
They are two things that help each other.
So
I think that
that's what more or less
I think I would do it as a little story.
what we started, the struggles
and what we are carrying and what is still missing.
so
Well, I think that would be something history,
This entire area was pure peasant,
peasant until eight hours from now,
full peasant and we have achieved it.
So finally, we continue looking for the partner,
we want to be a partner of the territory,
We are still looking for the partner, partner that means,
other donors.
Until now with the
XXX has been a little partner,
what about this year,
we have more or less recovered it to xxx
others
Xxx has been a partner for over 25 years
and we have recovered a lot.
It was once called The Tayrona Inheritance
from the movie Heart of the World.
It was called Tayrona Heritage
Why did they give them that Tayrona Heritage foundation?
Because the heir Tayrona, let him return it.
But Alan's foundation stayed there.
I mean, then like I'm demanding
the to reactivate the Tayrona inheritance,
because heir, the inheritance that everything he lost,
How do we recover it in the inheritance?
Then I will continue searching
the partner, a partner through donors
another we can look for partners of documentary filmmakers,
I know that this documentary can come out one or two,
which may be better or less.
I'm going to continue looking for a partner, documentary filmmakers,
and he is a documentary partner, he has to join.
In other words, it is not the interest of the documentarian.
of the other, but rather be a partner.
Let's look for one, two or I don't know,
for that documentary partner to join,
that this documentary filmmaker becomes a documentary
thick, big, capable
to start making the documentary presentation,
this presentation.
I think that is going to be more striking than in writing.
We have it there.
We have the book called XXX there,
it's a book. The book entry
It is a title that means trembling.
Which
the one from XXX We are showing the outside world,
That's how they are destroying it, that's how they are
ending, this is how they are ending it,
but in the letter,
I know that the documentary filmmaker
We have to do something as it is being destroyed,
I mean, it's over, yes, then
those XXX.
It is a message from the world cup that says beware
Let them begin to control the mountains,
eye that
from destroying the mountains so much is going to come
This XXX
That is why our message is
In many parts making a tremendous tremor,
It is a striking
What a tremendous lightning bolt it is doing to us.
It is a call that
Nature is making us, lower your attention,
The indigenous people know why that happens, so I think that
the message here
It's small that you are documenting it.
I think this is
that later we unify with the black line,
with the moor ahead. truly unify it,
seriously that
later, that documentary
We are not simply going to do it, but
It is a documentary of the future for youth,
for the new generations, to see it
as it was in the year 2023
and I don't know what year we are going to arrive, we don't know 2050, I don't know
What are we going to get to, let that youth look
That in the year 2023 it was like this,
and now 2035 we go like this.
They are like inventories
that you can begin to have the documentary inventory,
that is, documentary makes an inventory, that is an inventory
and that inventory must be kept in memory,
So there is not much inventory of indigenous people.
the world outside,
There is a lot of inventory, of Bolívar pod, which happened
So, I think that
the spiritual inventory does not
Let's do the inventory, but anyway
, in everyone's voice,
I think that would be
What I wanted how to make the message
and I think that, well, little essay
we are going to do this, little essay
that after you technically see and after
because they will see it necessary, if necessary, the
We will continue, we will continue with the documentation
and later
we can do social documentation.
I would put the child and that,
but we can do it later.
So
I think that would be like some history then.
of the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta basin.
and then you
I talk a little about Gonawindúa - Tayrona can explain
Can you explain what the organization is?
And which indigenous peoples are included?
Gonawindúa is physically a hill here,
It's a hill up there, you see the White Peak
and the Monte, and that Gonawindúa has four ethnic groups,
The Arhuaco , Kogui, Kankuamo and Wiwa ,
what is experienced in the Sierra Nevada belongs to Gonawindúa, Gonawindúa is
Is
where is the life of diversity.
Gonawindúa is a movement.
The word Go is something that factory
and at the same time a movement
,very good,
dua is everything that is the mountain range,
everything that is mountain range.
Yeah,
that's the movement,
That's why we call it the heart of the world,
because there he is,
Gonawindúa is Tayrona
regarding Tayrona,
Tayrona is Gonawindúa and Tayrona is the tomb.
The grave that the xxx xxx
and that grave is like that
It is the one who exercises governance.
In what you investigate, in what for the felling
to make a house, to build a road.
Every paradise has to be low
Consult, how the path should be, how it should be done
XXX, everything that is going to be done.
That's what we could
say, like the government, like
a state, that is, or like a government.
It is what would be called self-government,
because lately people talk about self-government,
But what is self-government like? self government
It is the consultation, in what we do it is what it exercises.
Then Gonawindúa
It certainly has a structure and Gonawindúa
It is represented with the big house that is here.
It has some columns, the big house inside.
Yes, they are the columns.
So when we speak we are moved, too
Is it the same, everything that the mountain has?
If then
Gonawindúa is
the life of diversity, where it is,
where is the life of the earth, the life of the air,
better said, everyone's life.
where is life
Where is the lung ?
Yeah.
So like where is life?
It is that it achieves that the columns that it descends go down
That is why we fight for ancestral territory
let there be no disasters.
If one sees that there
It's like the XXX we believe
here is what we believe
XXX no, the XXX says there is the problem.
Here is the peak, it ends here, then all the water
,36 rivers in the Sierra Nevada and there are more in the rivers.
For this reason, water
It is a communication of the sea
to the lagoon above, it has communication,
has diversity, communication
and that's why you can't cover the water
and the sacred sites,
So I think Gonawindúa is where life is.
And Gonawindúa is an organization
Own, we cannot follow
Nor by making various organizations,
but that is the organization of the Big House.
So I think I go down
Gonawindúa
The thing is that we are here making a documentary, that is, actually directed
That's where a guy told me, that's where someone told me
that here what is going to speak is Gonawindúa
with you, what we are going to film is with Gonawindúa
then it is with Gonawindúa
that we are documenting here, then
I think one day you
it's going to touch
climb Gonawindúa itself to see it up there one day.
If this documentary doesn't turn out well,
We say that it puts its head or its paw.
Yes then well I think that's the message.
That's why in the mountains, everything ends there in Tayrona
XXXXX XXXXXXXX XXXXXX
and a Tayrona confederation
and the indigenous organization XXX
Because?
Because they are all mestizo, they lost their language
They lost habit, losing the hut.
They lost, they lost and they lost.
They are,
I imagine that 50 from now he has to recover.
If you put batteries in, well, if you don't put batteries in,
they will remain like this.
So I think that
that is Gonawindúa and Gonawindúa
That's life.
Life, better said, where the life of humanity is,
humanity, universal life.
So
I think that's Gonawindúa.
If you can talk if we talk to the mamos a little,
but let's talk about the life of the breeze.
I know that was something that interested him.
But maybe you also have to listen as it is,
because before we were also told that well
The waters have no border, nor does the breeze there.
So it's a message to the world, right?
Maybe, then talk a little about
How is everything
connected with this place too, lest this
Place is not only here, in this heart of the world.
But it goes to everyone's door
who are going to see this documentary.
Let's see, I think
Without the breeze there would be no life,
So it is that while asleep we breathe,
asleep, we breathe, that is,
better said per second.
How do you save that breeze?
That too on the way
you can go without breathing,
that is, a path
where 100 indigenous people pass today
without breathing from here. 1 2 seconds,
three seconds, four seconds or four seconds.
The indigenous person who passes without breathing, saves,
save,
in a different way
to save it, like sometimes, like outside
They say, if the light goes out for a month about 20 minutes.
Does that save, they say no?
So
I think the breezes
It is in the physical,
It is in gonawindua .
There is a gap that blows a breeze
and
we say XXX,
XXX XXX
That is why it is very
partly as
talking, but you with the breeze, that is,
you are talking but with the breeze,
you are talking and you talk with the breeze,
but with the breeze he is going to start building.
Hey , let's make a documentary,
you start talking to the breeze, that is, and there
a documentary comes out.
So
everything is built
via XXXX.
The word.
If we are going to make some way,
we started talking here,
let's go to that road, let's do that, but with the breeze
you talk to XXX, with the shovel, with the XXXX
and with that you build.
Yes, with the same word
you build to do harm and you can do it,
with that same wind it can do damage,
and you can send it to do damage
when that breeze
comes, a tremendous breeze that comes
That breeze is coming. Every person who has done wrong
and that is the same thing that we send it, it does damage to things.
If we speak with a very nice positive
we make it a good wind,
That's almost what people don't understand.
but only those who can understand who is speaking.
That is, you are talking to the breeze,
that is, you sleep with the breeze.
For this reason it is essential
each society,
what you are going to talk, know how to talk,
because the great pollution,
great earthquake, great damage to
the same human, human spirit
The disaster is making him and he doesn't realize it,
He doesn't realize it with the word.
That is why the breeze almost that we see
it comes from the sea.
And others
They say that the breeze sometimes comes from the basin rolls.
They come from the lagoon,
but the breeze is
in each one, as a person.
Look, here I am,
here I am making a contribution with the breeze,
I'm saying it and that
The gentlemen there are listening to me,
No, this is very nice, you are contributing and they receive it
TRUE?
They arrive and find if they were sunbathing, look for shade,
Come on, look for the shadow,
We're going to sit there, I mean, look for the shade.
then a person
It has to continue casting shadows from there,
Because there is global warming there
and they need shadows.
Look, here we come and we are looking for the shadow,
bone the words
They say XXX, sit where it's cool,
look then when they talk about global warming
each person
see a shadow
so that they live cool.
But if you are very hot, you are very hot
because there they are dying,
Like global warming.
Outside science paints us otherwise,
very good, he tells us,
But the breeze is
breeze, it's asleep,
it is working and alive
is working.
If you cover yourself here,
has nothing to do.
So
in that same way it is that the hollow that is out there
We can't cover it because it has a connection.
a breeze is blowing
and another the breeze, what is already a breeze,
the gas that serves us, look at it
how we throw it away, the example is there
the gas.
So that's why that gas is
who recycles it,
recycles it
Positive words, is what the word
It rises and becomes a cloud
Bone becomes cloud.
And that's the beautiful thing we talk about in the
the gas that is no longer used, you vote on what goes up
and recycles it again, and that's how human beings are,
the breeze starts down,
the breeze starts down, down to the sea
and on the moon the breeze begins upward.
So from noon onwards
until 11 at night there is already downstairs
I recycle them all, when I recycle them all
At 01:00 in the morning the breeze begins to rise towards the snow.
Then see how it works.
So
one thing
It's counting the breeze
It has a sacred site and another thing is to say the breeze is
each.
Here we must play with the breeze,
not so much the words, keep voting
the air negative, negative, negative, negative, negative.
All pensive negative.
Well, that's what global warming takes away.
You argue with the breeze, with son,
you discuss breeze with your mom,
you discuss breeze between government, government.
You breeze argue with your son-in-law, with your wife.
Then look, everything is getting contaminated there.
second by second.
And that's what people don't realize.
Then look at the good one.
A good, good atmosphere, good
good environment, in the middle
We must have 90% positive.
Yes, but that's in every
person, in each one,
from the largest, from the smallest, from the mamo.
Yes, the mamo too.
If the breeze is bouncing very negatively,
Well, work is being very negative.
From the bishop, from the Pope, from the other, from the other.
And that is, if there is understanding
the breeze itself will carry us,
the breeze itself
can't stand the words there
if the air does not take us to other planets.
If then here I tell you in the world, in the world,
let's know global warming
It is not that so much damage is done, but it is
the same words, the same we speak.
One speaks, look, global warming is,
makes it... the one who has the most say, with the most money
has, with more
has, they call and say the word, has
The parable I do whatever, whatever I want.
So I think that here we should be more
It's like the attitude,
have each one their individual attitude
and that the attitude should be,
but the other in the world
you have to have the spiritual attitude.
When the lady is
pregnant, you must from there until it is the child
give him education from there.
If you don't have an education from there,
the child is born here,
for it will live as a total negative breeze.
So I think that in the world
we must also the attitude, the attitude,
family, attitude with the partner,
the attitude towards diversity,
the attitude with the frog
with cricket, behavior.
If there is no attitude
a change in attitude towards nature, since this
also the attitude does not change, otherwise the punishment will come
from them. So I think the breezes
I tell you that the breeze is in you.
If you want to be a leader like this tree,
Everyone, come on, leave there fresh,
A leader has to be from a shadow
big, human has to be a big shadow,
so that everyone comes fresh, bathed
and from there he leaves happy.
And it turns out that a leader is… a leader
without this it is nothing.
So I guess that's the breeze
Yeah.
then well we have already talked about a lot of this
with others,
but maybe,
well, maybe you could talk a little about devolution
of sacred objects here.
xxxx .
Well I think
return,
one without a child there is no strength.
Childless.
Any force needs
union, the community.
So I think that the return,
my dream is that one day
The world must be made to understand this,
the return, both in the clay pot,
so much quartz, so much gold, so much and so much and so much
that's the object
Indian is condemned, he is kidnapped,
is kidnapped,
the gold that has gold from dolls of all kinds or India
The outside world takes it and they use a necklace, they use a thing.
because he doesn't know the consequences.
So I do believe that you have to be a teacher.
in the world for the world to become a teacher,
not only the object in Colombia,
but
every state, every country
The object is not stolen.
o india lies gold museum
or India I find it.
Some day.
able
that the object
I must return to its origins,
Well, this or a lot or India can look like a
laugh, right?
But
We must do this by returning them to their origins.
Suddenly with the president of
Right now President Gustavo Petro
One thing has already been given, the mask,
the return of the
Germany surrendered, surrendered
and I think the president is going to help him a lot,
That mask is going to help him.
It will help his family a lot
let them criticize you, let them tell you, let them tell you,
but that mask is going to help him a lot
and he will protect him greatly in his life and in his death.
And he will do it, because that mask that he feels today
It was a kidnapping of more than 100 years, kidnapped
and the man has brought from there and brings here,
It's a liberation
It's a release from life.
and it will help you a lot,
All his life, until his death, he will help him.
Both his children and children.
So I think that
that is already an example.
This example must be reported
Worldwide,
not just that mask.
Today we need the return of the dolls
things from the taironas,
not only in the mountains, but throughout Colombia,
indigenous people.
Thus they lost their object, the other countries
of the indigenous people,
that also
It is located today in Rome, it is located where…
So I think the message is
These objects are not evolutionary, it is not for us to have,
If not, that object is the force so that, for the water,
for the air, for something else, something else,
another thing is harvest
the water, the water so that I have to return it
that they are condemned, kidnapped.
The dream is someday
that has been returned
to its origins, when
global warming
it is spoken, the people study.
Those are those
global warming that has them condemned there.
For the world outside
He believes that one is a piece of wood that does not speak.
That's for us
a swallow, it is a speech, it has a life.
So
I think I just want to say here
the example seen in the mask with
the current president who brought from Germany,
The other presidents who come will continue
that one exposed, also that president,
I think in history
He's going to be the president here.
and the president of Germany are an example,
that we will have them bet
like the Colombian president and the German president
if he could
voluntarily deliver,
It wasn't through the chancellor, but it didn't stay, no,
If not immediately, they delivered it.
So those I believe that example of the Lord
President of Germany and Colombia
one day, which happens, we can continue advising
of it, how they achieved it, how it, how they delivered it,
how not so much difficulty was achieved and given and returned.
This will remain as a witness,
example for life, then I think
is, those
These are things that I think speak a lot about return.
when that return starts to speak
possession, how they are going to have it.
No, we are going to have it,
tenure is
or where they caught him,
You have to bury it or you have to save it.
There is life, but life begins, annoying, possession
and the Attorney General's Office has to be watching.
You know if one doesn't even understand
like that, but look at it.
What is the dream of us
some day?
We believe the city was lost, the world outside says lost,
of course, for us
had, must be lost,
moss, plants tucked in, that had to be lost.
Then they so lost
they found him.
Yes, the dream will someday be lost again,
be lost again, be filled with
mountains.
Once when they proposed it to me
I said no, not like that
Because that is a prosecutor's office and it watches over the outside world.
Well, look, then I think that in the return it is
volunteer,
Individual, family, than in the hotel
They have a handle, everyone uses a chain, a handle,
everyone change their attitude,
May they return that to mother earth.
This has to be involuntary,
in Santa Marta some volunteer,
someone came to bring me the handle,
You brought it to me, sir, here it is.
And a child doesn't keep that either,
This goes to the earth.
So I think the return, we believe
that the return is not an object,
but, in the eyes,
return
We want that not only in Colombia, but throughout the world
return it to its origins,
to the objects of mother Earth.
and thus return the kidnapped children to Mother Earth
It would be a happiness for them, a happy one.
No matter what state of many years you are happy with them.
That is the return.
Good .
What
almost everything he told me before that he wanted to talk about
and investigate
well, but I don't know
you personally
how is your connection,
What is your relationship with the earth, with nature,
how it has evolved
or changed, or what that relationship is like.
like my person
Either everything or as a person.
As a person and also for everything.
Let's see.
Well I think
It's one thing to talk about generality,
another thing to talk about the community, another thing
to talk about family and something else to live is
individual.
So I think that
to be
a ruler, a ruler,
I must have all the connections
spiritual,
one thing suddenly
have a connection to the Interior Ministry, the mayor, that is
another thing,
but another thing is the connection
to the principles of holding a position,
to govern, to command,
because you know how to live on top of people,
that is, one criticizes him, the other well,
so the majority criticize him,
but one knows
cultural thing is that it was going to be positive.
always had criticism
For the majority, it was negative,
but anyway, if one was
the fight for a good life,
for a good life,
good living, the fight
It was not my person, the fight is not personal to one,
The struggle is of the people, the struggle of origins.
But many people make mistakes when they fight.
It seems like it was a personal struggle,
there is a leader who can make mistakes,
It can be almost personal,
but my fight is not personal.
The collective struggle, the family struggle,
the fight for Mother Earth.
So,
I think my connection
both here human and connection
with nature,
I know I have to head under them,
under their direction
and another part a little
know the outside address too.
I don't have much from outside,
but inside I do have almost 90%.
Have clarity,
That's why I don't get so contaminated from outside, it doesn't leave me,
I don't let myself be dragged from outside, I don't poison myself
from outside. No, the money doesn't poison me.
Because?
Don't know.
On the court a lot,
the court is inwards a lot.
For that very reason,
I have worked for years and years and
I have never had a problem with resources
because I don't contaminate myself, I don't crave that.
What I crave is on an internal level,
I don't feel like it,
That's why I don't fill myself with things, car,
I don't fill anything,
I don't even fill a pretty hat, that is, I don't fill myself if it's not...
I fill myself with internal things.
That is
A leader who does not have problems has to live
well, craving for cultural
You will never have a problem with the external world,
better said, have
90 percent contaminated from inside
and from the outside like one having 20% contaminated from the outside.
Of course, it is also contaminated.
Yeah.
So I think my connections
it is with what, with the principles
and
and the connections
not only how to say them, but live it
and practice it, exercise them,
not like living them or indigenous, not living my language with hair,
my clothes, don't wear them
not from the heart, but within the heart.
Because there is an indigenous person who exercises
only from outside, from the clothes, the language,
Yes, not my person,
nor is it from the heart above, but inside the heart.
Being the Indian is within the heart, not the clothes,
not from the language, it is not from the hair, but it is from within the heart.
And so I think that after one fights
inside their hearts,
you are going to achieve everything because you are achieving it.
In fact, for that very reason
this documentation that when I talk to you,
the documentation is there.
We wanted to do it inside the heart,
not outside the heart, but inside.
So I think that well
every ruler
you should know it
inside the heart,
This way the things outside will not contaminate you much,
even if they drag you in the face and smear you
everything is fine, even if it drags you,
they anoint you, they make you, but you are protected,
It is shielded like 90% of its culture.
Whatever you do.
Yes, for that reason
our security has to be inside,
If we don't get to this, we start to have people,
outside security, weapons
Start protecting yourself, that is
that we can reach a limit, that is,
It is already a figure from outside, walking with weapons
next to one and that is what we should not reach,
if it is not to have with the protections, with the spiritual,
Yes, good behavior with them,
so i think
Well, I think about 20 years from now
I will continue fighting with the people. and what are the others?
My ,
my profession that I have today.
This is not from the university,
but of a profession of the,
of the mountains, of nature.
My design that I make,
I designed my own
and all this is my will
When I was studying, a boy was a leader.
Lead in school, you do this, you do this, yeah.
So I think the fight
It has to be a natural struggle.
The struggle,
one thing is a profession, being a document, a paper
and another thing is to do natural fighting.
You have to start doing like some math,
because one ruler, one being a mathematician,
mathematical.
You add, you subtract, you split it, you take it away.
And I'm a mathematician, I just do math.
I know how to subtract less, take away, add to them, make them.
A teacher has to be a good mathematician, yes,
because if you are not a mathematician,
Well, you have to keep looking for someone else to help you,
otherwise you have to start being your mathematicians
and then
I think that culturally there is also that mathematics,
yes play, propose and guide.
Yes, well, I think those are things.
More cultural connections, that is.
I think from here
After a thousand years the Kogi people have to continue
that, that expectation still.
So that's why I believe that this, all of this
what we are talking about, youth like that has to start from that,
because one will continue to be the teacher, for them
He is still the teacher.
All this documentary is going to be for the youth,
so that's it.
It has to start from life, no,
but you can almost do it
Approach, approach.
How to build them?
I believe that, through dialogue,
that is, get closer
how to build it, presence,
Know the spaces and get closer.
And then, the most enjoyable thing,
how to have a documentary
and another a small pamphlet,
that is, something that remains as being built.
But another thing to build is,
I think that everyone outside
It is the essence of life, of diversity.
Here this world no one can be
here language, we change customs, different,
but the seed we are from the earth,
the seeds are from the water,
the seed of the essence is, we are only one,
but here in custom is that we differ
in language, in custom, but the essence is one,
the water that civilians drink,
the water you drink, that same essence
It is what one sows seeds, that same one, that same one.
There are no indifferences, there is no difference.
So I do believe that how we should build it,
We have to talk, everyone
water, all food we consume, that same
is that the child becomes, look, the child,
but the use, the handling
Of course, the indigenous applies differently, a payment,
and the world outside applies through a
the religion,
also the gods themselves, yes.
So I think that
the most critical thing how we build,
changing attitude in life.
Attitude,
Yeah.
How do we build?
Water does not build water once,
the breeze does not build once, so
It is how we build through spiritual work.
Concentrating. Yeah.
So I think that these little paths here
we are looking ahead
we can almost remain as something
built, not total, but a common path,
We can achieve a common path.
To continue betting,
so that you must return later master.
No matter how indigenous you are, you count
So. To be indigenous you have to build
one long path because if you don't build they get tangled
over there.
Yes, they said what and when they say
They said that they are, almost that you are not involved in it,
knowing that they don't, water is one,
the breeze is one, the sun is one, lagoon
It is one, all civil, humanity
Be it gringo or whoever, in life we are one, it is one,
because it
Gringo also drinks water and the same essence.
All semen is from nature,
It must be said this way, simply, without giving it too much thought.
And so it is, we are one.
What differentiates us is the language,
the custom, the clothing.
It's what makes the difference
but the bet is one.