So can you explain
what are you doing and what is this plant?
Well, this one kills
is called,
we traditionally,
This is xxxx .
Yeah
and it is a bush, a sacred bush.
A sacred daughter of Mother Earth.
She is a woman too.
Therefore, when it grows
she blooms,
bloom and
bloom
and they vote for a fruit, the red seed,
Like us women who grow, we flourish
and we reproduce.
The same thing happens with the xxxx bush .
She is a sacred bush that we xxxx ,
Well, men xxxx , we
The women pick it up and the men
They roast it in a clay pot
and they chew it
with lime,
They chew it and then that leaf
they pass it to the calabash
which becomes the poporo.
So yes, it is a sacred bush.
And that
because men use it, what is produced for them?
good since
the beginning
They left us this bush for men to chew
and
When they are men, they chew it and then
they deliver the mamos with their authorization,
Now they can chew,
symbolizing that a man can now have a woman.
So, that's why, since this is a woman,
now they can chew
the sheet
represents
the woman and that they can already have a woman.
This also helps
how to alleviate hunger,
that when he is on the hill,
when it's like in a meeting,
He starts chewing and concentrating.
When he is concentrated, he is with the bush, chewing the bush.
Women too?
The leaves, the leaves, chewing the little leaves.
No, not women, we only collect them
here. We
we do the work.
Is it a type, a plant,
coke-like guy too, or not?
This is the same coke.
But here the non-indigenous calls it coca, which
It sounds very very ugly,
that that name
that the non-indigenous gave him
They misused it, so they see it as a bad plant,
but it's not a bad bush,
It is a normal bush, for us it is a bush that does not have,
It doesn't do any harm, nothing.
The woman, yes a woman then
They train her badly because she is bad,
It's the same, for us it is a normal bush,
It doesn't have any, it doesn't do any damage, it's a normal bush.
But what does it do very well?
Yeah.
And they plant it here?
All. Every family
or each couple has their…
its nuance of xxxx , that is its traditional name.
xxxx .
And it also grows here, like naturally here?
Yes, this is natural here in the mountains, in any climate,
It is born in any climate.
Very good.
How
nan
do you collect?
We pick it up individually, as a group.
When we are in a meeting in the town, well
we go in a small group and
We pick up, we help each other just like what happens in the Big House.
In xxxx
to help us,
I don't know if you have heard the word xxxx ,
It's like helping each other,
being together, xxxx , like always helping each other.
Like the store?
Like the store, that's why it's called xxxx .
And that's like helping each other?
Mutually.
This also helps us
that we share, that
Let's talk, one is picking up the bush and is talking, this...
Yeah.
So the leaves grow back?
If one removes all the leaves
and that's it
After two weeks it comes back and sprouts, it grows little leaves.
and now they turn this color like this.
When they are cool
They are like more yellowish green.
When they are ready to chew,
collect, for consumption it is already like this, it turns greener,
dark green.
Can you show us the yellow ones?
The yellow ones are cooler here.
Are
They are bugs,
They are very buggy.
On the other hand, this one is already good.
So when one is collecting nothing
collect these more, the ones that are like more
already like jecha
and leave this, only this.
Are plants asked for permission to do,
like to remove the sheets or
Is it an equally natural process?
No, it's the same, just the same
that when removing the leaves
You just don't have to mistreat them,
but to keep taking
only these leaves,
do not mistreat them,
Don't hurt this one,
because this is a new one that is coming out,
This is new, so you don't have to remove this one,
but just get here.
Know the plant.
Yes, leave this one, because this one is for the next one
consumption.
Untill there.
And men do something
also for the poporo process with the shell?
Yes, with the shell.
And what is the process you do?
They collect the shell from the sea
They bring it and burn it
with
palm of… with palm stick,
They burn it and it turns to dust
and that's what they throw her in the dungeon
and consume it
with this.
From what age can plants be collected?
From what age do we collect it?
At the age of six, seven years
The girls now accompany their mother
to see and
already…
and to her
is collecting the leaves,
one tells him how he is going to do it
and they go
learning.
Yes,
and then
there are many plants here, how many,
I don't know, how much do they collect each time?
What we need, a backpack
two backpacks and tomorrow again and so on, whatever we need.
The work is constant.
As?
I mean, they constantly collect.
Yes, yes, always.
When we see that
our husbands are already running out,
We go and pick it up.
And I see that men also share leaves.
If they share it, it is a means of greeting.
This is not how you greet with your hand, but only the
you share
That's called sharing.
Yes, they share
the coke like that to the other
and the other shares.
One picks these seeds
and he plants them in another place and it is born.
Sometimes the leaves
We use the leaves as medicine,
It is used for... like for headaches, for ailments,
for pain inside the body.
One takes enough leaves, cooks them
and with that he bathes.
Yes, and that calms
pain.
This would be the seed.
It is not bad.
You can take it home as a decoration for the house.
No problem.
Isn't that prohibited?
how do you cook then?
Take plenty of leaves and cook with other plants,
like when the child has the flu that gives him a little pain,
headache, pain all over the body,
then take lemon leaves, lemon leaf, several leaves
They are used for the flu and you take a lot of this and put it on,
It is cooked and when it is already medium cold
you bathe with it or the baby or the person
and also the leaves can cook
about five or ten leaves and cook enough
and drink with tea.
Tea that also works
as for the pain
Yes, then the kill is not bad.
I looked at how it turned out, now
It is, it was left without leaves.
To be reborn again in
two weeks?
In two weeks that's it, it's already growing leaves.