They come out
mountains, drawing graphics
and
from xxxx.
And is it natural for it to look like that?
It's natural
And is that type of piece used?
That's the type that
is used to,
for poporeo .
This one too.
This is also used for popping.
And it takes a little while to burn,
this is very fragile
and is pulverized
fast.
So do you make a lime or how does that work?
Yes it makes a lime
And then when burning,
put in a container
and begins to evaporate,
washes it with hot water, with cold water
and
then
They put it in a container,
It can be a clay pot or a metal pot,
something airtight
and then it starts to evaporate by itself.
When it cools, it is pulverized.
It is the procedure alone,
does not contain chemicals or
add nothing, just burn
and then put…
you can say evaporate.
And
How does that interact with the sheet?
And then with the leaf it is toasted in a clay pot,
is completely dehydrated, no longer
the taste of green is felt
and then that's it
we put in the mouth
and in these pores
well
we extract
the lime with the stick,
an amount that does not harm the lip
because salt is very strong.
If I put it like that, it bothers me.
So
I take out a quantity and on the sheet
What do I have there with saliva?
and I am forming
different.
And that way, each one is different?
It grows,
then
starts to cover all the saliva
the mixture, the green comes out of the leaf
with lime,
comes out like thick saliva
and the wet stick and
with that
he leaves, as they say,
well, like painting.
And that's the action you're doing there?
Action, yes
and that forms layers and grows
Does it have a meaning in the form?
or does everyone have their own definition?
Each one then,
the meaning,
it is like
everything that is concentrated,
knowledge in spirit when as
For example,
When mom is teaching, then one is pooping
and then it is greater concentration
Well, one is focused on the poporo
and does not pay attention to what is happening in the environment.
So for us what is being formed
here is how we are weaving
and messing around there, writing
and that makes us
Since all our knowledge is oral,
then it makes things stick in our minds,
what the eldest says
or the mom.
Since we don't write,
helps us have better
hearing, concentration.
AND
when turning
or how to paint
then it helps us
that our spirit or our hearing, the thought,
the view works and
develops better.
When a mother teaches wisdom
Pray then help him
why that
stay in one.
And so
It's like the importance of poporo.
But initially at
Guys, it is only for use by men and at the age
more or less 16, 17 years old
that normally because the height
arrives,
I already know
deliver the poporo.
Did the mother
do you prepare?
On an empty stomach
like four days in
fasting and then
they're taking us
to a cave
and
there all the time
makes us like
pass on all the information
or the inventory to the mother,
except good and bad things we have done in life.
So that's what
in Spanish they call confesso.
But
is
report to the mother everything
one has developed in life
and to have a clean spirit.
and
then receive the knowledge of the mamos
which are already positive knowledge,
I mean what you will become
as a man, as a person and what
will do from now on in your life, in your decision,
in what you want to develop.
If you want to be a mom, or
wants to be a builder, field worker,
then one is prepared to receive all
that knowledge, or rather the initiation.
It's already starting
the stage in the life of a man, of responsibility,
because we live all the time
in the hands of our parents.
Without
depend on oneself,
the parents are the
in charge of ensuring that nothing happens to him,
protects them, feeds us, gives us clothes,
knowledge, advice, cared
so that nature does not charge us,
then they are the ones who are pending all their lives,
but we are already entering the adult stage,
where life will depend on you.
Then they train us
of four days,
It depends on the consultation seven, eight days.
So it's a little strict
upon receiving support.
Usually
are
fasting, you have to fast
and stay up late,
not sleeping four nights in a row.
And there are people who have a strong spirit
and are able to resist and other young people
they can't do it,
they do not resist.
It means that that person is going to have a lot of conflict.
and will not be able to level things in life.
It's not
Sad, it's like proof that the mamos do.
It is not the mamos if it does not taste that of nature.
Personally when I
They did that ceremony for me, I didn't have a problem with that.
Already.
There were humans called
Mamo santos from xxxx
One of the wisest mamos,
important, one of the last ones rather and one of them
He was the one who gave me that initiation, very strict,
but I passed that test without any problem.
I mean,
late night fasting at night and late night fasting
Well, what's going on there? each night
long a wise
is teaching him,
He is teaching you the law of origin.
All creation begins from creation
and all night listen, listen
and
I did not have any problem.
And since this is good,
after I put that in, can you tell me
what is the creation belief?
What is the creation?
The creation?
Active.
May the younger brother
called
xxxx
or mythology,
but more than mythology
Xxxx it could be something
as belief
or something that is real or unreal,
but for us
It is the beginning of life, the beginning of life.
Everything has an explanation,
just as science manages to explain things.
Our science explains.
Let's say,
the mamos explain how it was created
the universe.
When they explain,
They explain in the following way, they say that
first, before existing
The material,
there was nothing, it was
water and night.
That's how it started.
But the water
The water was not as such as today,
but the spirit, that is, nothing.
That is, from nothing it began to be created
on the moon.
That is why the expression, the word
moon comes from that foundation
then there was no water,
There was no sun, no stars,
there were no plants.
First mother xxxx,
and father xxxx began to,
in spirit
to create everything that was going to be
the earth, the planet.
Who were our grandparents
before
the first spirits that
gave creation.
Then
they
They assigned the work to the children,
to father xxxx, to this one
He ordered him to organize the land,
That is why he was called the father of the earth,
Xxxx, father of life,
I say about living beings,
of the nature.
The father xxxx,
he ordered him
the law of origin.
That they will organize everything that is
spiritual mountains
with temples.
Order
the law
spiritual.
The xxxx father that is
of the most
powerful who dominates all wisdom
complete of the mother,
ordered him as
keep that wisdom,
organize well
and leave each code in nature.
Therefore, father xxxx
knows everything,
knows what the law of stone is like,
the law of people, the law of plants.
He knows,
We asked him what the law is like and he explained it to you.
how to take care of yourself, he explains.
That is what the law of origin is, rather
imagine it as if it were a book,
that his mother wrote to him
and they applied it just as the mother indicated.
That's why they are the creators,
likewise mothers, mother
What are they
Xxxx, what
it is the Earth,
the fertile land,
the task also of ordering so that
there would be life
And they talk about mothers,
They talk about nine mothers in colors of the earth,
white earth, reddish earth,
sandy land
and well, wisdom explains that each land
It has a function.
AND
which is more
valuable that gave life in was the black, fertile earth.
AND
in that creation
They were spirits,
people.
It has its narrative.
When parents xxxx
They asked him to organize the land with her,
the story says so xxxx because of the color
He didn't like it, I mean the black, black, but
He liked the white ones,
cute
So
the black earth,
the Pope, well, a spiritual being,
He picked it up and put it away.
in depths because I knew that after
work with the other earth colors
I was going to need it because the others
they had functions for certain
things, but they weren't
perfect for organizing the territory,
for life they were not perfect.
And when all that happened
he realized that
the black earth was necessary,
but it cost him a lot to be able to
bring him
and other spiritual beings,
how xxxx helped him rescue
from where I was through wisdom,
but we are talking about spiritual beings.
In this way the law of origin
or creation as they say,
explain, the mamo explain
and then dawn, there was no day
and when he was born there was Father Sol
xxxx
well the sun
of the night
and after that xxxx was born
which is now the sun,
was born here on earth.
And then
Mother
He placed it in the center
and that's when it's already dawn and when it's dawn
everything that had been created in spirit
materialized.
Then they would wonder
How so in spirit?
That's why we humans,
before
do recording work,
think first, feel, first
start to feel,
does not speak it, but in your
spirit begins to ask how am I going to do it?
When are they going to build a bridge
First start analyzing from the spirit,
not first speaking,
but it represents I'm going to do it like this,
You just know how the rest are going to do it
He doesn't know, you already manage to perfect
that spiritual construction,
So that's where you say I know how I'm going to do it.
and it turns out perfect.
Then you have
origin, that is why it is said that everything was created on the moon,
everything is built on the moon.
In Spanish it would be first in spirit
so that things turn out well,
build it first very well from luna
and if they don't build it very well from the moon
all things fail, problems.
and likewise, because these beings
They materialized
and at dawn
it already materializes
and arises
first beings that are already
xxxx but now humans
of being gods
to order again
in the material,
organize the forest
like the father of the forest xxxx,
build
What is the care of the forest like?
That's why
when we talk about care
of the forest we base ourselves on that principle,
because in that code it explains everything
and so
the first men lived,
I say beings that lived, they were the children of the mother
and they built mountains xxxx.
and
by completing the mission now for us
humans, no longer gods, but
For us, they already left for xxxx.
Is for this that I know
He says that in xxxx they are present
and they demonstrate before the mamos
for the little brother,
for the xxxx, for the xxxx for the xxxx for
the xxxx, for any race
This is the placenta of humanity in xxxx.
So
That's what creation is.
Therefore since the creation
parents taught us
How to manage your own calendar
how forest management is taught,
how the management of sacred sites is taught,
It was they who organized that wisdom.
Every thing
who will receive poporo them
They organized it and we applied it.
when it burns
they taught us
and therefore based on that
healing is done
so that it does not affect life, so that Mma does not charge us.
Support.
And likewise
the wisdom of the sea, xxxx.
So
that's why every thing
and let's say mamos, every little thing
that you ask them, they know,
there is nothing mom or say
I don't know what that's like, nothing,
It's like our Google,
Spiritual Google.
Mm
Mamo is like me
spiritual
and
who was born of such a father
and what is the place like?
It's called that, place of
ways of speaking,
which is located as
at the other side of
the saw.
Mamo, because he fucks and dresses in white
has his
explanation, because he poporo, has his explanation,
there is nothing that says
Oh, I don't know what that will be like.
What is a butterfly? Ay! I do not know
It's no longer mamo,
but
you know the explanation,
the explanation
from this.
And that's why we,
I have seen brothers who
when
the science that even if everything proves
It doesn't surpass that mamo explanation,
because it always points to the same thing
and the mom already knew it.
Are they also scientists?
They are scientists beyond teaching, that is why once
here in the mountains there is a mamo called xxxx,
they took him to
Europe.
There was a scientist, an astronomer, rather
he was a tenacious man
to, as they say, compete with mamo,
of stars,
and it turns out that there is one very star,
the smallest, but the most like in science
important.
So he
astronomer wanted to know if the mamo is so wise,
without making mistakes,
this is what i was looking for.
And it turns out that
xxxx
He arrived and began to speak the name of each star
and tells
This is the one you are testing me and this is what it is called,
Its function is like this.
can you talk about the importance of fire?
Everything was people.
In the beginning the fire was human
and continues to be so spiritually.
She is a person, she is a mother
or a father.
In the beginning,
in the very beginning
It was not fire, just like this,
It was a spirit, but no one needed fire
and they always rejected.
The first parents rejected fire
because he was a child,
like a reddish child
that
when his mother told him
that they had to take care of that child because he was going to become
in the greatest
of all of you,
then the beings said like this
that a child that I saw born is going to be wiser
that I.
Selfishness comes from there,
They said I am superior to him
and his mother told him to take care of him
because he will be your boss or he will be your mom,
and they said no, he was a child that they didn't want.
What does that mean?
That the mother knew that in our life
We were going to use fire all the time,
like ours, our mom.
Then the indigenous the xxxx, well
fire is so important that from the moment it is born,
born next
of the fire that gives him warmth,
the food, it doesn't matter if you burn yourself,
better said, he can't do anything, because
If you say I will never use fire again
because a son burned me or burned me, well after a while
They are already needing it.
The same with water.
And let's say you're crossing with your dad
and the water carried them away.
You can't fight with water
because no matter how much I fight,
You will always need water.
Then the fire too
It was the same from the beginning.
and
How did they see that it was going to be necessary?
then they organized the father xxxx,
parents organized
that
since that beginning
They saw that in the future it was going to be necessary.
Then they created wisdom for him
for management, how to care,
proper care,
but if it is poorly cared for it is dangerous.
The fire is obedient, no more
if you give order
does what you order.
It catches on there in the forest,
turn on and
ends everything,
but if you don't give it that order, it just stays there
Quiet here, it stays there, if you need it to make food, nothing else is done,
but if you throw yourself there you will burn too.
That's why
the first beings, the mother ordered him,
They created spiritual management,
so this
the father of fire
xxxx, a male being and xxxx,
xxxx
a stone that is reddish,
which is fire, with that it goes out
In nature,
because everything has fire,
then it is regulated
through those stones
so that they do not harm nature.
But the same power of the sun
can…
can sparkle
any rock has fire
and the forest can catch fire.
That's why we love them
through that stone, xxxx,
they do the work to refine.
When the job is not done well,
There is a lot of fire in the territory
and xxxx, whoever it is starts to burn, burn
the disaster begins,
Well, that's why you have to take care
through the stone in the place where the father is xxxx
and mother xxxx.
Yesterday we saw
in the sector we were in
the father of fire and told us
the mamo xxxx
AND
later xxxx or father of fire ,
through cane fields,
by xxxx is the mother,
Is called
mother
of fire.
That's also where it came
the first fire,
that's why there are reddish stones
that
They call her mom.
You have to go to
place, down,
to have positive fire.
So.
As we live in a hut in the middle of the fire,
then it is cared for and regulated that way and does not cause harm.
It is very easy for a hut to catch fire.
That is the importance of fire.
Fire is a central, essential element
of the indigenous people.
When we go to work in the field,
We carry fires to scare away animals,
snakes,
mosquitoes
We carry fire everywhere,
It is part of our life, our culture.
When we go to pop
we are around the fire
and that is why it is said that the xxxx without fire
it wouldn't be xxxx,
I wouldn't have life
and that is why it is like its sacred object
that keeps all the time.
Is there a fire there in the hut?
It's always on.
And how is it going?
They
they use let's say like a rag
old clothes that are a fabric like this,
they get old and
They twist it and form it like a ball
so they don't burn quickly.
Then they turn it on and
they take it
in the hand or put it in
a small clay pot .
He takes it.
If you didn't use the lighter before
which today is used of the younger brother
because it's already a firework,
a firework
that the territory does not, does not accept it.
We handle natural fire,
skins, a type of skin called xxxx
that are like, like
not as crystal, like salt, but solid,
which are stones that pick up and between stones
They make friction and sparks vote
There is a tree that we use as a lighter or candle
so instant,
a tree called
Xxxx,
is to take a stick
and another stick and start…
oh and put some cotton there
and when you do it like that for a while it sparks.
Those are fires
pure, fires that do no harm,
but they are strong games,
that you put whatever it is,
the hardest firewood and pulverizes it
fast and gives more heat.
and only those fires are the ones that must be put in the temple,
not with younger brother's fires, fuse.
That fire no longer has life
and that's why the color of the fire is like semi-yellowish
or white, because pure fires are
reds.
And where it's cold you catch yourself with that stick
and he lights the stick
and the heat remains,
spreads heat throughout the house area.
like the elders
They usually don't use blankets, just clothes
Even if it is in the wasteland, your only shelter
what gives him heat is
the fire.
Fire is everything, fire
avoid danger, illness,
danger of nature.
That's why the first thing you do
when he arrives at a hut, like this
that normal, any animal can easily enter,
snakes
The first thing one does is sweep and place fire,
and if there are snakes up there, the smoke scares them away.
Spiders.
Everything is scared.
When they go to cultivate in the mountains they always carry a brand,
It is placed and
The smoke scares away everything and thus fewer flies bite you.
Is,
It's like the xxxx repellent.
And also because the younger brother today's health
He says it's bad for your health.
but a part does,
but as everything is protected from the levels
spiritual so that it is not a disease.
That's why
they have lived with smoke all their lives
and for us it is not a disease.
It's like the body adapts to that and
does not contaminate us because we
We don't inhale it all the time,
or else we would have charred lungs
like cigarette smokers.
That is why spiritual work is done
so that it is not harmful.
AND
that is the importance of fire.
It is dangerous,
The way they handle it.
We have all our lives,
We have learned to handle fire.
that suddenly
in the middle of the hut in the center the fire, the children
when they fall asleep they can roll around, fall,
but we have already learned
How to prevent it from happening.
There are times that
yes there are accidents like that,
They have been burned, an aunt
or a small child falling to the ground, it has happened.
Yeah,
but sometimes.
We every month, every week,
from time to time that happens and when for us
fire does that
It is because there is spiritual debt that the fire is collecting
and if you don't organize that
the fire after
burn everything, your house, everything.
When it is done that no longer happens.
Well,
I want to ask you
like some quick things that we haven't talked about,
What is the meaning of the two peaks on the huts
or the shape of the house?
The earth
It's a round circle
but
It resembles a temple
and so
the explanation, wisdom says
I mean,
there are first mountains that the mother organized
and those first ones are called xxxx
and there are two peaks
that are seen there in the background, by that edge
In the morning you see each other, they are xxxx,
are two.
Similarity to that
is what is built,
a house is built with those two,
two
sticks, two pieces
or two antennas.
Because those mountains,
according to traditional science, ancestral science,
the mountain is not formed
from the mountain surface, but
from the heart of the earth.
Your foundation
It comes from the heart of the earth and it goes out and it rises
because most of the mountain is above ground.
They were formed on the earth.
Because?
Because these two mountains are the sanctuaries,
They are first, the first mountains that the Mother organized.
That's why when we go to build
and so
the mother did the same when
He began to organize the land to live on,
always when a circular house is going to be built
with a pita
to make the perfect circle,
always place in the center
a stick,
a stick
and then they hit the stick
a lasso, a rope with another stick
and extend like a compass to
make the circle
exactly where the posts will go.
Then the mother
When he was going to organize the land he did the same and located this
first, mountains,
that materialized in the mountains and that is why they are
there
those two.
So when the house of two is built,
that similarity is
that connects with space and connects
with the interior, with the mother,
It also means other things.
We have two eyes, two beings,
It means that too
and when they are made of two chunks
only in the town, in community they make two
and on farms you cannot build two,
but of one.
When we found a two-family farm there
It is because one is an important man,
for example, a xxxx
or a rich
who have a lot of wealth and are the ones who…
but in the mountains over there we find
normal people, a lot of people.
We do not say poor, no, because that does not exist
in our culture, that is,
only as people
who has a normal life.
There are few things,
but enough to live on.
Here wealth is not measured
for material things, but for spiritual wealth.
We have a wise man
who is an authority that has a lot of wisdom, but
Well, he doesn't have cattle or anything, but he is wise,
has the right to the house with
the chubs.
So, how
can you comment that the big house is the same house
So, the hut house is the same as the mountain?
The temple is what is most explained.
You enter xxxx
and look inside.
The structure,
It has a structure, I don't know if you have seen some sticks,
better said, intertwined and the mamos
He says that the inside of xxxx is like this
and it has nine circles above
representing nine planets
upwards
and spiritual, one
In the center of the temple there are two posts that support
that's what it represents
the two mountains that come from the heart of the earth,
holding this planet.
and
That's how they build the temple,
because it was
a spiritual decision.
Being a mother's son
saw how
It was the internal structure of Mother Earth
and from there he brought the teaching
and he didn't give it to us.
Lastly,
well we are talking about the mountains that
comes from the heart of the world, so I have heard
Well, all the peaks
seniors are connected all over the world,
can you explain that to me.
When he made the first mountain, the center
where he put the circle, where he put the mother
as the first mountain that connects with the center
and that is why in the temple it is explained that
things are placed, each thing
around the center, of the stick,
that represent position of each mountain
and everything is connected,
They are all tied together, they are all interconnected
and that is what gives the perfection of the temple.
So
mountains connect to each other
and if one looks at a planetary level,
mountains exist as the highest in the world
that connect.
and then the lower mountains.
So we start from the top with xxxx
the highest mountain
and then it starts to go lower, lower
and here ends this one called xxxx
bigger and finishes sooner,
when xxxx and xxxx had not been destroyed
that ends as a low mountain,
That's what connection is.
Is that connection
spiritual?
It's spiritual, it's spiritual
because the mother's design is perfect
and on the spiritual plane it is aligned,
They are already aligned,
I don't know if you've seen the spider web, imagine the spider web.
That is the fabric of the earth.
They are all connected woven very tightly, in a spiral shape.
And what happened in one place is accurate in the other place as well?
That's why
if we damage that mountain it affects it
Because they are connected below.
And explain why,
If it damages an organ, it affects the rest of the system,
the one that makes the body function.
Can you explain how very quickly
what's happening with Puerto Brisa and what is it?
When the creation was established
as from the ancestral territory,
mother design
for the four communities
and of all the things that are in nature
in a single space,
so everyone can do work
of everything on earth
or in the ancestral territory.
That's why there was a gap before.
immense,
a lagoon in the center
and it had rings of every species of plant.
We had a kind of palm,
that surrounded the lagoon and on the second level
a species of other vegetation and
so nine rings
I had that region,
and then birds, animals...
everything was concentrated there
And what does it mean?
Because there the mother integrated everything
and forces the four brothers to
perform work there collectively
so that the integrity is not lost,
It has to be united.
So what happened, since it was a source
principal of spiritual life,
when all this went bad
altered
the rest of the fabric from sacred sites
and species began to appear that the mother
left beyond the ancestral territory,
a bird, some black birds,
They began to enter the territory and eat others.
birds, to dig their nests,
a total disaster, illness,
new diseases
to the territory. It started to dry, when it happened
all the avocado dried ,
plague fell on him,
Well, it also has another explanation for the fumigation.
And well, the fumigation is great.
But
his spiritual destruction was there
and many species were disappearing.
The water began to go down,
the water level low.
That is, who made what and what is Puerto Brisa?
Well,
Puerto Brisa is a foreign company
Brazilian company that was located there as a strategic point
to transport coal from Cerrejón in La Guajira,
why the Port of Santa Marta is a bit long.
So
that's the closest point
to transport in trucks there
and transport to other countries.
So, for that reason,
because there were no other places on the beach like
with that
training to be a port,
then they burst,
Before it was a mountain, a single mountain that was formed there
and what they did was split that mountain in half
and damaged these lagoons
and they lasted months
throwing everything away
and
There it smelled like metal.
Everything, everything and it's over.
The four towns
They fought, but
nothing happened.