So, first of all.
What are they doing here?
Hey
Well, good night.
In the name of the xxxx
Here we meet every
every 20 or 15 days and
So we enter here,
Only women.
Only women
to talk,
for
weave,
to guide us.
Well,
talk to each other.
So everything,
every 20 or 15 days we meet.
And the time we last here,
Well, we lasted five days.
All night until midnight.
Concentrating.
Yeah,
because this is ours
job.
Because when Mother Earth was created,
Hey,
called Mother xxxx.
So when mother earth was created we
entrusted
to take care of mother earth.
And one of those things is that
Let's concentrate on knitting.
That's why when we pack the backpacks,
backpacks are made
of everything we think,
the backpack is woven.
Here when we are knitting we have to be thinking,
In other words, have positive thinking.
So that the backpack,
because we make the backpacks for our husbands,
for our parents.
So that's why we have to do
the backpacks thinking
well, have a positive thought,
so that those backpacks
The person who is going to have it will do well.
The backpacks
you see that
starts in a circle and
circle, circle,
does not have…
If you keep weaving it, it has no end.
That is not a closed circle,
but a continuous circle.
So this is how mother earth was created,
then the backpack is made the same way.
Yes, that's why it's in circles.
And here you see our
roof is made of circles
up and up
It ends in a point, but it ends in circles.
And the xxxx,
we are in circles
like mother earth.
Like the last time
I said that
We the women
We are like mother earth and mother earth the woman.
So,
That's why we're in circles.
Everything is a circle.
Yes and the backpacks,
This is the,
bone, there are three kinds of materials
to make backpacks, in fique or cotton,
bone two.
And the other is handmade thread ,
but not that one, that's what we sometimes do,
but the natural
It is fique and cotton,
That's our material
that we grow it here and here
we protect it ourselves.
Because now all of us xxxx are knitting,
one is just starting, others are
weaving, others are already finishing it.
For example,
There is one of the backpacks, you see it a little thick,
this is for work,
It is not for use, as I tell you,
for office use, but for field use,
to bring firewood, to bring shopping, to do...
not to
be burdened carrying bags with these backpacks.
So we do it
to use it for everything.
And those who are here are all of this?
community?
Yes, all the women of this community are here.
Each community has
her group of women,
Likewise, men have their own house
in xxxx
for them and this is the other one only for women.
What is your name?
The big house xxxx
xxxx .
And yes, that
circle, that is, does that also represent life a little?
Yeah,
Why we,
we have… yes, this
represents life, life
keep going, keep going, keep going
and after dying, well it also continues,
It has no end, we don't know where it ends.
So that's also why everything goes here in the backpack.
Yes.
many of the sacred sites here are called xxxx .
And that's also a word for women?
Can you talk a little more about that?
Are they similar or are they the same thing?
Sacred sites are called xxxx because that is what they are.
sacred, like us
women, we
women
We are very sacred, because all men and women too
They are sacred.
But it's more about women and those places
They represent, those sites are women too
They were women and
So that's why they call it xxxx .
xxxx what does it mean?
Mother,
mother, mom
So why do we
all women give life.
Yeah,
that's why it is.
Just like the places.
The places.
And something else
What do you want to share about this?
well, from the woman, from this place,
what is happening here now?
In the big house, no
well here all the time,
all…
Every time we meet we talk about different topics and
So today was, today was the night to do
the backpack for men, for those
at work. Another night another kind of backpack.
Yeah
and we put the backpacks
colors too, the colors of us naturals
It's black, red and... not red,
the orange, the black orange and the yellow.
What does it mean?
Yellow means joy.
The black,
black represents that when
before the world was created,
the world was dark.
There was no life in material ,
there were only spirits,
so that's why it represents black
And it also represents that sometimes we are positive
and negative. I mean, we think bad and we think good.
So that's why
The black and white.
But there is more white in the backpack
because we have to be more
good.
Good mind, positive mind and little black
because
Nor can it be everything, everything black and everything white.
And red represents life,
which is like blood, because if we don't have blood
there is no life.
Because when we,
when, when the mother created us
He created us through the earth,
then the blood, the red
represents the earth that is life.
And does that also have to do with the necklaces?
The necklaces that we carry around our necks,
that makes us see
different with men,
because they also have long hair,
then they carry a backpack
and we women necklaces.
and the white
represents the snowy, that the snowy is white
and thought
nice, positive thinking
and peace is white.
Is that too?
the dress?
He
clothing that we all carry
and they all have whites
and
already.
And we all have red necklaces
that represent life.
Why the mother too?
The mother is earth.
Can you tell us what your name is?
and where are we?
xxxx community
and well my name is Carmen
and my traditional name is xxxx .
So
here we are also talking about strengthening
our traditional names,
because many of us were changed
traditional names many years ago,
When the colonists came to civilization
they left us, they left us
banning traditional names.
So we were losing them, but now we are
again in recovery
of our traditions, traditional names.
Does your name have a meaning?
Every name has a meaning
and with the name given to the children
is he,
as I say,
with the name you already know
what he is going to be.
Yeah.
So how
They didn't know, they weren't prohibiting it, removing it, all that,
but we are already in recovery
our traditional names.
Likewise with the cotton fabric that was already
as
already finishing, that no one wanted to knit it.
No, it is already
forgetting to weave cotton,
but we are already
strengthening ourselves more in our traditional fabric,
which is with cotton.
Fique too, since it is a plant too?
If fique is a plant.
And lastly, I don't know if there is a message
What would you like to bring to the world of women?
Of course let's take care of nature.
that we take care
mother Earth,
because if we don't take care of mother earth,
because the mother,
We live on mother earth, if we don't take care of it,
Well, we are ending up in ourselves,
because mother earth,
there are the rivers, the plants,
the animals, the stones, the mountains.
Yes, because if we finish the mountains
The animals are running out, everything is over and so are we.
we're running out, so
that
let's take more care
the planet.
Last question
The thread, the xxxx I know has a great meaning
xxxx culture I don't know if
can talk about that a little bit.
I know that everything is connected in your tissues.
Yes, this is a xxxx ,
We tell him that, we tell him xxxx
xxxx .
And the cotton one
is
xxxx
everything is xxxx
then through xxxx
We are like mother earth.
It has xxxx too.
What are those xxxx ?
The rivers.
We women are also xxxx .
Yeah,
Because through one our body runs,
we have our veins
that's a xxxx too. So
we are connected
with, for example,
If we dry up a river or cover up a river, well, we are,
We are like blocking our veins, our arteries.
And then you don't have to cover a river,
because that is an xxxx , so that's how we are connected.
Those xxxx are imaginary, that suddenly one says
but where is the xxxx I don't see it.
But they are there, there are the rivers, the mountains,
the mountains you see like,
like it has a thread
well, that's a xxxx .
Very nice.
Nice, well, our roof, you see it
everything has is
tied by means of xxxx , by means of vines,
vines, everything is tied by means of vines,
those are xxxx .
So it's xxxx .
And everything is connected?
With xxxx
Armed with that.
Armed with the xxxx .
Well, thank you very much.