What I would like to do with Moselantja
is for us to live in peace
Peace means peaceful life within the family
Let us be people who live well in peace
My name is Matsele Selikane
I live at Ha Masupeli with my two grandchildren
Thabiso and Moselantja
Libraries are also traditionally a place of community
I also believe that we can
build community with a digital library
Thats one of the reasons
that we started working at schools
I anticipate that Solar Spell would reach
to all these populations in across Africa
Solar Spell Health Solar Spell education
Im anticipating having all the Solar Spell
libraries across Africa in remote areas particularly
The moment you come to
the demonstration on the Solar Spell
and how it works
and how you can access the books
you can even see the faces
and the smiles you see on the people
Its because they know that this
is what we have been waiting for
To them they know
this is what we have been waiting for
we want to have it