I'm going to ask you some questions so you can answer us.
First, can you tell us where we are now?
What is your name? And what is eirüku (family lineage) from here?
That is, the one of you who live here,
That you tell me the lineage of all those who live in this
community if they are Epinayú or other
It is not necessary that you tell me all but only yours
Ready? Yes, they are already recording
Here we are from various lineages, there are the Epieyú and
are the Uriana
Here there are also Pushainas like my partner
This is how we are constituted
my family is Uriana
I can't tell you that we are all Pushaina or Epieyú
because various lineages within the community
For example, there are Uriana children, our grandchildren are Epieyú
because we are already mixed
This is how our last names work as you tell them
What is the name of the community?
Neima
You haven't told us your name, could you tell us
Do I have to tell you my name?
Yes of course
My name is Torira. OK thanks
Be careful, you're going to knock down the enramada (traditional wayuu building)
Ok now what's next
You can explain the environment that there is like the sea, the moon
That is in its territory here
How is your territory constituted?
Can you tell us about what the territory is like?
For example, you have the sea, you have a canal
That is, everything related to its territory
Because we know that some live in the midst of
cardon cactus and there are none here
Can you say how the territory is constituted?
Over there is another context, we have the sea here, for example
Over there it is also pure sea
On the other hand, over there it is a mountain, because it is already another area
Only this small area in front has bushes.
What stories or stories do you know about the sea?
Tell us what you know or have heard about the sea
One of the things I've heard the most is that before and now
They don't want us to live here
By the municipal officials
As I told you last time, that has only generated unemployment
Because it is something that was not organized from the beginning
For example, there they tried to build a bridge, but it was left unfinished
As well as the roads that began to be built but were also abandoned
So, attempts have been made to build the roadways, but there are
disputes about it
That’s how it has been
Because they already know you and you have come here before
That's why they didn't give you a problem when entering and
record here
Because in these lands there is no planting or
alleys or anything
I would not have received you if you were someone else
But then I said, it's true he only came to
know what we are
Thank you very much grandmother for letting us record
If everything goes well with God's help more
later we will come with a bigger team
Those who work with films because
they are just students
But if everything goes well, we can come to
work and believe me I will take them into account
I will come whenever I can to visit them
So I thank you for allowing us to record and being here today.
Well, the last thing to complement the image of the territory,
lately there are some divisions marked by politics
local government
Has moved or has modified the territory somehow
There is the lagoon where we come from,
they have put a bridge at the entrance
She commented that this was very beautiful before, there was a lot of freedom
The sea entered there and surrounded you
You know that those who live near or in the
sea shore they call them Apaalanchi (caribbeans)
Instead, we who live in the north
We live by grazing animals such as goats or sheep.
You don't, you live from fishing for that
The question is, what is life like for a Caribbean?
We Caribbeans clearly live from fishing, some of
they practice swimming if they want
that's how it was before
Before, people did not use swimming goggles
They didn't use that, they just went into the water without any of that
We used to swim, play and have fun in the
sea when we were children
What we cannot do is to drink sea water,
because one used to fetch water on a donkey from the jagüey (lagoon)
because it would be a lie if I tell you that we drink potable water through pipelines, we drink dirty water
And we also cook with it, that's why we appreciate every
drop of water it doesn't matter if it's dirty
That's right, that's why water is so scarce and valuable.
It's true
Since I am Wayuu, I also know and I know that what you
consume is what you take from the sea
Those who record don't know that, could you tell them?
About what they eat and so on
You say it so that it is recorded on the camera
The animals of my ancestors grazed on
areas where there were grasses and bushes
On the other hand, since there’s only breeze in these times, the
animals have starved to death due to lack of grass
And to give the animals drink, they were taken to
where there was water in lakes
It was strange if they did not drink in a day, otherwise, there was enough to quench their thirst
The environment aided grazing before
Sure, when we had the animals before
That was also the life of the fishermen, they used to
fish a lot
And with that we ate a lot
Before we didn't eat rice, it would be a lie if I said yes
Before we ate fruits like iguaraya, pitahaya, tunas
We drank chicha from the fruits of the mokochira (guamacho, local plant)
In short, we ate the fruits of the plants
thanks to the rain
We ate honey, black plums and so on.
Well, and as for the fishermen when they go to sea
They know the days when they can fish, of course they do,
could you tell us about it
They know the days and the place where they can fish each time
It's the little I know because I'm not a fisherman who
they know it's them, like my partner
Well yes
They are also guided by a star at night according to
what they say
so they say
Well, that last talk about the language of the sea
The uncle is the one who has gotten into and known the sea the most,
unfortunately the water is not helping
And well, she talked about how they know that language
if it’s calmed, I think we should do
an interview with him, it's very good to know that
It is very good that you ask him the question of what is the
different between a caribbean and a sabanero (from the savannah)?
Grandma, how is an Apaalanchi (Caribbean) different from
of one that is not?
Practically, that they’re “the rich”. They live in a different way from the fisherman
It is different because the rich, as we say, are separated
Instead, the Apaalanchi is here like everyone
The man from the savannah has its animals in its own territory
Yes, thank you very much
However, that does not change anything in the traditions
No, it’s the same
It is the same in everything, just as when “la dote” (a ritual during marriage) is requested for
a woman is the same way nothing changes
If your old people have told you something
Surely they have told you that these necklaces were accepted
as surrender for bloodshed
Threads were accepted inside a totuma (traditional container) to
compensate the damage caused
By a person where compensation is required
for physical damage
Today that is no longer accepted
They want it in money, animals and jewelry. That's how it works
now then it has partly changed
Before, it was easier to resolve a conflict than now
They helped each other to reward the damage, some gave
even chickens for support
that's how it was before
Or also when a person comes to visit
They used to them something like meat
Yes, now they bring rice, corn and sugar if you can
I work there
And we feed on it, there are times when they bring the animal
alive if you wish to bring it yes
"So that they eat the guts" will say the one who brought it,
this is our way of living
It is the same with the fishermen who visit us
they bring a lot of fish
That's why he is given something for what he brings too
Yes, as a gift exchange
This is how friendships worked before
And what is her role here in her community and in her family?
ok another question
We already know what a Caribbean person does, such as fishing.
What do the Apaalanchi women do in this case?
She is dedicated to household chores such as looking for firewood to cook
There are some who dedicate to the art of weaving after
their chores
When resting or after looking for firewood
But, there are some women who no longer want to work on that
Women in the past were more engaged in weaving as
to make chinchorros (hammocks) and others
For example, I still make chinchorros
It's in there, if you want, record it too
Yes of course, now it is recorded for others to see
We who do not know what the life of the
Apaalanchi we do not know if women also fish
But you just told us that women
They stay at home and take care of the children.
Yes, but sometimes I go with those who fish
to be able to feed us
We help by cleaning and collecting the fish that they manage to catch
And before they fished for turtles, they would go away at night and bring it back.
So, we looked for the little ones to prepare it.
and so eat it
the big ones sold them. Now they sell them at high prices
because they are already scarce
Just as food has risen in price too
Yes that's how it is
Can you say something about
you know that there are fishing seasons according to the fishermen
There are days when there is very windy. How do you know
What are those days?
When they see the algae floating, they already know that the fish
they are not that deep
Because that is what the fish feed on and they are easier to fish
But, when almost nothing is caught, it is because they do not have
The fish are hungry according to the fishermen
What changes have you seen in your eyesight in nature, with
with respect to the sea or the lagoon
one more question
How was the ease when fishing before?
When you were little, was there an abundance of fish?
or is it the same as now?
It's almost the same as now, well yes
Well I have also heard a tale from the old
They said that before the sea had many fish and now
there is almost no more
Yes, they fish, but they are very small.
And the spirituality of your way of living with the sea, what is it?
Grandma, you know that everything has a
spiritual connotation
There is a spirituality behind, for example, when hunting
much to the rabbit nature manifests itself
What is the spiritual connotation that the sea has?
The sea feeds on people too, several have already died
people in the
There is a supernatural being in the sea that feeds people,
we say Pulowi, maybe the arijunas (not indigenous people) call it different
For us it is a supernatural being
Who feeds on people, makes them seriously ill until they die
This is how delicate is the spiritual connotation of the sea
Have you dreamed or have you seen this phenomenon?
If I have dreamed about it, I see it in my dreams with a giant tail
And there are many types of phenomena that appear at night
They would appear there when that little house was not there,
there was only us
There was no one like now, there was only us
for years
There was only one of my daughters from the beginning, with her husband
who worked with shrimp
Until I told my husband to stay here
because we worked with shrimp
We can't be suffering at midnight, I told my old man
I fished at midnight with my old man and I ended up sleepy,
I even fell asleep on the way
I would get up when I bumped into something on the
road to the sea
And since then, we stayed living here
to avoid suffering too much, and here we are
Yes, it is true, when we want to live well it is necessary to move
For example, my father was from the savannah
And he came to work with salt, since then he has
grown old here
And looking for a better quality of life
Yes, of course, he wanted to try his luck elsewhere and it went well.
that's how we did
They may even have animals, but no one (wants to)put them down
in the midst of so many needs
Even so, they sacrifice them to sell them and
be able to buy food
It is the same with fishing because we eat through it.
That was before when everyone had their animals
That's right, your words are very consistent
She responded very accurately to tell the truth.
I don't know if you have a message you want to give to the world
Well grandma, to finish now
The good thing about these cameras is that whatever you say
will be recorded
When they finish, it is shown to them so that you can see it yourself.
So, what you say will be recorded so the children
of now and those of the future generation see it
what I want to say with this is that you give a message
for you to see and hear later
Yes, it would be like talking to them in the future
Can you tell us what those words would be for the children?
You can say, for example, that they value culture and
don't be ashamed of it, as well as some advice
for the new generation
Of course I'm going to tell you
Yes, but, you can say it here so that it is recorded
Kids these days are a bit rebellious
But it is up to them to remember and maintain what we are,
remember their grandparents
Remember their grandmothers and think about what we do for them now
It is up to them to remember our words when they are adults
They are the ones who should reflect on the future if
they want to do it for us
These here are my grandchildren, I have other young grandchildren
but they are in Manaure
There they are so they can study
I'm the only one that stays here
It is true what you say
The message is also for you, you must remember our culture
how you came to me, you must remember me later and visit me from time to time
Bring me coffee, or whatever the arijunas send to whom
the breeze moves their hair for being here
That in fact I am glad that they see that my
Enramada (traditional wayuu building) is made of rag
And sadly I don't have chicha now to
show you and explain you that that's our drink
Made from corn
But there is no water son, there is a lot of drought
We suffer a lot from the lack of drinking water
that's how it is everywhere
Not even in town they have water, over here we have even less
Yes it's true, my children who are in town sometimes
have to ask their neighbors for water in a jar
So what you say is very true, that's everywhere
That is why it is good to record the true reality of
you because that
That puts in trouble those who work in the mayor's office
Because they say in front of others that you don't
have needs
That is true
That's why it's good to record your words because when
it is made public they scold the municipal administration
And they track them, so we have to show how
we live without shame
and without fear
So thank you grandma
And believe me that I will return with Fray because we will not
we will forget about you
We will keep them in mind, in fact, what we record at the same time
past we are still working on it
we are still editing
So thank you very much for sharing with the arijunas
And for saying it in front of the cameras. Now let's
do another interview.