grandpa, tell us about people
Caribbean
This is our fishing area, right here
We have brought our children
That's why we've gotten used to this
And not what the arijunas (those who are not wayuu) work on.
This has been the profession of our fathers and of
Our grandparents
This is where they have always fished
Here
When there is a lot of wind the breeze pushes the insects
From the mountain to the sea
So, it's easier to catch the sardines as they say
the arijunas and that is what we eat in summer times.
Our father Juya (rain) has not arrived here,
Our grandfather
For this reason, we have lived from fishing
and not what the arijunas work on
This has been our job.
We don't know what it is to steal
Because our parents didn't teach us that.
They only fed us what they caught and it is
What we have learned since then
One question, what is the wealth of a Caribbean?
Their wealth is their craft
What you earn from their job
Because with that they buy the boat, the cast net
If he wants to have animals, buy goats and
He has them in another territory
Far from the sea Thus, his animals are there and he is here.
This is how things should be
On that stick over there and the one over there
animals go straight
there and there
They do not go beyond that point, but they feed here
Months or years can go by, the animals always
get to that point in the day
Even at night, when the
stars come out, that's their sign
They always know the area where they are going to eat
They are guided by the sound of the sea to locate themselves in the area
This is how they do at night
Another thing I wanted to ask is if
In summer times there are usually many fish or not?
No, only at those times of the day when
that there is not so much wind
There are days when the tides are still and so on.
And as for the months
Are there months in which there is an abundance of fish?
Yes, they last for months because they have their habitat here
In April there are usually no fish
Yes, because those who are dedicated to this know the months
In which there are fish and in which there are none
where there are no fish
Yes of course, in April as he says,
The wind is very good for fishing
The wind comes from the southwest and pushes the boats there
Little by little into the sea
Yes, that’s good, thank you very much, another question
You know that in our culture everything has
a spiritual connotation
those of us who live in the mountains when we hunt the
rabbit it is necessary to take into account that there are some spirits
If we hunt him frequently, those spirits get angry
Does the same thing happen with the sea?
Well, they say that when a person fishes
Frequently from the sea many fish appear
While for others the fish go to the bottom
It is a spirit that is attracting him,
that's why he gives it only to him
And then it makes him sick
It comes in a woman's body
He tells him "come on, let's go there" and when he is convinced
He feeds him something to put a spell on him
And with that he gets used to her.
I have heard the story of a guy
That when they see that the waves move too much
they chewed jawapi (medicinal plant)
Why did they do that?
No, it's alouka (malambo) it's for it to leave him alone
so that the spirit is happy
It is happy if they bring it something, they throw it into the sea
And you have to ask it to give you fish and that's it.
It's true, that's the spiritual connotation it has.
That's why you shouldn't rush to fish just for the sake of fishing
Because if you do, you lose.
And so it goes, if when moving a goat
is not sacrificed for the arrival
It can be damaged by a nail or zinc.
Yes, everything has a ritual
It has a spiritual connotation, yes.
To maintain harmony, right?
Yes of course, to brighten up the territory
Brighten the Earth.
If you’re moving, you must do “la comelona” (a big feast)
to harmonize coexistence as well
Another thing, I mean, another question
Was there more fish before or is it the same as now?
no, there are fewer now
Tell us about it so it's recorded on camera
There are no longer as many fish as before, that's why there is little fishing now
If we fish, we return with little
As it is little, you gain almost nothing with it,
barely enough for food
Also, there are a lot of people fishing nowadays.
Also, the new boats with
Johnson motors make a lot of noise
That noise makes the fish scatter,
Yes it's correct.