Well.
Can you explain to me what the project is that you're setting up here?
That you're setting up here?
Well, we have a project.
We have a store.
They call it xxx.
xxx is...
Well.
This project is called "Threads for xxx" (Má).
And this project
involves fabrics, backpacks, various kinds of backpacks.
And well, where we are right now,
this is where the people live
that we partner with to do
this project
which is about, which is about the backpack,
we do an exchange
of recycling and all that it involves.
And well,
we do this for the good of our community,
a cleanup.
And that's why it says "Threads for xxx."
It's for the good of
our community, our land.
And here, you can see a lot of
this,
the pollution that
is very common in La Guajira,
and that's why we are working on
that, on this project,
and well, we are happy.
What is pollution, what kind of pollution?
Well, when we talk about pollution,
it's related to garbage,
with papers, everything related to consumerism,
and that
and well, we're trying to collect all of that and
to do an exchange, as I was saying, as I mentioned earlier.
What is the thread made of?
The thread...
Like, I mean, what is it? How did it come about?
Yes, the thread. I mean, are you using plastic to create the thread?
And that's like cleaning it up, helping in that aspect?
Yes, helping like...
As you were saying, it helps our community,
As you mentioned,
it helps our community in a way,
because we, the Wayuu people,
it's like, let's say,
well, since here in the ranchería
is already full of garbage and all that,
so, to improve a bit of this, a bit of that,
that's why this project was born.
and precisely to help our family
and all our relatives.
That's why this project is here.
Yes, so, tell me about your work here.
What do you do with the jewelry?
How do you manage them? Or
What threads do you use? What fabrics?
Well, on our side, my mom and I,
we always use wool.
The question is not... here we use wool.
We make things like this,
like plastic that is collected,
they are taken to the cleaning stations in Manaure,
and as for cardboard and other reusable materials,
the recycling center, they give some coins for it,
so they work on it,
but we don't dye with plastic or anything like that.
And what designs?
What things do you make here or what kind of backpacks?
Yes, backpacks, and also chinchorros.
And
the backpacks, they have a
color, some of them have
what they call "beds," which have various colors,
my mom is showing them.
It's very beautiful.
These are the backpacks,
and well, as for the question, how is my work here?
Yes, so what do you do?
What are the symbols?
The symbols,
Here, there are various types of weaving.
And well, as my brother said,
That's why my work is related to this.
That's why I don't know much...
And he is the one in charge of everything when he goes to the town.
that's it, well, and my duty here
is to take care of the people,
how many backpacks we deliver,
this,
And well,
and as I was saying, there are various kinds of backpacks,
many times in xxx, there's one they call,
well, the ones with multiple colors are the basket-like ones.
And there's one that's called xxx here,
there's a type of weaving called xxx,
in xxx,
it's not this one, it's very, very different from this.
And how did you learn to weave?
Weaving, like
what weaving has to do with our ancestors,
you learn from a young age because here, everyone knows how to weave.
We are all taught, as we are Wayuu, and it's one of the things
one of the most important things in our culture
and that's why, as Wayuu,
we have to know that.
That's why I learned to weave since I was a child.
Watching your mom?
My mom and my grandmother
and all the other relatives
and so on.
And what importance does weaving have in the culture?
It is very important because
there's a narration that my grandmother used to tell,
that in the past, before,
one day,
there was a girl,
about how weaving was born,
that's what I'm going to talk about now, how it was born,
there was a girl,
her name was xxx,
And well,
that girl was,
she was like she was lost, she had no family,
And one day, a boy
came out, he was shepherding
and he found that girl.
And he asked her where she came from,
but the girl didn't speak,
and she was young.
And well, he took her to his house,
he took her there, but they didn't know who her family was,
and then,
time passed, and the girl stayed
in the boy's house with his family.
She had been there, and at night,
at night, she would make chimchorros, but no one knew about it,
that was a secret,
and she would make chimchorros
and also
she also made backpacks, but on her own, just by herself
And no one could know about it
And people were surprised
in the morning
They saw that, and where did that come from?
And since she didn't speak, she just kept looking,
and that went on, time passed,
and she made many things,
the hammocks,
and then, until one day,
the boy,
the girl had grown up,
she had become a young lady right there, and they locked her up
And she still did that
And well, until one day, the boy
who didn't mean to, entered the house
and found her doing that, and no one could see her,
And well, she disappeared.
Because she's not a normal girl, so to speak,
and that's how it was born,
that's how it remained for us,
the Wayuu people,
and it's one of the things, one of the customs,
most important
in our culture.
And does it have something to do with the spiderweb they also weave?
Oh yes, the spiderweb
also, because spiderweb
in Spanish is "telaraña," in Wayuu it's "xxx"
It's the same in words, in Wayuu it's "xxx"
and that.
And do you learn from them too?
Yes, of course.
That's why today you can see what weaving is,
thanks to her.
to the spiderweb.
How many hours a day to create one?
One backpack,
The smallest one,
My grandmother is very fast because I am a bit slow,
sometimes it takes me two days for one backpack,
My grandmother sometimes makes two backpacks a day.
Well,
the big ones like that last a day, the small ones
you make two
backpacks a day, as I was saying,
And well, here I also have a little nephew
who also makes the xxx
What is it?
The handle of the backpack
He also knows how to make it, that one.
And does he do it there?
Yes, and that's in progress.
And the designs, where
do you get inspiration for the designs?
Inspiration has to do with nature,
For example,
like the clouds,
like the water, which is blue,
That's why many are inspired by that,
and the red color of blood.
Can you tell me the name of,
the meaning, the significance
of the name
of the store and the project and all that?
Xxx, aha, xxx,
What does it mean?
And what does it have to do with?
Well, xxx
means
What does that word mean?
Well,
that has to do with
with the red color,
which is the color of blood, that identifies us
many times, especially in our culture,
that blood is important,
and that's why we put it there,
it represents the red color
xxx. Yes.
Can you once again
talk a little more about the inspiration
from nature in the textiles,
how does it come out?
How is that?
In the textiles?
Well, when it comes to
nature, as I was saying,
the water,
also these,
the cardones, also
there are many types of plants
that sometimes one
also
the clouds,
that is also one of the inspirations, and that's why
we also incorporate it into the weaving
in this,
does this backpack
have inspirations from symbols
that have some meaning?
Trash bins.
And the learning of it,
at what age do they start weaving
in each
community, in each family too?
At what age?
At seven or eight years old,
they
are taught,
but girls also, sometimes,
if they want to learn, they start at five years old.
they start like that, and boys too,
even boys know how to weave.
Not just women? No
Yes, even boys and also older people, even men.
Most of them, everyone knows how to weave.
And is it something traditional, traditional here? Yes
Yes,
because here the backpacks
here,
we have a great need,
craftsmanship related to weaving
is what, as I told you,
it's what
because sometimes we make backpacks, right,
We take around 20, 25 of them to the town
and we sell them
and buy more thread and
We also buy things for consumption.
That's why it's very important,
because we depend on that,
since there is no work here.
That's why we depend on the trade
of backpacks, hammocks, and all handicrafts.
That's why it's very important,
that's why men also start to
make backpacks.
Do you feel connected to your roots
when you do this? Do you feel
connected to your roots while weaving?
Yes, yes, we are happy,
and beyond, outside of
Colombia, they recognize us more because of this
and that's why we are very proud to be Wayuu
and we will never stop weaving.
We will always weave for the new generation.
Always,
our tradition will always continue.
And that's it.
Are these backpacks famous throughout Colombia?
Yes, outside of Colombia, they are known all over the world.
And is this the emblematic one of the Wayuu, this one?
Well, yes, this one represents the Wayuu,
what the weaving is.
Yes, I've seen it all over the world.
Also, all over Colombia.
Also, another question. Can you explain to me what "Xxx" is?
Xxx?
Earth,
Sand, "Xxx."
It's earth, "Xxx": land.
And what does it mean to you?
"Threads for Xxx."
It's thread for our land,
and our land is
what is here.
That's why, because of our land,
we are working.
That means for our land.
For our land,
this project was born.
For how to take better care of it,
for the environment,
taking care of our surroundings.
And that's it.
Nothing more.
Is it related, like all of this art,
and craftsmanship,
and the threads for xxx?
Threads
For xxx,
it's the thread related to craftsmanship.
And that's why
the weaving,
and that's why, as the thread forms.
And it has to do with craftsmanship,
and that's why everything is very important.
Can you tell me your name and where you're from?
My name.
My name is Ana, they call me Ana,
but my full name is Ana Luisa,
my clan is xxx
and well, I am from here.
Over there where we were just now, that's my home
in the community xxx
and well, my family lives here.
Well, how do you identify yourself?
Or what things do you do?
Wayuu Taype, I am Wayuu
Xxx xxx
Well, I am saying that I am Wayuu.
and I am here in my land.
and I don't let our tradition fade away,
just as our ancestors left it for us
and also the new generation.
And here we are.
And what do you do?
I do weaving, and we also make hammocks,
That's the only thing I do this year, like this year
I'm not studying,
but next year, I will go to school.
That's why I dedicate myself only to making backpacks
and also helping my brother.
I also want to ask you, like,
what is your connection
with the natural world, with nature,
personally how do you connect with that,
how do you relate to the natural world?
The natural world
To nature.
Well,
I like the sounds of the little birds
and listening to them every morning and also in the evening,
because they sing twice
in the morning when they wake up
and in the night when they go to sleep.
And well, I like that
and also,
how
do I connect?
And as I tell you, that's it.
Alright, that.
That's what I can say.
Well, in everything you do,
I suppose you connect a bit
with nature.
Yes.
In the weaving too, grinding the
Corn.
Well, yes.
If there's anything else you'd like to share,
any message you could bring to the world.
Well, we all here wish that
you support us with this project and
I wish that this project
can be more recognized outside Colombia
that it grows more,
that people from outside can come
to see our project and
that we don't stay behind so they can know us more.
That's the message.
And what would be your
ultimate goal, your goal for the entire project?
Is that what you just told me, or how?
Our goal is,
as,
to see this grow,
and that we can,
grow this and thus we can all work,
have resources,
because as we are just starting,
as I say,
due to lack of resources,
many times it's that, many times
we stay like this,
but here, here we are, here it is, and here we continue.
What are the
challenges you face here?
The challenges?
Issues
that arise in our work?
Work, yes,
day to day, as part of our routine,
but also in the work, well generally here
Well, the need we face
is the lack of water,
Because, I mean,
where my house is, in the community,
we don't have water nearby
to say, only the xxx
because the water we drink is from another community that is our family's
but it's from another community
and that's what we face daily,
lack of water, and
what else?
As for grazing,
Like what,
what things or what things?
As I was saying, the water