Hello, how are your souls?
Thank you for opening this space to listen to us
My name is Karla.
Greetings to you, my name is Karla,
I belong to the school
for approximately nine years.
My role at school
Well, be a woman, a trainer .
I'm a dancer, too
I sing the Jayeechi which is one of our traditional songs and then I take care of it.
I am also in charge of teaching
everything related to our culture, principles and values.
My name is Veruzka Henriquez
Acosta,
Wayúu Pushaina (family lineage)
a craftsman ,
knowing
I am part of the
from the Saüyeepia Wayuu school
approximately ago
ten years
and we are in charge of multiplying knowledge,
not to rescue, but to strengthen
Our culture.
Good morning, my name is Anyelin
Daughter of the Jayariyu
I belong to the school
Saüyeepia
Inside Sauyeepia School
My role is to dance
Good morning,
My name is Katiuska Yamileth Jiménez Fajardo.
I'm here,
I'm here with this
learning to dance
Yonna, listen to this
and know everything
is heard belonging to
what is called
The Sauyeepia School
That.
Is.
Well , well. and for you
which? Well, what did we just see in the dance?
Can you explain to me ?
What what happened ? _
What were they doing in the dance, the steps
and the significance it has?
Well, our traditional dance,
Well, since long ago,
Since ancient times it has had some main variants.
which are called pachikuata and Pa'tawa , which
Well, it was what we danced at the beginning.
AHA
Our steps are closely related to nature,
in fact there we take like birds, for example, in
the one who is crouched
is called
Tortolita is one of the traditional birds typical of here
We also take into account traditional games.
There is also, for example, the tro mpo , which is the one danced
going around and around , that one too. The one we dance
g represents the Samutkuaya (Zamuro)
in fact the one who is here,
the little black one, well that's the one we were imitating.
We imitate all the birds
in everything related to nature, the cloud, the wind.
That's more or less ours .
meanings .
Does anyone else want to talk ?
Well
And you, what is the connection you have when you are dancing?
Good with your spirituality
nature or with the boy too?
How do they feel ?
What is the experience like?
So
The most beautiful thing is that we enter a kind of
a harmonization.
Both in the Piyoi (dance space)
the ground, his elo, the circle and with the people around us.
But Yonna, more than anything, we do it for pleasure,
for pleasure, oneself,
because
As you can see, not all of us Wayuu do it .
I mean, lately we are losing it
thanks to the fact that they exist
centers
like the teacher's, like Saüyeepia , where , for.
Where
They strengthen and we try to
to give it,
make known and that other young people
strengthen.
that part.
Or also like
helps us,
as well as to also highlight
those values that we have here,
that for example that of harmony
be at these events and start with a
Yonna is like starting to liven up the meeting.
I mean,
That must be
the main thing,
It should not be left last, it should not be left in the middle . C on
That is what it begins , at the touch of the Kasha (drum) .
It's like someone who says the notice says now, the event is going to start.
Come here, get together, cheer up.
That's like the sign.
So just one
listen to sound,
Now the women get ready and say “I want to dance . ”
I mean,
It's not like they force you
But women say I want to dance ,
that you feel it, exactly like something that moves you.
And that too.
What is the role of women?
I see that the woman is going
controlling, exactly if
because it is not a competition but as a whole.
The man and the woman, but the woman there
It is the fundamental basis, because
the two, the two people, both the man and the woman,
Well, they are like giving,
showing his skill, showing his strength.
The man dances backwards,
He doesn't look even though we are going straight , I mean.
there is no advantage.
Honestly, we're on the same level,
but the women there in that case are the ones that show the most
the force
because the faster it goes
has the possibility of knocking him down,
thus showing worth and strength.
Sometimes yes
came at the moment of knocking down a man at the dance,
He says no, that girl is strong,
that family must be well prepared,
If you should have that woman,
then they start looking too.
The man If they see that it lasts a lot, as in the case of
Conraditus
He danced with all of us, then he danced again.
Then he says no,
that boy
He is strong, he already knows , he already has experience, he dances, he likes it,
So
are those little things that really
It makes everything wonderful.
And that has a relationship too.
to the Wayuu culture , bone
the role of women is something similar
to dancing, it's like that too.
Women are very important in our culture.
As I said at the beginning,
we are all who are
here, we are women trainers,
although we are not mothers, although we are not grandmothers or anything,
but for the simple fact of being in a family
be in our territory,
We are transmitting our knowledge to girls,
children. In these moments here
Well, we now reveal something of what we know
and that makes us a woman
Trained ra.
all the knowledge that a woman has is very sacred
and they are
spiritually as connected with
with everything that surrounds us.
In fact, dance also has a
a spiritual connotation, because when dancing
barefoot because we relate to our Mother
Earth (mma) then that helps us
also
how to connect with the dreams that we are going to have that day
to harmonize our territory
so that we have good dreams, good omens, as they say
How did you feel at the dance ?
Jaashaja jumala
talk girls
Well,
dance for me has a meaning,
because when we dance
we feel like dancing with
freedom, with joy,
with love, so because it is our culture,
we feel that we are free to express ourselves
in that way, dancing with our partner.
That's what we have done, we women
wayuu, dance, because Yoona has a lot of meaning,
because it is very, very used in various events
on several occasions, such as the departure of a Majayut (young woman) ,
like a confinement
and many things.
That's why we have Yonna
present at any time,
because it is something that represents us
to us Wayuu women and it is the Yonna
Yes, they also asked me that, when did he introduce himself to
the dance ? Here it is for this event, but traditionally when? .
By rituals , by rituals,
by dream, in hills
or the departure of a Majayut (newly young lady) .
And what is Majayut?
A, just, a just young lady
what, what was J imolü (girl)
When she develops, they lock her up and when she comes out
She is practically a young lady who is already forming
and then be a good person.
That is a ritual too , a ritual
what is done to the new ladies
and the Yonna is done
when it's going to come out, when it's going
make yourself known as a new woman,
because she is no longer a girl, she is going to be a woman, then
This ritual is performed and it is also accompanied by food,
drink, like a party, as they say,
but more than anything it is for that.
also been like a celebration
Yes, it's also like a celebration.
Yes, because when they dance they begin to say well,
look, a lady is going to come out, a woman and the men
they are always too
as if waiting to see who that new lady is
Who is that new lady?
And that ritual also works , it's good to dance the Yonna in the middle of that ritual
It's like driving away bad spirits,
As if to say we already danced, we already ate,
Those spirits are already happy
and they are full
They are going to leave this new lady alone
so that your process lives .
And they are made for that too.
If a dream does not ask you to do a dance at that time
such a lady must dance, put on this costume,
one does it to get away precisely
those bad spirits, diseases and so on.
And how long does this confinement last?
It's the lockdown
In itself , it lasts during the days of menstruation, but
After her menstruation she has to remain locked up
approximately a month and a half or two months.
It depends on the family,
It depends on your grandmother or the person or woman
who is accompanying her.
And where is the bull run ?
In a mud house
when the girl has her first menstruation
He tells his mother, months before they will have chosen
a woman who will be accompanying her ,
He will be instructing her, he will be guiding her,
saying and teaching the values, everything
related to knitting, for example.
Then she will be locked in a mud house
which is like that always.
It's always secluded, it's a new little house, in fact,
They prepare her, let's suppose, she is just a young lady,
not long ago
has already been developed
when she developed before she developed
Sorry, obviously between the family
We get together and say well, the girl is growing up,
Your new stage is already approaching,
So we have to prepare everything.
Then a new house is ordered to be built and it is bought
everything absolutely new because it is going to be a stage
And the old is given away
What if which one is it?
What are the
women's jobs or women's roles
on a day to day basis ? .
There are five fixed jobs as such, there is that of the Outsü
which is the, practically the pillar of the Wayuu territory
within our culture
is the
O ulaküt the visionary,
there is the woman E´inalü
What is she, the artisan ? there is the woman, the ceramist
and finally there is the woman
trainer that in this case well there are all of us included ,
Those are the five fundamental jobs
And within those five, the others are already released.
For example, dance comes from being a female trainer.
And they want to share something more
that I had not asked them.
I don't know what you want to ask
who want to know more.
From a woman's everyday day.
wayuu
What is an E´inalü woman like?
In that of an artisan , for example.
She can share with you because she is an artisan.
Well, like all roles
which like all roles, is also very important
harmonization at the moment
to knit because we knit
For pleasure, not all of us knit .
Suddenly,
At a time of confinement, they instill a lot of craftsmanship in us,
but it goes in one as a woman or as a lady.
well, I am a life-forming mother
and
I don't
pay attention to the fabric at the time of my development.
I liked it years later ,
already at 15 years old
I started knitting since
There I consider myself an artisan because I have been
1 0 years in this profession
when knitting,
let's say it the way it is explained
It's something nice because, because one enters into harmonization so much that if
we are going to give him a relationship,
We can give it like at the time of gestation of a baby because
just as the fetus grows inside our womb,
that is, it is the same, as it is done in the backpack
it is growing, little by little
They give him love and care
and we give
and we try to ensure that it does not have a deformity,
that I don't have,
that is, one wants it to be perfect ,
the same with the baby
and when it comes out it is
when comes
the feeling of
of gratitude, of satisfaction,
because already
It's something beautiful, something I can't explain
It is true and so are all
all roles
or all our roles are like that, everything has one , that is,
how you will feel very spiritual, something that, as they say, is very
Exactly, it's very difficult to explain
I mean one feels it.
And when you see, for example, an artisan,
Well, one already interprets everything
without needing her to explain to me
already knows that she is a mother
For this reason we do not explain with our mouths but with our hands.
And the designs, the dance.
Also the dance.
Just by starting to do
The different variants say “ah it's such a bird”
without needing to tell one
And that's what they have on their face
Can you explain to me what it is? why does he do it? that
What significance does it have ? What symbol ?
Well this is achepa (makeup) it is one of
Our traditional makeup
can be done in different ways
ways, it also has different uses
also depending on the occasion.
Right now,
how this is a meeting
and how we did the harmonization.
Well, we design.
This means the sun,
we draw the sun,
taking advantage of the fact that the sun is hot today,
So we capture all that, everything.
As I said, nature
It is in us, that is like our life too
I mean because
We left our Mother Earth, as we say,
so everything is connected with us.
So today we played the Sun
and it can, we can, even those who are in the kitchen.
I don't know if we can see it today, because we cover our entire face.
with another who is paip ai
or it can be with mmeera , which are mushrooms.
For example.
This is a plant, it is called Pa li'ila
One has to wait for it to fall, for it to set
Red, she has her bone preparation, everything is a process,
and the one we have is already prepared,
It is simply starting to add water in this case,
but usually traditionally
It is with white sheep's bo
is with sebo .
He knew too
It is another process in which they prepare the tallow, strain it
it is white, white,
whitey is not just any sheep,
It doesn't have to be a small sheep either.
Newly
then they start preparing it
and then one has it stored there
and when we are going to use it, we apply the tallow
and then we apply the p aipai
Yes, yes it is for
as a blocker, if we are going to look for firewood, if we are going to cook
so that our faces don't burn ,
so that it doesn't get stained . In this case, since it is a ritual,
as we are in harmonization and it is a meeting
We say mi'ira, then we have
the agility to capture what we want
like makeup for different occasions,
Not then, for an event, a soft makeup
that for a recording it is already something better ,
It's almost like that
And that spiral too
It also has a meaning , because the dance is spiral, Yes.
Everything in our culture, everything being, everything
It is based on the spiral,
because in our life after dying,
We are going to Jeepira as we say,
already have like another life in the afterlife.
So it's not like suddenly by scale, like suddenly
in that of Westerners,
which is by stairs , until it reaches the last
Ours is a spiral because we don't know where it ends,
because one travels the path of life in a spiral
and come back again for the same
what is Jeepira
Can you explain me
What was the ritual he did?
with smoke and wood? and why did he do that?
AND
That is an incense, it is not witchcraft,
It is not witchcraft, it is our incense, as it is a harmonization
Well, we are pushing away the bad energies.
It's very good too
to ward off those diseases like the plague
In fact, I have it posted here too.
This is not wood, it is white bija,
It is a plant that
It is widely used for general ailments.
in fact during Covid
This is what helped us a lot,
a lot, as a territory
wayuu, was what we could say,
which saved the lives of many Wayuu .
So,
So what I did was
a kind of incense, because we make it akai'ja
to move away
those bad energies and make this meeting a good one
fruitful and for also, since later
do not come
pests, taking into account that nowadays we see them ,
Virus variants ,
what is affecting many Wayuu children
That's why it helps us a lot.
And to start the dance too.
Exactly, to also just start the dance.
That is why some elderly
breathe freely.
Well, well, the video too,
That's how it can be explained.
Well we've seen a lot of red
and it has a meaning also in the culture for you is
women, for the wayuu
yes of course,
the Red color
It is one of our most representative colors.
It means for us purity, love, peace.
But it also means blood
It also has, it has like
one meaning
positive, so to speak,
but at the same time something like negative because the blood for us
It is very valuable, it is sacred .
In fact, if we suppose at this moment
there is a conflict and a person is affected
and his blood is spilled, because everyone says no, now
That is a problem,
Then we have to solve it because blood was shed ,
so the blood here in that
meaning of
which is very sacred,
You don't play with it , even with the animal's blood.
if it is by ritual or if it is by dream.
There are times
in which it should be allowed to spill
and there are times or occasions in which it is consumed.
Does not consume it
Neither are men generally consumed either,
so
and like everything, also what we have
In our culture it is red , for example the achepa is red
it is already
one of our most representative birds , it is also red .
iisho
He is a cardinal, then
that is, basically red
It's like what we have the most there, that is, it's what we have the most
represents us
and it has that meaning related to everything. Also these blankets
It makes us feel like , if one wears red,
one feels at home, calm, it transmits to us
It is also or instead.
If one wears another color, for example yellow, I don't know,
one feels like one feels uncomfortable,
but red is what represents us the most.
It means a lot to us.
Add some of anything to it.
Come?
Do you want to say something else?
Yeah
Tell Kati how you felt in the Yonna , for example.
You who are new, how did you think of Yonna?
Or whatever you want to express
Well, she's my little sister.
If that's why I scold her a lot,
She 's my little sister, so she's new at school.
So she's learning and she's learning
Then I'll
I'm saying share with us how you've been feeling,
did you like it?
So
when one dances in the Yoona,
When I dance, I feel happy,
one, I feel this, I feel that
I feel happy
to do what I want.
I want to learn, this I want,
I want to be one, I want to be like this as my partner See u
I want to learn to knit, to dance
also, make hammocks,
make backpacks,
this one
is to be a seedbed
and
make wayunkeera
be way unkeera what we do with mud
and what else.
And that seedbed ?
What is it? seedbed are the school children, the
smaller. So
Seedbeds comes from the word seed sa uyee .
So that's why we say seedbed , so yes.
and like her, like that
As we have many children at school.
So with the children, no, we don't take them like that.
She is my little sister, I have been at school for many years
and I don't take it like that,
but it is something that must be awakened in her.
Tell me no, I want to go
, I want to learn what everything is
d the want.
If I am forced to take it
here he was with his face,
but no, she enjoys it and enjoys it.
So much so, it looks fun and feels very good.
It was the first one you did
and how well I am, how well.
Well and for each of you
If I could carry a message to the whole world.
What message would it be?
You start. Can you think for a moment
I hope we don't let our culture lose.
If it is something so beautiful and so ours.
and it would be nice
that we value it more
and let's strengthen it
because as I tell you this has not been lost,
It's just that we have to strengthen it
but that is in one
Well
as the companion said.
As we are experiencing what the Yonna is
which is making wayunkeera (clay doll) or doing many things
As you can do it too, you can practice.
Of course, it's not easy,
but if given time, they can learn to dance,
They can learn to be wayunkeera (clay doll)
to knit,
don't be ashamed of the culture
because it is beautiful.
Be wayuu
It is the most beautiful thing in this life
and learn many things from our ancestors that already
They are not here with us now, but there are
things that have left us
speaks
send a message to the children
I want to send the message to the boys and girls.
I want him not to be ashamed
of the Wayuu culture that
To learn
to do, to do the
Yonna, the Wayunkeera
I want them ,
May they learn just as I am learning now.
and nothing more
Well
to close
When they ask me a lot about messages
It inspired me a lot.
she was picking up, exactly,
I was trying not to repeat myself because if I don't know,
I have a lot of love for my culture.
For example, I have had many opportunities
to do other things instead of dancing suddenly
my traditional dance of dancing folklore different cities,
champeta, reggaeton .
They have called me for contests,
but seeing the cultural crisis
that we are honestly going through,
Well, I feel like I can contribute my grain of sand.
from what I know how to do, from what I like,
which is dance, music.
Also my
know, learn, multiply what I know.
So my invitation is to love
what they have around them, regardless of whether they are Wayúu
or not. No, sometimes you can't imagine the spiritual connection
with nature
that has the different cultures here in our country,
and sometimes one gets careless.
For example, when we go to a city
we are very attentive to anything
because we don't know what meaning it has.
Then suddenly for those who come
from the outside, it would be very nice
Also, just as you who know,
who are interested in knowing
what does each thing mean ,
because that's how they also begin to respect it,
start taking care of her and they also start to love her.
And also
you who are not your own
Wayuu, you can contribute your grain of sand
To be able to make known what we are,
to continue strengthening everything we have, maintain it
and keep it .
We at this time
what we want
is to preserve that for future generations.
Then the invitation is also for you.
When he makes us known there, then let them remember us,
May they remember and they will always be welcome here.
May you also teach us
also.
And the last thing is if each of you can tell me
yes we have permission to use this in the documentary
our what are they doing
recording , and first before publishing anything
We passed by you to verify, but
as I am.
already authorize and so
well me Veruzka Henriquez
Acosta, I authorize
Let them use my image as such .
Ok here.
Me too Karla Epinayu
I authorize you to use the image
I Angeline Jayariyu, authorize it to be made public
this image so that everyone can recognize it .
She is a minor
So I'm going to authorize it for her, since she's my little sister.
well me Karla Epinayu, representative of Katius c a
Jiménez authorized him to do
your image is also used. Thank you so much.
Anayawatsu.