Where are you from Neko?
I am from a territory called Akualü
Although the elders call it Manaure
Ah, you came from the wild west and now you're here
In Nazareth or township of Nazareth as they call it
We are in the territory of Usijou´, in Alewalü.
I don't know if you've heard that it's a sacred place.
Yes, it is the only one with some characteristics
different natural
Yes of course. My grandmother and my mother's grandmother were from here.
Where is the sea? If over there, from here you can see the sea
Yes it's true.
Yes, they lived here
But is the sea far from here? Yes, it's far away.
They said they moved, they had left their
things as you can see
There where the pieces of amuchi (ceramics) are,
are their ancestral remains (bone)
They decided to go to the seashore because
They say they were already bored here
Then they left, but they came back again. Yeah. right here
This was what you were talking about, right? Yeah.
I can touch it? No. It is prohibited
You can't touch it, you can only see it. If you touch it
you can get sick
When you touch it you take away the energies of the dead
that can cause you some harm
Same with your arrival here
TRUE. You had to harmonize with the territory because we
surround the souls of those who lived here
This belonged to them right? Yes, that's why their souls
They are here because those are their belongings.
This was their territory and they said that no one can
take part of this sand
Then we, the Pausayu, arrived to inhabit it.
I understand. And what did they bring from the sea?
The sand, they threw it here so that it would stay like this
That is, they brought the sand from the beach in
this desert piece
The old people say that through a dream they were told
to bring the sand from there
I'm telling you so you can say it, this part
then they cut it
Guille said that in the dream they were told
the next
That, if they loved this land so much, they could bring the
earth up to here
and that's what they did. This is how this place originated
You could say that. That started from a dream
and so on
So they brought him here, right? Yeah.
They brought it little by little until it spread
As you can see this before this was small, but after
They expanded it up to there
Yes, now I understand. How nice to know the history
behind this
Yes of course, in fact, all this that is here
It's also beautiful
Yeah. It is very good to make known what
we have because it is part of our Wayuu culture
You will already know that this place exists in La Guajira, Alewalü
will be recognized by the world
Through stories like these you will learn not only
the place but its spirituality
Since there are also many jewels of
the deceased
That is why it is a sacred place because here are the
things from those who created it
People say that here in the north is where
are the most sacred places
And that is why it is important to make them known. Yes of course.
Well, thank you very much for what you shared with us.
Anyway, thanks to you for coming,
For coming from so far to know our territory
After winter it doesn't bloom here? No,
Does it stay like this? Yes of course, it gets wet and that's it
The animals walk and do not get their paws wet.
You see there is no grass. No.
And if it rains a lot? It may rain a lot but still
It does not bloom because it is a sacred place
The territory is sacred
That was destined. Yes, that's why they were created
ancestors who saw here
People who come to Nazareth say that their
ancestors are from here too
Those from Dusakawi (health association) said that their
grandmothers told them that they have ancestors here
They say they will come back here again.
Yes, that's OK
I think it's good that they come again so that
learn more, we make you climb the mountains
Yes, we have to arrive earlier, look, they are already rushing us. Yes, it's true, it is complex.
Because it is already getting dark and we already have
we have to leave because of how sacred it is
You are in Alewalü in the Alewalü Dunes
Smile smile. Stretch your hands. That
That, that raise your hands, aha say hello, say hello.
Alewalu