Can you explain to me, who are you and what do you do?
And what ritual are we going to do? anas alika
Good afternoon.
my name is
Teolinda, Wayuu Epiayu
My name is Teolinda from the clan of Epinayu
I am from the walapuinje ranch which means “dreams and interpretations”,
dreams.
Today I am going to tell you about traditional medicine
that I inherited from my grandmother.
As we know
here it is very difficult for one to run towards
a doctor or a health center,
so as we are growing up, our grandmothers taught us to purify
and they taught us about traditional medicine,
how we could cure one of our children.
For example, when the child has diarrhea, we can give him
jawapi a medicinal plant
the jawapi, which is a medicinal plant, helps a lot
to clean the child's organism and that diarrhea can stop and can also
help to clean as if it were a chamomile, but it is a jawapia, made with medicinal plants
and also when the child has a fever or diarrhea or vomiting
We also have this medicine here, we make it,
we take and start right here with the stone
and we put it
in this totumito (container) and we give the baby a drink.
It also helps scare away bad energy.
What plant is it?
This is called kalenasee
Kalenasee is a plant that, just by its
smell, scares away spirits.
Well now in this moment
here is my niece,
She is sick
and I am going to give her medicine that through dreams
Grandma interpreted. She showed me one of the plants
Which one is the medicine that I am going to give her,
because she had an accident
and the accident had her here in the collarbone
and I have to take the medicine
that is called a'tachon,
a´tachon is a medicinal plant medicine,
it also helps a lot to clean the blood
and for the person who also suffers from a fracture
or a very serious injury.
One takes this, attaches it and begins to scratch it
with a stone now
soak it
here with the water
Now it looks as if it was water, all fresh,
So I'm going to give her a drink
for that fracture to heal
do I drink it all? yes my lady, drink it all because it will cure you
The other goes here
I'm going to cure her with a little
what was left to where
has been fractured.
and that
is the bija blanca
this is a very important plant
And
to bathe our boys, or girl.
The moment that,
When a girl has fever
and when you can't sleep at night
as one says,
"She is restless", is when the girl, the baby or the girl
does not sleep well, sleep is
like drowsiness.
Then looking at her, we take the bija,
we start cooking it
we are not going to do that anymore, but we are going to cook it
or it can also be by pieces
we already have it here.
It can also be accompanied by chirrinchi (alcoholic drink).
you'll be fine, it won't hurt anymore
this disease is leaving you
you will be fine
You won't get sick anymore and it won't hurt anymore my girl
that's when the girl, like I was
saying at first that she feels bad,
with flu, wanting to vomit, nauseated.
One cures it with the malua, which is one of the best-known plants.
and to scare what she has,
if she is, well
Feeling like apathetic, that she feels
that her body is not hers, that she is gone,
then through dreams
we dream and see which plant we can cure it with.
They show themselves to us by dream interpretations.
There I saw that in the dream they said that she
they had to scare her away what she has
and try to do a purification
of body through malua
better known as bija.
Is it an energy purification?
Yes, an energy like hers, she is sick
to scare away what she had
or the energy that was already bad
and suddenly they scare it with something
cold that is the chirrinchi (alcoholic drink) and also with the medicine
she's going to feel good
everything she had wrong
She will get her energy back.
Well, in her case, the flu,
we have
We also have the
with the
kalenakalu, this one
three together,
these plants heal
the flu disease, of the asthmatic person
doing vaporization and by drink
and the vaporization with sea salt.
One of those who fought a lot
With the COVID disease
It was this wonderful (plant) that you see here,
doing the vaporization with the sea salt.
All three of them together
Are mixed and you have to drink it
before coffee or breakfast
because it is already in the morning.
It is the first thing that before drinking coffee, to
drink this for the flu.
It heals our children quite a lot,
is the only medicine
that we use in our ranch.
when our children
or when there is diarrhea
very strong that the diarrhea comes with blood.
This is called turio'u, the turio'u
or itachon (because of its cup shape)
It is when one begins to scratch the itachon,
already scratched,
touch,
A red, pinkish color comes out, that is the one that will cure
to the person who has diarrhea
it's called wainruin'ou,
This wainruin'ou medicine
Do you see the color?
wainruin'ou is for diarrhea.
Let's say,
Our children drink it and it helps a lot to stop the diarrhea
So the diarrhea no longer continues for the child or the lady.
When diarrhea comes with blood, it is already accompanied
of the turi´ou of the wainruin´ou (plants) with this
which is called palisa or kinou'ta,
that is the red medicine
And they are sticks and this is dry too,
all three are cooked together and you start drinking it
twice a week, Monday and Tuesday,
Then the other week Monday and Tuesday.
And so on, until the diarrhea goes away.
Drink it just a little
and it must be very bitter
so it can stop the diarrhea.
On the other hand,
we have here the kasuou
when our children
girls develop at the age of 12,
we also have to purify the body with jawapia,
clean the body
In order to have the girl
with firm skin forever and that she enjoys
eternal youth,
We give you the mou'a, the mou'a is the dove
and we cook it as if it was soup
and as a traditional drink so that she
Can have very clean skin
and to stay well,
it is called kasuo´u (white bun), a stone
kasuo´u The drink of the majayut (lady)
or the confinement drink or the young lady drink.
well and
one of those is the,
the bath to purify the body,
the bath
tries that when there is a problem, there are many kinds of problem.
For example, it may be the problem of death
or the problem
when there is controversy
for example, with the territories,
one has to find a way to take a bath
to scare away that problem, so that it goes away,
To avoid a problem between the two families,
that family has to stay united
and for this problem it is necessary to look for the solution.
And then, how do we do it?, with the bath
Basically all medicines are already together
which is the bath
That already comes
with chirrinchi that's already cold
and start to do the bath, scare it from behind
so that when it goes, move there, look there
well, with the totuma like this,
one does it like that, scaring
The bad energy
so that this problem does not come back
and she has to push it away and let her talk
and tell it to go to the bottom of the sea, taking also
of course
the lania (amulet or charm), begins…
I'm going to take out the lania.
The lania is a tiny backpack
That Lania is Grandma's.
jawapia
This jawapia you have to try to scratch it
to do the girl's bath, to scare the
problematic, move away that problem
so that none of the family will be touched,
nor the family
of the young
It's called jawapia
a medicinal green plant
that has its name,
but it's grandma's secret.
You don't have to say,
but you have to show nothing more than medicine,
because one never reveals
what is something important to her.
You must keep it, you can take it
with your own hands,
The plant.
This is the lania
of the grandmother
You pick it up and starts to
take away anything evil there is
take what’s evil to the bottom of the sea, let no evil come near here
so that it does not affect our guests. God I ask you
who entrusted me with this plant to protect people.
Scaring away with this, it is the grandmother's lania,
pushing away what comes above,
if it’s a territory problem
or death problem,
and one has to find a way to cleanse oneself,
to purify oneself and we can also find the stone
with indigenous protection.
And that was also because of grandmother's interpretations
That are these stones
It is called tuma or cornalina
to try to get clean
and protect yourself.
As you can see also jawapia is drinkable,
It is drinkable so that it stays in one's stomach,
whether a person comes to
dare to seek to kill,
He comes looking for death, he doesn't,
because it is protected by this jawapia in the stomach.
And the same goes with the protections.
Ask, ask.
Where does all knowledge come from?
Well, that knowledge comes from the
Grandma, it is ancestral, but as
I tell you at the age of 12 we learn a lot.
That is why one says that education comes from home.
What we learn first is from our elders
and traditional medicine
we inherited it, it is an inheritance for us,
because when we are in growing up
They show us or teach us about
traditional medicine
and teach us about values
and that is ancestral
How does one choose to be knowledgeable?
Well, when Grandma is very old,
For example, 90 years old,
she has to search and she won't tell you
You're going to replace me
she begins to dream and in her dreams,
she chooses the person who is going to replace her.
And that person that she chooses,
she has already analyzed it, and sits it down,
he sits with her,
begins to teach him his gifts, his wisdom,
what does each plant mean,
What is each plant for?
Look at this, you're going to dream
and they will show you through your dreams
the medicine you are going to use.
Is it spiritual then?
Spiritual yes, Spiritual, of course,
because you know that is also biblical, too
when in the time of Jesus he sends
to José, for the dream
that he had, that he had
to reveal dreams to the Egyptians
of the seven plagues
and they never believed, and from the famine
and it really came. once one
for dreams, one also has to go through the line of
that and believe,
because the truth is that a dream,
It's not a game, it's a dream.
And that dream must be treated if it is bad,
you have to push it away like I was doing to the girl,
scare away that dream
that they dreamed for her, take all that away from her.
That's what the dream is about
and it has to do with traditional medicine.
And all that?
It's like a story or a
knowledge?
Knowledge, a knowledge.
That's called piachi
medical,
medical
ancestral, has its piachi name in parentheses
(ancestral medicine) and the piache can also help on deliveries
when a girl is pregnant
and the child is wrong, because he can
one to compose lifting it here from the waist to here
so that baby can be located in its place.
Then on the birth day,there will not have difficulty.
You can say that word, lapuja.
Dreams, lapu'je yes, lapu'je
Sure, as I was saying earlier
That
grandma tells which person
she is going to choose, she dreams first, lapu'je
Dream.
One more thing, how do plants taste?
Because I have knowledge of those plants, I learned,
It's like the doctor
the one who studies to study,
For example, headache.
I can grab a chirrinchi
I put it on my head, my headache goes away
because I know that it is good for a headache,
for diarrhea that comes with blood
I know what it is, it’s this one, I start to scratch it
and I take it
or I give it to drink, because honestly
maybe no medicine can cure it,
but suddenly this can cure it
because we have had some cases.
A case, an example,
a man who was evicted in a wheelchair,
came from Italy, where science is most advanced
and they evicted him in a wheelchair.
He came here, here to Manaure to visit, like you
As a tourist and I received it
and I told my grandmother that there is a man
who is in a wheelchair,
but he was evicted because he cannot walk for life.
My grandmother told me for God nothing is impossible,
maleiwa, for him nothing is impossible.
Maleiwa is God and if He shows me in a dream
What I can cure this man with, yes it can be cured.
They showed him it was sea salt,
and the salt raised it
marine along with a massage
nothing more, and with chirrinchi.
And nowadays, this man walks with crutches
when science said he’d be on a wheelchair
for the rest of his life,
He was lifted by a Wayuu woman.
Faith,
and faith moves mountains.
May I introduce you
again, like who are you and what do you do
and where are we?
Okay, yes. Anas aliika, good afternoon, tanulia
My name is Teolinda from the Epiyu clan.
I am a Wayuu indigenous
one of those who is, one of the knowers, one of the
piachi (medical) obtained by grandmother,
since she is very old.
She already has her replacement.
Little by little she is leaving her gifts, her wisdom
and that is through lapu'je,
dream interpretations.
We are here in the walapuinje ranch, which means dream,
anayawatsu
anayawatsu is thank you.
And the last thing is that if you have a message.
Well, the message that I am going to give you is that
Us, the wayuu, the idea is that this
stays with our grandchildren, with our children,
with our grandchildren, not to be missed.
We want you to know our
medicine, just as they have their medicine,
we also have our traditional medicine
that we got from grandma.
Thanks to maleiwa (God),
that is everything, He is who created the plants
and we are using all those plants to cure those who are sick.
I invite you to come
and can make a good purification
here in the walapuinje ranch,
If you feel sick, if you feel something, come here
I wait for you here, here in the Walapuinje ranch
The knowing woman Teolinda, Thank you..
the way she interprets dreams
How do you know?
I dream, I sleep and
the next day we sat down with a coffee
Juana bring me coffee please
rinse it first
Now I am going to tell you how they interpret the dream.
And what does it mean to you to be Wayuu?
What does it mean to be wayuu?
Something big, something wonderful.
I feel proud to be wayuu
and I thank Maleiwa,
God, because I have known
to such a good, beautiful, intelligent woman,
like my grandmother, and that she has taken
care of my mom, through her knitting
and through traditional medicine.
And me too right now
I'm following Grandma and I'm her replacement.
the knowledge,
knowledgeable, because I learned to give birth to a child,
I already gave birth to a child, I learned how to be a doctor,
and was,
It was very difficult because when she came on the road, it was like
And now?, what am I going to do?,
there she comes and you could see the little head.
When I saw that the baby began to come out,
I said “Teolinda, you can do this!”
and the baby came out and when I took the scissors
where was she and
I broke the navel and tied it with a thread.
Today the girl is already ten years old, I learned
to receive children, (to be a) midwife.
A very nice experience
I really liked it, it's like a health center,
to receive too. I mean, I didn't study,
I didn't prepare myself, but I prepared myself
in my ranch to be a doctor
and to learn about traditional medicine and
here I am, with you.
Did you also see that putting the collar on
It has a meaning?
This is my protection, my indigenous protection.
This is my protection.
This necklace, this is the Tuma, the Wayuu gold.
This is my protection that grandma prepared for me
for all sickness, health, work,
lately for love
This is medicine, but with protection.
Now, the dream,
we sleep
and the next day we come and
we talk to each other, just as we are together
we say to each other, good morning what did you dream
What did you dream of?
Oh me, oh!
What did I dream, oh well…
Well, tell me your dream.
I dreamed something nice that it was raining,
and everything was green.
That has its meaning. The rain is the tear
because it falls from the sky
because the tear falls from the eyes downwards,
it is tear
And when it's green
you think that something is going to come, that something is going to be,
that the land will produce again.
That interprets the dream to us.
So we believe a lot in the dream
and believing in the dream,
because that dream is already biblical, it's not like
We are going to invent it just because,
but because you are going to tell the truth of what you dreamed of,
without telling lies
To say that you dreamed, what the dream means, and the dream
one has to say it at the moment, speaking
means so much and one starts to drink coffee,
What else?
[Interviewer Well, that talk about the rain,
Well, are the elements sacred in this culture?
We identify ourselves with the four elements,
rain,
because we always ask Juya for water,
Manaure is the town that lasts,
if it rains a year, it is twice a year, no more water falls again.
So with the climate change
is when the problem arises
in the form of malnutrition, of begging.
Because grandma tells that years ago
all this land was very fruitful.
We could sow what was the guajiro bean,
the ahuyama, the watermelon, the melon, the corn, the cassava.
But years ago it changed.
Then he showed up, do you know what?
Why did the problem arise?
because I always understand that sometimes they say
the wayuu is lazy to work, it's not that,
but our wayuu
or we, our relatives never studied,
they never went to school
they never learned to speak spanish
and to be able to work you are required to have a diploma,
They demands your resume.
But what resume, what diploma
it will give if you never studied and never learned
to speak Spanish?, if what they learned
when growing up
were the fabrics of our backpack.
How to recognize different types and classes of backpack, from Kanasü,
of one thread and what is not Kanasü, that is basic,
that we see how it is,
It takes me a week to do it.
While that of one month is a month,
because the dedication, the time to make a backpack
you have to give value to
our backpacks, because one is the one who has
to demonstrate the time, the dedication
to that backpack when weaving it. also for sleep
interpreting our backpack, in our dream
We also interpret our backpacks.
Also
we interpret dreams, too
In nature.
Because if I am going to say, today the cardón,
from the heart of the cardón the house is taken
of what he is
yotojoro (dry trunks), is removed from there from the cardón
and Cardón also, from the heart of the cardón or the pulp of the
cardón also uses it
the one who herds the goats, because there,
because he keeps water in his heart.
In all four elements.
This, for example, the ka'i, the sun is very important,
because that was the identification of our grandmothers of the hour.
The Kashi, the Kashi
Moon,
when it's halfway
already one is prohibited from cutting the sticks
because the stick is damaged, they become termites
and also with the water, which
It's a precious liquid
because without water there is no life
and also the fire.
I identify with fire.
Many questions have been asked to me about why I identify myself
with fire, because fire is very important,
because in the fire, the fire interprets me,
that has a meaning
one of those is when the fire…
because when you have your firewood off,
your kitchen off, it's because your life is off,
You will not find anything, not even a blessing,
because my grandmother says oh, and why
Do you have the firewood off?,
because there is nothing to cook, there is no food there,
And because there is nothing to cook.
You turned the firewood turned off?, turn that on!
You don't know that
God says that one has to have the firewood on,
as long as the fire is on
There is life, there is life!
Anyone can come with a kilo of rice,
a coffee slip, something, but turn it on! and
one turns it on
And also at the moment he dies,
as we have two funerals,
the first one when we mourn our deceased
and the second one
when we began to collect human remains at
five years or six seven.
It is the last farewell to our deceased, that the soul goes
resting at a place called
Jepira that is at El Cabo de la Vela,
and also
I identify myself because also when one dies
one has to follow the light,
because if your life is dark and
there is no light because your life is turned off.
That's why I identify with fire.
Well,
Now I have a question.
how is it…
there is a communication with the spirits or with whom
Are you learning such things from dreams?
It may be a relative of one.
My grandmother.
She is the one who speaks, she is the one who says.
They are ancestral.
It's not just any spirit
it has to be a relative.
It is the one that tells you how to take care of yourself, how to protect yourself,
But, that grandmother is already deceased.
She's already dead.
So by dreams, speak, choose a person.
Before it was the grandmother,
but she chooses, when she has
at a very old age he has to choose a replacement.
But it is always a familiar.
It's not just any bad spirit or anything like that,
but a familiar, as one calls it,
our angels.