Tanülia tayakai Joaquín Ramón Prince
(My name is Joaquín Ramón Prince)
Jayariyu, tayakai
(I am a musician)
Ekirajüi tepichi sunain tüü wemirakat.
(And I work in a training process)
Sünain tüü weinrankat,
(With Wayuu children)
Sunain tüü wakuwaipakat sunai tüü
(From the Wayuu community)
Supushuakat
(Through dance)
Sulukat tüü woumainkat tuvo un mal trato y se robó mi mano
(To preserve and maintain our music)
Ani taya ya´ya sunai tüü tekirajüin naa tepichikana sunain tüü ontoroyoi
(and the harmony of the Wayuu people)
Maasi, sawawa, turompa
(such as the Ontoroyoi, Sawawa, Maasi, Turompa, and Kasha)
Sunain tüü yonna suma tüü jieyu ekirajaka ya´ya tüü wakuwaipakat
(I am a cultural promoter)
Well, my name.
I'll speak in my Wayunaiki language first,
I said that
my name is Joaquín Ramón
Prince Bruges of Clan, from the Jayariyu eiruku.
I'm a musician,
I'm a cultural manager,
I've been working on an educational process
with Wayuu children
here in this space that you see, and there are also other spaces
to preserve and maintain the music
and harmony of the Wayuu people through dance,
art, songs, and musical instruments
of the Wayuu, such as the Ontoroyoi, Sawawa, Maasi, Turompa, and Kasha.
Well, I will
speak my language again.
Wayakana shipi´jala tüü mmakat.
(Wayakana shipi´jala tüü mmakat)
Esü wunu´u, esü mürüt
(I am a musician, I am a cultural promoter)
Esü uchi,
esü wayuu,
Wayakana yashi sulu´u tüü woumaikat
tüü woumainkat nojotsü wakoroloin, waya sukorolo tüü mmakat
werüin tüü, palajana, antushi
chi juyakai sulu´u tüü wouman tüü mmakat
chi juyakai nia Chi watushikai
tüü mmakat shia weika woushi
anchi jolu aijuin tüü wunu´ukat
supula nanjuin tüü weirainkat sünain tüü jo´utai
sunain tu wekiru sünain tüü wainkat
sunain, piruin antüshin
chi jichikua nanjuin tu wakuwaipakat sünain tüü weirankat
Well, I spoke in my language, and now I will switch back.
Let me repeat now so that you understand. I said that we are
I said that we are
the guardians of the land,
there was an ancient time,
as the elders say.
There was a beginning, an ancient time
when our father Juya arrived,
who is the rain, for us, he is rain and not just rain, because he is a man
and the land is our
ancient mother, he arrives,
it rains, inseminating her, making love to her,
and from our mother, plants are born, the first beings, then
the animals, and third, the birds.
And in the fourth generation, us,
the humans, the Wayúu people.
But it was a woman.
As the elders say, the land
is very sacred to us.
It's our mother,
and we should not sell it,
because we are not owners of the land,
it owns us,
because we are born from it,
and we return to it when we die.
That's why it is very important
to preserve the instruments and the music
through thought, through the heart, and through the wind,
because my body
is the one that creates music through thought and through the wind.
And that's why our ancestors exist,
the wind, the wind, Papa,
our wind
that blows and forms whirlwinds
born in nature, that teaches us how to make music.
I'm going to play a tune, which I told you is called
"La Crianza en la Tierra Wayakana Shipi'jala tüü mmakat."
We are the guardians of the land.
And that's how it is.
Just a moment before starting
to change the Atlantic configuration,
set workers.
From the State, Stars of Iberoamerica Context
Ready.
It's like that.
Oh, oh oh oh.
Oh, oh, oh
Well, this is another instrument
also made by us, just as I told you before,
it's called Maasi.
We use this during herding,
and to communicate with other companions.
That's why I said it's better to do it in the community
to have the spiritual connection.
The wind helps us make the music,
so it also helps us communicate
through the music,
so with it, I'll tell you a story,
when we're herding,
we communicate, each one has their rhythm,
their sound
and distinctive sound.
If I hear a sound, I say, "That's Pedro's,"
if it's a different sound,
it's Juan's, and mine is also different.
So, I communicate with Pedro through the music,
it's like having a dialogue through playing,
asking if he has seen a lost sheep
when I'm herding, and that's how it is.
That sound is made by us,
the music, the music, we create it from our minds,
we only need our ears,
ears and thinking, thinking with nature.
Plants, the air, they are the ones that help us
make music, interpreting the sound.
That's why it's important for us,
these plants had a life,
this material comes from a plant, it returns to another life.
Now, it's speaking and singing to us.
It's still alive
You know, they are born, they reproduce,
but as you say, "arijuna,"
we say "arijuna" because they're not Wayuu. No,
it died for you, but
for us, it's alive, it has another life,
and it's speaking through my body,
through the wind I'm creating.
It doesn't talk,
and that's why the sound, it has a high and a low pitch.
See, this is the high one,
and this is the low one,
this is the maasi, in our language.
"Ontoroyoi" in our language has no name in Spanish.
In truth, the elders say we made this out of necessity
to maintain the harmony of the Wayuu people and to
keep friendship among those of us who coexist.
And that's how music is for sadness,
when we want to court a woman,
a female, we do it with this too.
This one is called "sawawa,"
we use this ourselves too,
Young men use it to court women,
with a feeling when we are sad,
when we are in love,
we make music with the help of nature too.
When we hear the birds,
we make music, the birds help us create
the music, along with the wind and the sea.
This is a song here of a Wayuu in love, and it goes like this,
Oh, oh, oh.
Well, that's the sawawa,
as I told you, it's made by us,
and these are materials from nature,
these instruments have a ritual, these three,
these instruments can only be played during the day and night,
we can't play them at night, maybe when I travel to a city.
But in our territory, I can't do it,
and if I play them at night, I have to ask for permission
from Mother Earth and Father Rain,
because they have a ritual.
They say that at that hour,
after six when the sun sets, they are already resting.
We can't bother them in the morning so that
they wake up with that musical sound,
to bring joy to our territory,
and only men play them.
Sure, a woman can do it too,
but for us Wayuu, it's frowned upon.
Maybe you can do it, a non-Wayuu woman can do it,
but a Wayuu woman cannot,
because it's a fundamental craft of the men.
At the moment of herding,
at the moment of searching for water at the Jagüey or the casimba,
and at the moment when feeling something for a woman.
That's why the instruments are very important, so they know
what Wayuu music is and what these instruments are used for.
This one is called "ontoroyoi," sorry,
turompa, this one is called "birimbao," they call it mouth harp,
it's a well-known instrument among various indigenous groups,
it was brought by colonizers.
We adapted it
in a way that suits us and made it for ourselves,
we manufacture it, women and men can play this one,
as you can see, it's made of metal, very different from the plant.
Plants have life, this one never had life,
and this one is made
by humans and is riveted, whereas this one has
a more spiritual character to make it,
these ones made from plants,
I'll play a tune for you, it's called the flutter of birds, at this time
the birds are fluttering to rest,
and they start doing it like this
and when it rains, they also start fluttering.
Oh, oh, oh
Oh, oh, oh.
You
Are you blowing or just using your mouth?
Not just the mouth, the mouth is for resonance, and I inhale
and blow, but not very forcefully, softly.
Yes, the mouth provides resonance, and
I have to press my teeth together here
for it to produce the vibration
from the reed in the center.
That's interesting.
They are alive, but you are alive too.
Yes, I'm using this one, yes, correct.
Yes, correct.
So, for us, it's important to preserve the music. This is the tambora.
Now, this is the kasha we use for dancing
at the yonna. We use
the dance rhythms at the yonna. There's one called the horse race,
That's why I wanted to play it, and
I was inviting you all
because in the community, one can focus
for longer periods,
because you hear noise here and noise there.
So, it's not clear: in the community, nature helps us
to concentrate, and that way, things truly become
evident, what we are, the music, and
and maybe I'll bring another musician from the school because it's
different
what he plays compared to what I do, it has a different sound,
it's the same instrument,
the same tune, but it has another language.
The sound is different, each one has their touch.
It's like if he composes a song, it's
different from the one I compose,
That's Wayuu music, we create it, and it's very important to us.
As I said, the wind
and the whirlwind, we call it "pichikua"
in our language, "pichikua" means whirlwind,
and "jo'utai" means wind,
because in our bodies,
we create music through the wind, thought, and heart,
and what you think,
we turn into music with the help of the instrument.
That's why it's very important to preserve Wayuu music
and for you to know about it.
Taking the music to another level
with other instruments that are not Wayuu,
we are already doing it, the functions and trials,
and it has given us excellent results.
Yes, maybe combining the music of
reggaeton with the turompa,
the tambora with African calling drum,
we are doing all this musical work
to preserve and maintain our cultural richness,
without forgetting about ourselves,
our language, our spirituality,
our territory,
our clan, which is our social organization,
and the traditional economy where you live.
These five main pillars are very important,
which are our cultural expressions that are
within the Wayuu normative system,
and our voices should always be in our
language, that's why I started
speaking in my language, which is Wayunaiki,
that's why it's important,
Wayunaiki means "people of good thinking,"
wayuu ana'a eki
people of good thinking or good head.
So, I invite you to join us, I don't know what you think,
you can come with us tomorrow to that place,
it's a very beautiful place,
and I have to call and let them know that we are coming with you.
So, yes, that's the plan, I don't know.
If it works for you
And about what you were talking to me at the beginning,
about the harmony or the harmony of the music
Can you talk a little more about that,
about preserving harmony?
There is already harmony in nature, and for me,
it seems like the music is trying to reach that harmony, to be more connected.
If we maintain music through spirituality,
through spiritual connection, I can play the instrument here,
but it's not the same as playing it in my community.
It's different there because I have a connection with nature,
with the birds and animals,
and the plants are what help me
to maintain that energy
and the body,
because with my body, I think,
because we are the fourth generation.
we do the sound interpretation
and not so much with our fingers
but with what I think and what I see,
because one learns through observation.
Yes, what I hear, I put my ear to it
I hear the birds very well, I hear
the waves of the sea, I hear the
fluttering of the birds,
I also hear the plants as they move. All of that
is what teaches us how to make music together,
with that we make our music and also
the animals like the birds.
That's why I played a little bit of the fluttering of the birds.
It's all through nature,
that's why music is very important to us
and within our community,
because it helps us create harmony
and spiritual connotation,
because there is spiritual music like the tambora,
there is healing music that helps heal the sick
and helps ward off negative energies.
During the time of COVID
there was a dream from women, spiritual authorities
of the Wayuu people
because there is a spiritual authority of women.
There was a dream she had where a yonna dance had to be performed,
which is a dance,
that's why I said it was better to explain
there how it was and that the tambora had to be played, which is the kasha.
in order for that COVID energy to go away
and he said we should place a plant called malu'a
which has good energy and
that way, the energy of COVID
wouldn't reach our territory
and indeed it didn't affect us much, only impacted
the city and urban areas, and that helped us a lot
to preserve through music.
It helped us defend ourselves from illnesses, bad energies
and to preserve what one desires and feels.
Yes, it has power
I have taken it to the Philharmonic Orchestra of Bogota,
yes, there we are preparing for a performance,
we are testing with other instruments,
like the violin,
like those big drums, we are conducting all the tests
to present it in a sonorous way
that can be showcased to the world.
In the Wayuu village,
we also have an instrument.
Even though it's small,
this instrument, called sonoros, holds a special
meaning for us,
it's very, very spiritual for us,
very important for the Wayuu people
and that's why we preserve it through the school
we have here,
teaching the boys and girls
about Wayuu music, why we do it and how we do it,
and why it's important to maintain Wayuu music.
And can you tell me a bit about that?
More about the school and what we are going to do tomorrow?
Well, you see the image there,
that's Maestro Jorge Enrique,
a Wayuu music teacher who taught me, he passed away.
He's resting in Jepira because when we die, we don't
go to heaven
nor to the right hand of God, we embark on a long journey
to the paradise of the dead, which
is where you go to the Cabo de la Vela, and our soul rests there
We embark on a long journey
and through everything we feel and do.
The elders say
that we become water,
we fall into the sea there in Cabo or Jepira, and then
it evaporates, rises to the sky, and falls back to the earth
to fertilize the land and
We return to another life,
the plants are the same.
In the Wayuu village, we don't pollute the plants,
we don't harm nature,
but there have been many people
who have come to pollute our territory
and some Wayuu people have also learned to do that, and that has also lost
the way of preserving, taking care of the instruments because there are plants that are no longer there
in some parts, so we have to look for them
in other territories
because in our culture, there is a space that is only
reserved for the plants, and that cannot be disturbed.
It's as if it were our heart, it's the Wayuu,
that's where we plant,
we maintain all the crops so we can eat
because everywhere else
we can't plant, only in that specific area,
which the Wayuu identifies through the heart,
and there are the plants
and the musical instruments where we can make
each instrument to play
the sawawa, the maasi, and the ontoroyoi.
Through that.
Do you choose a plant yourself?
Yes, we make it ourselves,
I personally make it, I search for the plant,
they have their time, the moment when I can cut them,
I can't cut them anytime,
they have their moon time
and I can't cut them. We
ask permission from Mother Earth through rituals
to be able to cut the plants. I can't just
cut them at any time, no, they have their time.
And is there
a connection between dance and music?
I mean, I've seen that the drums don't.
Yes, the dance of the yonna
is done with the Kasha, which for us is a drum
and during the dance
There's a ritual we perform before the dance
in a sacred space called piyoi, which is a circle.
A circle where the girls dance barefoot,
sometimes, these days, as the sun has been very hot,
they've had to dance in a space wearing sandals,
but it's always barefoot.
They wear their red patterned shawl, symbolizing
what red represents,
our blood, the land,
especially what relates to spirituality.
And there are different dances,
what do they show there? The steps, like those of the alcaraván,
they do the step of the tortolita,
the dove, the vulture,
everything that exists in nature,
showing all the richness we see in our territory,
that's what they portray through the dance. The Yonna dance
is a challenge between the man and the woman, in the strength they measure.
That's why the man goes backward
and the woman goes forward always.
And there, the woman's skill is more evident than the man's.
That's why it's important for the woman in the
dance to wear her veil (kiara) beautifully,
her face adorned with palisha (red powder)
and her hair elegantly styled.
That's what adds beauty to the yonna dance.
Yes, that's very good
It could also be possible to play a little more.
Well, yes,
Well, let's play a bit here
On the drum too,
but I can stand up because I have to stand up
Alright, I'll put
this inside the pocket if you want.
Right there.
Yes. No, no!
Well, the rhythm that
I'm going to play is a rhythm
of yonna.
It's the traditional dance
of the Yonna.
I'm going to play
a rhythm of the horse race.
Well, those are the rhythms
that we play with the kasha
and well, with the Yonna dance, we play more.
Well.
What else could it be?
We'd be happy to listen.
You can play the song if you want,
the one you said you were going to play, another one.
No, no, if you want, I can play another instrument.
Let's continue, that was the sound of the turompa, and
Well,
I'm going to play the turompa with a sound
called the jumping dog
or the jayariyu dog
it's called the jayariyu dog, meaning from my clan
We identify ourselves with eirüku.
Well, you Arijunas call it a clan,
but it's not a clan, it's the eiruku
which is my
mother, who are part of the interclanial,
they are a family to us
we don't have any interclanial part,
at least my children are not my children,
my children are the children of my sisters,
and the children of their daughters are my children
because they belong to my clan, my eirüku
and we play a tune from the eirüku like this.
Oh, oh, oh
un muy
Well, that's a rhythm
that I have always played,
and with music, melodies as well,
I play it with fusion music with other non-Wayuu instruments.
I'm going to play a rhythm,
about what one feels, what one thinks,
what
is called, it's called the sounds of the earth.
Yes, when you feel the earth, you feel the wind, a noise,
and it's in this way like this.
How do you learn your songs?
Do you create some yourself,
but do others pass down through generations?
No, no, no, the music comes from oneself,
sometimes we imitate others
another rhythm from a fellow musician,
but most of it comes from our own inspiration
in the moment one thinks and feels
and what one sees
as I just mentioned, in nature,
these are the things that teach us
The teachers are the plants, animals, and birds
The wind makes the music.
Well,
I think we are going to play the casimba rhythm here.
When you draw water from the well,
it produces sounds that are sounds of lament.
And it goes like this.
Oh oh, oh
oh. Oh
Those are the sounds.
What is that thing down there?
This is a calabash, called "aliita"
in Wayunaiki, it's a gourd that we have
This is "mokochira" (plant).
Yes, we always put this on it, sometimes
as an ornament to hold it.
And it can be disassembled like this
so we can store it
It can be taken apart and assembled like clarinets.
Right?
They call them the same way.
And that's it.
In which
environments?
Usually, the music is played
I mean, during the day.
Well, I was saying some are for the night.
Yes, some of them have specific rituals.
This instrument is only for daytime,
it cannot be played
at night because, according to the elders,
if we do so at night, it calls
bad energies, because at that time they are resting,
they rest to think,
to prepare for the next day and speak, speaking well,
the horn normally, yes.
The "kasha" can also be played at any time,
because "kasha" is sometimes used for food gatherings.
They say the "tambora" too.
We copied the drums that the Spaniards brought
to our territory with snare drums.
We observed them and, because of the need the Wayuu people had
to create something harmonious to maintain the sound,
to keep the dance.
And that's how the "kasha" was created, but using our own materials,
like the plant: this is a plant, and these are animal skins.
Here, we have the generational aspect that is part of
our cosmovision.
of the generational aspect while playing exactly.
And this, well, it's a material that has no life,
it's metallic, brought by the colonizers,
and then we make music with it.
And what about the red thing?
We use this as an ornament to maintain the
energy and harmony.
to identify ourselves because this one is mine.
I identify myself with this color
and the colors and the tassel,
so we use it as an ornament to keep it that way.
And what's that thing there?
This is a "Koushut," that's what it's called,
but today we make it as the maestro Enrique has it,
with a feather, it's called "karatsü,"
and it's used for dancing the "yonna," as part of the presentation,
but it's used more to identify us
if one is a good musician,
a good craftsman.
Yes, in the past, it was used to identify during wars,
when there were interclan or Spanish wars,
they would wear it.
There's one called "tu'upana,"
and this one is called "koushut."
They wore them to identify themselves
amongst each other, to show who was the leader
So it's a symbol of leadership within the interclan group.
If I wear it, I identify myself a lot,
and people recognize me with this a lot.
wherever I go, I have ones in different colors,
depending on the outfit I wear, the guayabera,
or if I wear my traditional clothing, perhaps
if you come tomorrow, you'll see me dressed in it.
How important do you consider music?
Is it like everyone in the community ends up
being a musician in some way,
the children, the adults?
How does music affect you?
How does it change you?
Music comes as a legacy,
a legacy of the family.
Not all Wayuu are musicians, it's a legacy.
And if we teach the children all the instruments, maybe they'll learn one
the one they like, maybe
this one or any other, but not all of them will learn.
If I have 40 children, all 40
won't learn to play all the instruments.
Maybe one or two will become good at playing
the maasi or the sawawa, but
over time they grow to like it and they learn it
on their own,
by listening and observing. We learn
through observation and listening,
we don't write, we don't record,
it's all by ear, just listening and observing.
That's how we learn.
And that's the legacy we have in school,
the legacy left by my uncle.
Master Jorge Enrique, who is there in the picture,
the legacy of our grandparents,
that's the legacy they give us, and they are concerned
because they say that those of us who are left,
because they have already gone to rest in jepira,
we have to preserve and conserve
the music through this,
what we do as a school, we call it
Ekiraja in our language, but
in your art as arijuna (non-Wayuu),
we call it school, as you can see the looms as well,
the women make their weavings
which we need to wear the siira (traditional dress).
Everything has a legacy
and a spiritual connotation,
because that's what women allow us to do,
If we don't make the music, if we don't have women
to make these things for us, we can't make the music
because with them, we also
think and feel to sing
and make music for them.
And songs? Are there songs about love too?
Yes, yes, there are songs, Jayechi,
but I don't sing Jayechi because it's a spiritual song.
Yes, that's it, everyone has their own theme,
and those songs are mostly sung by people who are experienced
if there's a spiritual healing song,
it's sung by a woman Outsü,
who is the spiritual authority, sung by women singers, and
and men also sing it
during parties
when they are drinking, when there's chirrinchi (Wayuu alcoholic beverage)
they start singing Jayechi
and they are anecdotes that tell their history
in their language.
And are there songs
that are not their own,
but have been passed down? I mean, songs
that everyone knows or that musicians know someone created
and have been interpreted again
No, if you hear
a Wayuu singing a non-Wayuu song, he might sing a ranchera.
Why?
Because on the coast,
the first people who arrived in our territory
were Mexicans.
That's what our elders tell us.
That's why we use the tin cups where
you drank from
are from Mexico.
Those tin cups are not from us: they came since the conquest.
So if you ask an elderly Wayuu man to sing you a song,
he might sing a ranchera.
Why? Because it's a legacy that comes from
years ago,
our elders say that within our music,
the first music that arrived,
which is not ours, was rancheras.
Not even vallenato, because vallenato was created here.
The accordion vallenato was created here
it was created in La Guajira and spread to the south
It reached Valledupar
and in Valledupar, vallenato music was created
because it was originally played with a guitar, and then the accordion was introduced
because it is a music, practically
we can say it's indigenous
because the tambora drum
comes from Africa, from the African or Afro people
and the guacharaca is also indigenous
because it comes from the Sierra Nevada.
Really? Well, it's interesting that here on the peninsula
a lot has been influenced by the Wayuu, from what I've read and heard.
Well, there have been exchanges
between different cultural elements
from all around the Caribbean, Mexico, North America.
Yes, of course.
A point of
exchange.
Of course, that's why there's so much mixing.
My grandfather was Dutch, because he passed away.
That's why my last name is Prince.
That's what my grandfather said,
my father, that when the ships arrived
on the coastal shore,
in Puerto López, he arrived and fell in love with my grandmother.
They lived on Carrizal beach, where we will go tomorrow,
That's why that territory belongs to my father, but my own territory
of the clan is around here, in the border area,
but I have rights because my dad was from there.
And we always lived off
the traditional economy of the beach, which is fishing.
And that's because we have the sea,
we are "apalanchi" in our language,
"apalanchi" are people who have the sea.
Well
I have a question
I would like to know
if men are the ones who
make the music,
what role do women have, what is their role?
So beyond receiving the music,
what role do they have?
Well,
women also play instruments
there's an instrument that is played with the hand
but it's played by girls,
not by older women, it's the wawai and the iruwai made from a small tree
I don't have it here, but maybe they have it over there with the kids
The kids can play that instrument,
most of the girls play it
And also, as I mentioned before, for us,
it's very important for a woman
to be able to make music and those who sing "jayechi"
in their "jayechi," they sing anecdotes
of their history, of themselves,
of what they experience, sadness or sorrow.
Yes, like a song where they compose the music themselves.
Yes, very important. Women also make music,
but here, it depends on the fundamental work
they do because in Wayuu culture,
we have a normative system
a plan where each person has their fundamental occupation,
the woman has her fundamental occupation
and the man also has his fundamental occupation,
that's why we always maintain the Wayuu culture
and preserve cultural expressions through
the social organization we have.
What is the occupation of each one?
What is the occupation of both women and men?
Well, the occupation of women is diverse.
There are women Outsü (spiritual guide)
there are women Oulaküt (visionary)
there are women einülü (craftswoman)
and women eikülü (educator) and atükalü (ceramist)
These are the five fundamental occupations of Wayuu women
and for men, there's the pütchipüi (speaker)
the Wayuu alaüla, who is
the maternal uncle, Wayuu ekirajasu (teacher)
sunai tu wakuwaipakat (our culture), that's how it would be seen,
look, I have my hand here,
This one here is the grandmother, and this is the mother
and this one
is the maternal uncle, and this one is the child,
so to make my instrument, I have to grasp it
from my grandmother, my mother, in order to grasp the knife
and they teach me how to make the instrument.
The woman is always present in the worldview
and here too, mom is here,
oushi (grandmother), tatushi (my maternal uncle)
because the achon (son)
the achon here no longer has a clan,
he is here, holding it, and I make the instrument in this way
when I hold the reed, look, there it is
holding the mother, oushi
Grandmother and mother
the Wayuu woman is always there
and the maternal uncle here in the middle,
this is the maternal uncle,
he is the one who exercises authority, who enforces
behavior within the community
there they are.
We are always five, five manifestations
which are
mother tongue, spirituality,
territory, social organization, and traditional economy.
There are the five on the finger
and there are also the five.
Grandmother
What is this one? Mother, maternal uncle,
the grandson, and achon (son)
There are the five, and that is
they are always part of the organization,
the woman is always present
That's why it's called
"eei" which means mother.
Eei.
Thank you.
Well, if you had a message
that you would like to share with the world, what would it be?
The message would be
well, these days we had the visit
of the president, it was quite hard for us,
it was a good visit
and what the president said about us,
about what he said
about us.
I have always said one thing,
life is sacred,
life to make music is sacred, and life for us
is very important,
because when we die, we go to another life,
we are not dead, that's why they hold wakes for us
and when our remains are exhumed
they say that we are still alive and still here on earth,
I mean, as I said at the beginning, we don't go
even to the right hand of God, we don't go to hell,
instead, we have a long journey,
and that long journey is the message
that I bring to the Wayuu community and to the whole world.
to make them aware that
in the department of La Guajira, there is an indigenous people
that has its own music,
that has spirituality, has principles,
values to maintain the music
and harmony of the Wayuu people.
That's the message I can bring, and for them to know
the music, to listen to the "sawawa,"
the sonorous music
of our Wayuu instruments.
And to confirm that everything you've said
we have knowledge to use it in the documentary
and the music as well.
Do you allow it? I mean,
Would you allow us to use your music
or what you played
to be part of this project we are working on?
Well, yes, I can do that, but we
are protective in the sense that
it is for a good purpose
not just for you but also for us,
because you are taking a legacy
it's not something trivial
because this is not something you can find in a music store,
like a guitar, like a trumpet, you can't find
any of these instruments or the Kasha.
It's an effort that we make to manufacture
and create it.
No, not to make it for the need to sell,
but a necessity that we have as a people.
Wayuu to maintain and preserve our cultural expressions
through our spirituality.
So, if people see a picture of Saüyepia (the school)
or maybe of me on social media and they are promoting it,
they might think that I am
selling, that I have money, and since I live here,
these chairs, these benches are for the girls
and boys who come to listen to the music,
this piece of zinc that you see there with holes,
is where we make the music.
Not long ago, we won some money
and when the president came, we had those looms made
so that the women and girls can make the "siira"
(men's sash) with the threads, and that was earned
because someone came to give something to us.
And we are going to Bogotá
to perform in the first week of August,
we will spend a week there
a large group from Saüyepia, from the school
to showcase the music and the dance expression.
We are going to a gathering of indigenous peoples
and we are the ones representing La Guajira, the Wayuu people
it's us from the school
we will be there in the first week of August
I will go with my group,
more than 15 girls here, between boys and girls
and then I'll go alone on the 22nd
until the 26th.
That will be from August 6th to 13th at the Teatro Colón,
we will perform at the Teatro Colón
and at the Centro Nacional de Arte, the Nuevo Teatro.
Maestro Iván Benavides,
who is the director
in Bogotá.
From the sixth to the thirteenth of August.
And then I come back again.
I come with my big group,
and then I go alone with another person,
I perform at the university, I think it's the Javeriana.
From the 23rd to the 27th of the same month.
So that's what I'm saying,
what we want is,
maybe as a donation,
it's not for me, it's for all of us,
that's how we sustain ourselves,
and look for the materials because we can't find them here,
we have to search for them in the Sierra de la Macuira
or in the Sierra Nevada,
where the Wiwa people are, who lend us their territory,
and I have to ask for permission to gather the
materials to maintain more instruments
and do everything
with the children of the school.
Yes, tomorrow we have an activity
I'm inviting you because it's a community
where they are going to hold an event, a harmonization ritual,
and they invite us to participate.
I will talk to the people,
I'll tell them you're coming
I know they won't say no, so you can come with us,
and maybe you can record a video or interview us,
which also helps us to sustain ourselves.
the
the school, you know.
If what we don't want is that
because it has happened to us
not only with people
like you but also with people from here in La Guajira
who sometimes take our material and publish it.
At least it happened during the pandemic
they took images
from a video we made, for a festival in Uribia,
but there was no festival
and the authorities took it
took it and published it during the pandemic
and all the mothers called me because I hadn't seen
that the girls were in the publication
and I called, I sent a formal request to the governor, and immediately
they took it down from the networks
and I left it at that because I wanted to, I didn't want to,
I didn't want to sue them for copyright either
because they didn't have permission to publish that
and they were selling that as material.
And that's because we really didn't give
any permission, and it has happened to us several times
with images of us
because, honestly, and it's not to tell a lie
The only school that exists
with Wayuu characteristics is us.
And here in La Guajira
there are more than 600 cultural foundations
We are a cultural foundation through the school
and we are the only ones with cultural character
it's us
and we showed it to the Ministry of Culture
when the president came.
we
we met with the Minister of Culture and the Vice Minister
they sat down with the entire Ministry's leadership,
Population, Heritage, with us
and they didn't let anyone else in
because many people wanted to enter,
here at the Mayor's Office, and they said no,
we are only going to have the meeting with Saüyepia with you from the school,
So that was just for us.
They took an impression of us
asked, "How do you live? Why do you do this?"
"What time have you been working with culture?"
We told them everything.
Firstly, the truth is that we do not have support
from the municipality or the department, we live on what
suddenly comes, people like you who visit us and bring us
that's how we live and from politicians
that sometimes give us coats, shoes when we go to Bogota
so we live from donations.
We work with cooperation
we have some allies,
a school just like this one, but for African drums
we have
and I have drums in there that have been given to us,
they are a school of drums
in La Boquilla, Cartagena, which are Afro drums.
and we have a project called School
of Knowledge of Cultural Rights.
With them, we create a cultural life plan
to maintain and preserve everything cultural.
That's why I'm telling you
I told my friend that not just anyone
we let in, only those who do this,
Yes, yes, because it has value,
not just money, but cultural value,
the value it has as a people
which is ancient, what we have.
Well, then we'll keep in touch,
We collaborate, and before publishing anything, first
Of course, with our name,
the address of a school here in La Guajira,
of course, exactly with our name
and yes, look
I'm also going to give you a photo
and a thousand more.
That's it,
what I'm up to.
You don't have to
do.
It's good to start with the introduction and
Well,
it's a photo that I'm going to give you, a Polaroid.
I don't know if you've seen it, but it shows...
But before we do that,
Can you say it again
Just so we make sure that
Of course, where are we now?
The school.
And I say that in Wayuunaiki is fine too.
What do I have to say?
Just your name.
And that you authorize in the school.
In the school
which is what it's called here
My name is such, we are in your school
in Uribia
The date, and we are sharing a bit
of our knowledge.
Okay? Music, okay.
Got it.
Well, my name is Joaquín Prince
from the Eirüku Jayariyu, and we are here
at the traditional school "Semillero Wayuu," Saüyepia Wayuu,
and sharing with you
the cultural richness through music, through
the spirituality of our community.
Well, thank you for this visit
It's very good that you come, get to know
all this cultural legacy that we have.
As you can see, this is the space we have
this is a sacred space for us,
because here we maintain all the richness with spirituality
of the Master Jorge Enrique,
who passed away, leaving us this legacy.
And we want you to know it as well,
that you take it far and get to know the school
that from where Colombia begins,
there is a school that is strengthening
and preserving the richness of Wayuu music.