Can you explain what you are doing?
This is a portable lamp.
A Solar LED lamp
Well this is what we did
in India.
I can put together this plate,
but since the batteries are already there.
With this lot,
this lamp charges
From the sunlight,
This one is 10 volts.
Yeah,
10 volts and 7 amperes
I,
From India I learned to assemble.
This is the plate of this lamp
that I can put together myself.
These are the components.
Yes, they are the components.
Here are the resistors.
These are resistors.
These are,
resistors.
These are the
AISI.
The diodes, the
capacitors that are diodes.
This is an offer .
This is a transformer, a capacitor.
This is another capacitor.
This is a
I knew this
and I learned that there.
These are the components of this plate.
I can put this together
and I have my book, through the book it was
that I learned to put together
each component.
If I don't set this up well, it doesn't turn on.
But through this
I repeated it every day, the teacher would tell us
that a resistance of
R22.
Well, they taught us colors
because resistors have colors.
The red, the yellow,
the black, the green because they have a voltage.
We do the math
through colors.
They taught us.
This is a 22k resistor
and I have to search
the little plate
It has its numbering where I have to
put.
Well,
This is a lamp plate.
It's this one here.
I can teach
the boys, just like they taught me and I didn’t know
what voltage, well voltage yes, because I learned
that the numbers, that we have to do the math,
the basics.
I didn't learn that quickly.
Yeah.
So with each one of those you put them together for the other
people from the community?
Yes, of course, because after the course they send us this.
The government has to finance the school
so they can send us the material
and to electrify the community.
“Barefoot school” (Barefoot College) in India,
and this is a PCB plate
of a control that is this one that is here.
This is how they gave it to us like this in India.
“Go set up!”
Do they just send you that?
Yes, they give us this
back in India, that's what I did every day.
To set this up.
The components, they gave us the components, just like this.
So it comes simple like this
and you put everything together?
Yeah.
From the beginning?
From the beginning, from scratch.
Just as it is.
There's the end.
Until it turns on.
This is a control, a loading control
which controls the charge from the solar to the battery so that
it keeps.
Yes, this is a 40 volt charge.
and 10 amperes.
Yeah
This
They asked us. “This name!”,
“This name!” said the teacher
and we repeated what he said first,
“PCB!” first repeated. “PCB!”
And he said “This name?” “PCB!”.
Okay, “Charge Controller!” meaning the control
Do you understand me that English? Or is that English?
Yes, it is! (Laughs)
And that's how we learned it
“Charge Controller!” “This name?”
“PCB!”,
“This name?” “Charge Controller!”
and so then the components
aha, “This name?” in “resistance!”,
Oh, “resistance”
and so on.
We learned each one's name
“This name?” the teacher “This name!”
Yes,
In this organization, what is the importance
that it is women who learn?
Well, it says at school because we are grandmothers,
and we stay in the community
teaching our children or our grandchildren
and that is why the importance of women is
because she is the one who is always in the community
and men don't, they leave,
“Men drink” they said.
That's why it's so important
Elder women,
because if they are young, they also go to the city.
On the other hand, the mothers are grandmothers, and they already stay at home.
That is the importance.
That's what they explained to us in India.
Do you believe in that too?
Yes. Well, that is.
And how does it work?
the solar panel,
goes through what regulator to charge the batteries?
And then when can you use it?
Well, the regulator is this, that is,
is this.
This is the control that regulates the load
from solar to battery.
It keeps it.
It does not burn the battery, but it has already reached its cycle.
Ten years it’s ten years.
There are only five years of lifespan for a battery.
Time has passed,
but when this was given to the community the lights turned on.
Happy, happy.
What happiness!
This is the page
from the school.
You get in there
And that
when the community brought it to me
all this disassembled, burned.
Sure,
I have a spare
because they sent me spare parts from India and I can repair,
give them again.
But if they don't want to make the payment.
Yes. What is the payment?
It's $5,000 pesos a month for maintenance.
If, for example, that battery or this one finished its cycle,
With that cash, with that money,
I can buy the battery,
Go back and turn on the lamp again.
But if the community does not collaborate
with the payment, which is $5,000 pesos per month.
I have told them they can kill a goat and
That goat makes $60,000 a year.
Yes, it's nothing.
But they don't have the money for that, or they don't want to pay?
No, they do have.
But, with just a goat,
one goes and sells that goat,
And it’s 60, annually, it’s 60
is that worth it?
Of course, or even more.
and let's say,
how to give them the importance,
that is, make them realize the importance
of electricity?
Right now they are suffering,
They are?
Yes, they are feeling the suffering
because everyone is off.
Sure thing.
So how to give importance?, come back,
re-electrify.
oh well, fix this again
turn it back on and new batteries.
But here’s a thing,
pay for a year in
advanced, with that money
that which is going to be deposited in a bank.
It's not for me,
It's for the committee, because there is a committee.
I have an association called Azoperro,
I have the association.
And with that association the money is managed?
It is managed, the money is put in
which is maintenance and which is not for me.
And let's say, I see that you have there
television?
Before it turned on.
Did it turn on before?
It had Direct TV, it had wi -fi
Also my battery is already dead,
but I think and think about it a lot,
I have to replace it,
I'm going to replace it.
and where do you get the materials for that?
There, there
It is also sold in Uribia.
That's worth it, it's worth like every battery from that big one
It's costing like a million pesos.
Umm , yes a million pesos.
There are three large batteries
so that I can turn my workshop back on, because sometimes
I start to repair,
I concentrate.
Yes, I have, I don't like knitting, I don't like knitting.
I don't like it, I don't have patience.
Do you love electronics?
It's the one I like the most, it entertains me.
Yes, yes, I like it better.
Let's say, a project, but it's not like
individual, but
solar panels, but much bigger
to electrify
everything, is that something you have thought about, thinking about how to make it bigger?
Not like each house has its own,
but to enlarge the project and make it like one?
They have done census here, they say...
that they are going to electrify
the entire Upper guajira with large solar panels,
to turn on a refrigerator, I don't know, but that takes a while.
That's what I'm waiting for. Hopefully.
You can lead the project.
Yes, that's what they told me,
but I don't know how to wait.
The companies that are here, Helios.
Tell us a little more
from the school they want to open
where they want you to be a teacher.
What is it about?
That's there in Cabo de la Vela.
Well they want to do
that project there like in India,
that women learn to
repair their own equipment for maintenance,
because it is going to be electrified
in that area due to the wind zone.
That's what I understand.
They told me like this.
So they are going to hire me to teach. “This name?”
I don't know if they are going to bring the material from India, I don't know,
Until now, I don’t.
But is it in association with them or do they want to do it separately?
Apart, yes apart.
They are on it,
They are already communicating with the school.
and they are going to bring a teacher from India
In order to reinforce.
Sure to reinforce.
Yeah
and let's say there are no initiatives for that here,
I mean, like he's a teacher from here?
I don't know, I think so, of course, there must be,
but they want to bring it like in India.
Because do they learn like this
illiterate, semi-literate.
It is a strategy that they have to
learn.
Are you
an electrical engineer?
We set this up there.
It's very impressive.
I don't know about that, it seems very complicated.
Me too.
I said on the plane, what am I going to know about mathematics?
I did not know anything.
But you learned to weld and everything.
Yes of course.
Here I do it, easily.
I weld.
I grab here and there.
This
So
I have practiced that already.
and do you have the iron, the solder?
I have everything, everything, everything, everything, everything.
And how could you weld if there is no power?
There isn’t because my batteries have already arrived to their lifespan too.
They no longer heat up during the cycle.
Yeah.
Would receiving more batteries mean receiving that payment from the communities?
Yes of course.
They have to each one.
It costs 1 million pesos every five years,
well, you can surely save a million pesos in five years.
Yes of course.
75 communities, or people?
75 families, in Macuira too.
And here.
Yes, in Macuira.
And can you pass us the book?
The book?
Is the same.
Did you learn
in English then?
No, I wish I learned English.
Here it is
I have all these tools, I have them all.
Yes, but the book is not in Spanish.
No, I have brought translated
some when I had wifi, I started translating.
I translated some of them
because
I want to know what this is called in Spanish and I
I learned it was just (in English). Here are them all, the resistances,
of how many,
all these little things.
[Interviewers,
let's say, since it was like 10 years ago,
with the updates of technology,
do you think there will be new ways to do it?
Ah, I think that already in India, at school,
I saw, I get in
always on the page, I see that they are more different.
Yes, they are back and lamp.
Then you should get technical.
Become even more expert.
Clear
That's what we want
So we send you back to India?
Yeah,
or right here.
There’s no need.
Is it possible right here?
Of course you can.
Look
the colors that I learned every day they taught us.
I said why do we learn that color, I already know black,
I already know the brown, I know the red.
We didn't understand why they taught us colors every day,
the numbers.
Do you know how much a thousand volts is in colors?
thousand volts
It is a black and 000 that is the black, black, black.
I took courses on this, I also know how to put them together,
but then also the same thing.
I knew them.
AHA. I said in India, for what?
If I already know the black,
I already know red and I know, we didn't understand, because
when they taught us resistance, Ah! It’s the resistance,
So this was not for the semi-literate either.
You also have to look at mathematics.
Yes, but then they taught you…
Here and here, for example, one does the math, here it is.
And did they teach you to draw then
how much voltage is there?
If there is that much voltage, how much resistance is there?
like in math and like amperage times voltage.
Yes, but a little.
I learned those amperes.
Sure.
Here it is, go,
the volts, do the math.
I already learned this
and I said oh no,
because they said it was for illiterate people,
which is not so much for the illiterate,
I said when they showed me these numbers.
But did you know how to read?
Of course, I am
high school.
My grandmother has been in second grade.
There were women until they reached second grade.
and they learned.
They learned hard but cool.
Yeah.
These are my teachers.
Look how cute.
I knew all this.
This is Teacher Magan.
They dressed us as Hindu.
Yes, she does, she is very cool,
He lent us his things, he dressed us as Hindu.
I have photos of me dressed as Hindu.
These are the teachers.
This is a man who
uses crutches.
Yes Yes Yes.
Teacher Umán is cooler.
“Teacher, Problem?”
No.
No problem.
No problem , he told me.
With that, with that patience,
It was with him that we learned the most.
We said every day, women, “teacher problem!”.
I mean, as it is, I don't learn, I don't know.
And he said no problem , no problem .
He was so cool.
Him,
But more than all he and this one.
He,
who was my teacher too,
I think he is the one who is going to come.
Um , he was in Guatemala and has formed a school
in Guatemala with Rodrigo Paris.
Do you know when he's coming or when it is?
When school is here, they told me.
And who is organizing the school thing?
The People of Ipse .
That now with Petro and him
They are with Ecopetrol,
they are going to finance
and I think this is the one that's going to come.
I don't know,
He told me like this, all of these are teachers.
This is a little different topic,
but what changes have you seen in the environment?
Here?
here.
Well, at the beginning there was a change, of course,
there was joy because
People could charge their cell phones.
The children studied at night, did homework,
I think they're back
the same as before and it makes me sad
sometimes.
That's when they invite me and say
What is the progress? how it moves forward if that is backwards
and it’s embarrassing for me to say that
let's say
because children study and that is not known
have put in the effort to say well then
is that they are no longer studying,
I can't charge my cell phone anymore, like they haven't said how
please take and buy me a battery, fix it .
No, nobody,
but that is the commitment.
If any organization arrives
to provide us with the battery, that's what I plan to do,
In other words, get the family involved
that has to advance
money
and we electrify them, if they don’t want to,
It is not electrified.
But is that
It is something very small, but it shines.
This little light shines a lot at night,
There are four for each family,
One here in the kitchen, on the bed inside
and lasts all night.
And does it charge every day?
Every day.
This is the,
here it connects,
here we connect the,
we make the connection here,
here we connect,
We connect here.
This is the positive and negative.
Well then
here the panels are connected,
positive-negative solar panels
Battery.
We connect here.
This is for the lamps
in the four lamp.
Have you never shorted by mistake?
Didn't it short out or burn?
No, because you have to be very careful that one
do not connect the positive to the negative
If any of the resistors is shorted or burned
Ever
And how do you know when they are burned?
With the,
with the... what's his name, the tester
Oh, do you have a tester ?
Yes too.
Do you have a multimeter too?
Yeah.
You have everything.
With that I
I realize.
already.
Well.
Yeah.
That
I mean.
How is this connected here?
Oh, okay.
And how much do you know how to say it?
How he has control of it.
But do you know how charged they are or not?
Because here he has the little light when he shines.
AHA.
When it is green he is charging.
Good.
When it is red it means it is not charging.
to that.
You don't know if they are 100% at 50?
No.
It is not measured with the tester.
Oh okay, and he tells you how much?
Yes of course.
How much voltage does the battery have?
How much is the voltage?
Maximum 12. 12 and.
12.5?
No, ten is not carrying our load.
It has to be 12.5.
13 is fine.
Charge to be in English.
We have access. Very good.
Okay, yes.
Well
well, it is very lamp.
I hope they turn on again.
Before they did.
It's not very modern,
but it is something very, very necessary for the community.
It is very necessary because one can go to the neighbor at night
and he carries this in his hand, shining.
Look how we get to night.
All dark.
Total,
Yes, the light bulb is going to go out now.
Mmmmmmmmm well, it's working. Yeah,
It's like that, she already knows.
But you know, you learned it from my mom?
That is, I had six months in a school in the summer.
Yes, she, you know, she's a helper.
There you go.
There. Wait please.
Oh.
What if you already
You know, all the components of putting it together and so on.
Ahhhh
and
that we must move forward
but don't do it because it's not easy, quite
easy, though.
That's how it is.
There is also a lot about passing on knowledge.
The generation.
Yes to the one I'm missing in the living room.
No
here is the free room.
But you know.
concentration is needed
because it also comes
many people here visiting and
It's already driving me out of control.
Clear.
Because that is a concentration, it is closed in 1/4,
No
change the row.
The women are concentrated from there because they don't
They don't know how to cook or anything.
Oh, sure, yes.
Pure class, pure class
from 8 to 12 and from 2 to 5.
Every day in the afternoon.
So we got up at eight.
Yes Yes.
And concentrated there because
We no longer thought about children, nor about
not even in the goats,
like it says in the book.
We had to forget about the goats of the
I.
Did you ask
Was Oscar O Car left here alone?
Yes how are you.
Excellent.
You know everything is fine, he said.
He never said it was wrong.
Oh, of course, and everything is fine, he said.
He sits.
And there I was, that from and Venezuela
and he didn't want to leave them alone here.
With the other family.
There, yes, with my sister.
Sure, but very bi
AND
Well.
Wow, complicated.
But you know. It. What is
in sight,
No?
Well, barely.
If I ask him outside.
Yeah.
And he learned that whole book.
Of course, I
I say of course, it is.