Good morning, my name is Magalys Polanco,
of Pausayu lineage from usijo'jewat
I am here to talk to you about the role of
the woman within the wayuu people
The woman in our culture is the base of everything
Women are the basis of our existence
same as wayuu
Because we are
The generators of lives, we guide our
children to maintain us as a people
That's why we are sacred and with great value
within our culture
Because we are transmitting from generation to generation
in generation our legacy as wayuu
From them comes, for example
Our social organization, as well as me who
I am from the Pausayu lineage
We will always be of our mother's lineage
because it is from her that we come
That is why we do not carry the lineage of our father but of our mother.
In addition, women are formative mothers because they are
those who guide children from an early age
They train children, instill in them values
And he instills principles in them from childhood.
That is, women have many roles
essential in our culture
We form from our womb, we
we breastfeed and then take care of them and raise them
We teach them about the different roles and
trades within our territory
And in our house, how to look for water, wash
and other chores
Both at home and in general
How to help graze, to get the milk.
Teach him to be immersed with animals
teach girls how to make
hammocks and backpacks
The woman herself is the base of everything because she is
the one with more roles than the man
Although man also plays a role that in
In this case, the maternal uncle is the one who advocates for the family
He is the one who sits down to solve a
conflict through dialogue
And we also instilled that in them, that they have to
respect your uncles
We tell our children
we too
We train our girls when they become
ladies we can do it mothers or grandmothers
We take care of her and guide her in the ritual of confinement
in her first menstruation
And he is taken out of the house until he finishes his
first menstruation
During and after this ritual you are given some
Wayuu medicinal plants
And they are our jobs as Wayuu women
When our daughters grow up, you are ready.
for marriage
They get married, the man asks for her hand if he sees that it is
a good woman
It is there where the maternal uncle or his father sits at
discuss commitment
To agree to agreements in order to close the commitment
before the wedding
That's one of the uncle's roles
Another thing, a woman
When there is a conflict
You must find a way to soften men
She is the one who knows how to talk to them and how to appease their anger
You need to tell them it's not okay to be in conflict
should never aggravate the problem but the opposite
Women should always talk to men
as well as their children in the midst of some problem
She must always emphasize to them that she is not
okay to be in conflict with others
That's why she's always willing to solve it
to give their jewels as a reward
She says here I have my animals so that
reward the problem and thus be in harmony
and this is more or less the role of women
in the wayuu culture
When our daughters have their husband
We must look for his uncle or his father if there is none
To be the representative of the family
in the commitment
The mother tells her brother about the marriage proposal
So, he must ask for the dowry for the bride, that is, animals.
The necklaces, cows, goats among others.
Although I emphasize that in ancient times mules were requested
I clarify that this is not buying the woman but
gain respect in the bride's family
What man buys are animals and
goods to be respected and valued
In his wife's family, that's why it's important
delivery of the dowry by the man
If the man does not give the dowry, he is not valued or respected
Is that how it works
When a woman gets married
Well, now I'm going to talk about my trade
I have been working on something for 10 years when I went
India
Ten years ago when I went to India
I lived there for six months
I was gone
To embark on a new experience during the
time I was
I went to take a course where we teach you
Of electricity
I learned to make a lamp
I learned how to make a controller, one that works
through solar energy
By means of a battery, that was what I learned there
Although it was very difficult for me because I didn't
knew the language of the Hindus
It got very complicated for me, but I made signs to
communicate with them
And thanks to that I learned a lot of things from
there and of the Hindus
And when I got back from India they told me I had to
bring electricity to my community
And they sent me materials for that
As for 75 families in the community
Although it took 2 years to get there because I
sent by boat to the community
And with what the arijunas gave us
(people from other cultures)
I organized everything so that each family had solar energy
Although now they are no longer working almost because
it's already years old
The batteries are already worn out and old.
Although we are already looking for help
with new batteries
However, for now we will be without power. we came back
to how we were before without energy with nothing
Although my wish is that we have energy again
So that the children do not suffer at night
to do homework and so on
'Cause children in the dark can't do
nothing to advance with your studies
And I would like some foundation or organization
Will help us
For the energy to return, because I am willing
to do everything possible to achieve it
For my community, I just need some materials
like batteries
Because the rest is
However, I am happy to have brought the
source of solar energy to my community
That same one I instill in the children of now
That is, I teach them how devices work like
circuit boards
And the children really like being taught
Well, that's what I can share with you.
that experience
In our culture women have an important value
So much so that when they separate, the family weighs more
of his mother in a decision
Yes, the maternal uncle is like the father, the father
biological does not have as much implication
Could you tell us a little more about that topic?
Why our social organization starts
of our mother
Yes, it has always been through the matrilineal line
and not from the father
I explain a little more, yes, well.
Ready? Yeah.
Our matrilineal line is strong
Because when a father separates from his wife
the matrilineal is what prevails
Since we are the ones who stay
with our children
The mothers are the ones who form and the father alone
It is practically biological
He can leave and nothing happens, because the father
of our children is our brother as a mother
The maternal uncle is the one who weighs when it comes to taking
decisions about our children
That's why if the father wants to leave, he leaves and nothing happens
Because what is important is the matrilineal lineage
through the clan
for this reason, women are the foundation of our organization
social from mother
On the other hand, the father does not, because he does not influence so much
that's why you can go normal
Could you say where we are now and what is
the difference here with Manaure and Uribia?
What he wanted to say?
Where are we now?
And what is the difference here with the other areas?
I don't know Manaure that well
Well now we meet in Nazareth
what is the north zone
The way of speaking here is very different from those in Uribia
They say shia we jia but both
they mean the same (that)
What we have here is a bit of ease with
the water, and it's quiet territory
The land is good for animals because
there is grass and that gives us more animals
And when there is no grass, they still feed in the mountains
On the other hand, in Uribia, I understand that there are
lack of drinking water and that the temperature is even higher
Here we are fine, well in this northern area
Now we are in Ksyushupanoi the
my father's territory
Here they love us very much, they treat us well and they respect us a lot.
That's why we are together living in harmony
Here we are very happy
And how constant is it for you to be in a city
versus being in a field?
Being in the city is not easy because there are
to buy everything there
You have to always have money, something we don't have
Instead, here we have our animals
so as not to suffer from hunger
We are going to Nazareth to sell our sheep, our
goats and from them we get food
We don't spend buying other things because here
we have what it takes
We have milk that animals give us, meat and
our own garden
Where we plant grains, pumpkin corn and a little bit of everything
Therefore, we do not suffer from anything here, but rather
otherwise we live well
and we are fine
We do not have to be thinking about what we are going to
eat because we live well fortunately
And as. If we have our own milk,
meat, fruits and others
Unlike the city
If a young man goes to study in the city, he goes through
many needs
He begins to miss his territory and what
he fed here
On the other hand, in the city you must have money to
everything or else you will suffer
Well, that's what those who have gone to study at the University have told us.
Those who have already experienced it
Because the others have not gone because there is no money or
rather because his mom doesn't have it
As soon as they finish high school they stay
just here and now
Can you explain to me what are the sacred sites there?
and which ones are we going to see tomorrow?
One of the sacred sites is Wolunka from where
it's me, that's my territory
Where does my mother come from and my grandmother is there
Because where we are now belongs to my dad
Uriana (Magalys's father's bloodline)
I am Pausayu and my father Uriana
Can you explain to me too, like tomorrow
we are going to some places
What is the importance they have?
You understand me? No.
He says that like tomorrow we are going to meet
some sacred sites
They would like to know the importance of these sacred sites
Wolunka
According to the stories of the ancestors it was a woman
That she had teeth in her vagina
And there were also two young brothers
Those who worried about leaving descendants.
They saw Wolunka when she bathed
They saw the teeth in her vagina and they knew
that they couldn't even make her fall in love
But they said they needed to leave descendants,
So they planned to knock out his teeth
Where they knocked out his teeth, the water remained
reddish with Wolunka's blood
You can also see the footprints and the stone from where you
they released the arrow, tomorrow we will see it
That is the origin of that sacred site because the
woman was called Wolunka
Alewalu, where we go tomorrow is also sacred
Because since ancient times they used to find
valuable stones
How tu'uma or other valuable stones they used
our ancestors
That is why they also called it a sacred site.
because in it they found the most precious stones
To make the jewels that we have inherited
our ancestors
Of the stones of alewalu
Where are the waterfalls? Yeah. That's where our
lineage also, the Pausayu
Since you already mentioned the others, could you
tell us about where the waterfalls are
I have heard that they call it the eye of the water. Yes, because it is a big waterfall
Could you tell us more about that place with the waterfalls?
A girl had an accident there years ago
And Patsualu? It's the same one with the waterfalls too
They have to tell Geovanny to locate them well tomorrow
You can describe the place where all the animals drink water,
which we will visit as well. You can describe it?
What is it and how important is it?
The importance to the community?
It is because of that same water
All animals drink. That is, the one from the well
Although before the water was extracted in an artisanal way
But thanks to the alpina project energy was put
solar to drain water with motor
The water is no longer drawn by hand, since that is how the
people suffered a lot
Because they had to raise the bucket with water through
of a rope using only the strength of the arms
Now it's just starting the engine and the water rises by itself
to give to all the animals
What is your dream with the community?
How would you like to see the community grow?
The first or main thing of all is what
I said a while ago
That in the community the energy returns through
she solar energy
So that the children can study, that they can
do your homework at night
That cell phones can be charged since now
It's their turn to go to Nazareth to load them
So I want there to be energy
For us to be alright again
aha that's all
You can also describe the Sawa'a (roasted corn
ground) that we just saw and ate
What is Sawa'a? and how is the process?
Ah, the Sawa'a
That's what we eat
It's like our sweets
First the corn is toasted, ground and added
panela to be delicious
That is our snack in a share or meeting
What is Sawa'a (sandstone)
A clear example is when a conflict is to be resolved
Or solve a problem between different families
What is distributed during these meetings is the
Sawa'a to share among all
Well, you living here in such a beautiful place,
I don't know if it has a connection with the mountains or with the
nature around you
Yes, of course, with the animals, more than anything, with the goats.
With the sheep, with the chickens
everything around me
As well as the garden that we make
That's all
They want to know something about spirituality
Of the territory
The old say that there is a spirituality of everything
In my community, for example, they say that through
From dreams they see the spirits of the mountains
And the fishermen say that the sea has a
spirituality with some beings
It's because of sleep too. Yes, could you go a little deeper?
for our guests
Why we should not ignore the spiritual connotation
of the holy places
The spirituality of the territory is through dreams,
if he tells us to play the Kasha (drum) we do
If it is to attract the father rain we touch it, if it is
to harmonize one day you also play
So that nothing bad happens to us
So that diseases and pests do not reach the community
If the earth starts to turn red, we already know that
we must play the kasha
And make good food. All that the dream asks for
Can you tell us who is mma'? or What is mma'?
Mma' is the land, territory and our mother at the same time
I wanted to ask you, for all the people who don't
They are Wayúu, which is what you would like us to learn from you.
From their community, from their grandchildren, from the children. What can we learn? Of what you are and of your practices
Respect for our culture
that they recognize our value and that they do not make fun of
we for our clothing
They respect our culture
That you respect us rather
Is it alright like this Neko? Yeah
It's right
If you have a message that you would take to the world
what would?
Yes, that they respect and value our culture
That they recognize us and respect us in any
corner of the world
Because our culture is wonderful in every way
We have diversity in crafts. AND
we respect those who are not wayúu
So that there is mutual respect because, just as we respect them
we hope you respect us outside of here
Don't make fun of us because of our clothes
Because we respect the arijunas a lot
(someone who is not wayúu) when they arrive in the territory
We are kind to them, although I admit that we are not.
we are all like that
But, here in the north mutual respect is maintained
with ourselves and with the arijunas
Well yes
When we went to India they said that the blanket was very
beautiful because we went in a blanket
Ready? we're ready, we're done
And be careful if you are going to download that because there is nowhere
load it. You saw that we returned to the same thing again.
I wanted to ask you something else about spirituality and magic
What is magic for you?
Spirituality manifests itself through sleep
The Lania that is against
That that is revealed through the dream
The counter is a protection that is revealed through the dream
In the dream he tells someone "today this is going to happen to you"
But go there on the mountain where you will find such a plant
You prepare it and bathe
And that person has to fulfill what the dream asks for.
Because if you don't comply, something bad happens to you.
And when he fulfills it, nothing happens to him
Like the piachi (spiritualist) who has her spirituality
and their gifts
Here previously there was an old lady who was the
children's piachi
She was the one who cured the children, but the lady has already passed away.
She also had her gifts her spirits
She asked for either animals, necklaces or whatever she asked for.
And if they did not comply, the baby would not heal and she
she was also affected because she got sick
That's spirituality with dreams
That's how it is in our culture
What else? Other
The importance of water, what is it?
It's life, life
It is essential for everyone, for humans and for animals.
Without water there is no life, hence its importance to us.
But we thank God that as long as we have water
And in Nazareth? In Nazareth yes, because we have a stream about 10 meters away
Is where we're going now
It is different than other parts. Yes, like there where we passed
That's why it's nice to live here, we don't lack anything, thank God
And with the wind. yes you can breathe fresh air here
Here the wind is very strong, you can tell me about the wind.
Yes because we are in summer
There is a drought, from the month of June, July and August
In September it suddenly starts to rain. the rain is coming
The wind has died down a bit
The wind also has a mythology in culture
wayúu or is a spirit or supernatural being
I don't know much about that.
The wind is not necessary. Yes of course
our ancestors say
That in the beginning beings like the sun were created,
the moon and the wind is their brother
There are several types of winds, there is the normal one like that of
now and the whirlpool
I don't know if you have any other information other than this.
No no I dont know
Although they say that this represents hunger
My dad says that when there is a lot of wind it is
why are you hungry
I mean, for them it's because there's a drought
There is summer and the animals no longer have to graze
Because they get scared by this, when there is a lot of wind
And the last thing you could tell us is how
How far are we from Uribia or Manaure?
How long does it take to get here?
It's far, it's 6 or 7 hours in a good car
and more the sun
It is a little removed and the path is a bit difficult
And is there something else you want to share about your connection or your relationship with nature?
With the earth, with the animals, with the wind, the
water or with that place
Well, here I am fine, I feel calm in peace
I breathe that tranquility
I don't feel stressed
Peace is breathed here
Very good anayawasu (thank you)
Well I wanted to know about something so we're not done
I wanted to know about the sun and the moon, I don't know if there are
mythologies about it
Or what role does the sun or the moon have?
the moon yes
The moon when it approaches
The summer, the autumn that is on the moon
My dad always told me, "it's not going to rain, it's already
the moon on that side"
Says it's getting closer and it's really raining
old men are wise
My dad always says like this "look, it's going to rain"
they, they
They watch the time with the moon
When it will rain, when it will not rain and when it will
be bad the rain
They say "no this year it will not rain well, because
the moon is on this side"
It's wrong like that
And I tell my dad how do you know that? he tells me
than looking at the moon
And so
It's going to be bad the rain is going to rain a lot this year
What other things did your dad teach you? oh the song
of a bird that always sings around
So some say, no this year will not see rain
Look what that bird is singing
What they say is true, it doesn't rain not enough
Do the birds know? If the birds know, the old people, the grandparents too
Of the sun if I don't know much Neko.
It is a sun that heats nothing else, it is used for energy
Yes too
And if there is no sun, there is no energy, they do not charge
cool batteries
Here we always have that problem and don't even mention it
rainy times
Because the sun does not rise, all the time is cloudy
What is your clan? And how important are the clans?
The clans are what represent us
Since each family has a clan and an animal
that represents it, that is, they have their dowry
What is the clan mark?
And what is your clan and your brand?
I am Pausayu
And the animal that represents me is the black wasp
with a cool king
And my mark is like a
Maye you can show them our brand
Show them please, that's on the right blanket. Yeah
That's on the blanket, the mark
Yes that. this one here
Del Pausayu. I have it here on the forehead, if that's it.
That is the one that represents us
Everyone has their importance for each family
They recognize him by that, where he is from or where he comes from
I can have two brands on my animals
I can take my dad's and I can put mine on that animal
Here it is
This is my dad's, Uriana is this family's. and this is ours
I mean, we can take this
I can use this to mark a cow or cattle
We can mark this and this
So that they differentiate us like the Urianas
This is from a Pausayu
Because we here are achon, that is, children of Uriana
How many clans do you see there? How many?
Many? Yes, there are several, there is Pushaina, for example
Arpushana, if there are several
How many animals do you have?
Well, they are dying in my absence for a month over there
Because they are careful, if the owner does not come
that also exists
'Cause they steal right here in the family, as you know
that one is not
They sell them
As they know that one is not there, but when one is here
don't mess with them
Because one immediately follows the footprint, we follow it
That's why there's no robbery here, and if we know who it is
poor him because he has to pay double or triple
For one animal they have to pay ten
ten sheep
That takes away the desire to steal
That is why there is peace, because that is the payment for a lack
who wants to steal like that
You have to do it well hidden
And that is why there is peace because there is a payment
for the faults
And that is a wayúu system. Yeah
If there is no payment, there is a conflict, just as I told you that
the woman is the one who intervenes and so on.
Like those countrymen from last night who formed us
a whole mess about it.
One time, just for introduction, you could tell where from
you are now what do you do
I am Magalys Polanco, wayúu Pausayu
And my ancestral territory is Isi'jou
What is in the Macuira, dune
I am mother and grandmother
And in my community I like to help people
As I was saying, I took the solar energy course,
I also like
Because being in the community is not very good
One has to go to bed early if we are in the dark
On the other hand, with energy one goes to bed later
because there is light
We can do chores like knitting or reading
And here in my house I work with the animals
I take care of my goats, sheep, all the animals, the chickens
And that's who I am in my community
And when people come here, I like to help them
and the book? Oh the book.
Well we wrote a book with Juan David with the help of Neko
About energy and what I did in India
Anayawasü (thank you) Jatsü (it's over).