I find it very interesting
That the Wayuu people hardly have
A border.
Yes, that's precisely it.
Yes, precisely, this is the theory
and this is the practice.
So, I have both of them
And sometimes, as always,
it's something that is said with pride.
it's not like my culture is binational,
but that pride is something that truly costs.
I mean, for example, to me
I had my elementary school in Venezuela
when I came to Colombia I studied high school,
but with the Venezuelan documents and also
I have the Colombian,
I have both documents and when I finish
the high school
that paper doesn't do me much good,
because i was hoping that, taking into account
is also an idea from our culture, at least I would say
Let's transfer the paperwork to the Colombian and cancel the Venezuelan.
But bureaucracy does not allow
that and we are that,
we are a victim
of a border that we did not want to enter,
we did not put.
So that's the other side of saying
I am binational,
is negative.
So yes, it could,
no problem, I could answer.
Well, first of all, let's start with which one?
is your name and what you do.
Well, what is your name?
Where are we and what do you do?
Well, my name is Neko Agustin Pio.
We were in Manaos, La Guajira, in the media guajira.
And what do I do?
Well, I'm involved in several things, in fact, things
that are related to cultural conservation,
in this case,
in particular the culture to which I belong
me, which is the Wayuu culture.
Then,
Precisely, I can say that I am dedicating myself
to the creation of audiovisual content, producing short films.
and to literature, writing,
passing
the oral story from our culture to writing.
So it is also a way to
of systematizing knowledge
and wisdom that have been bequeathed to us by these people who
that has been so difficult to continue.
If you are, where are you writing,
putting that information?
Now,
for now I also write literary
works, very personal, like my name.
I have already had the opportunity to,
to publish two books,
one I worked as a collaborator and in another
because I worked in a way that
Single, a single actor, in which
have been my big accomplishments, writing.
And also
I am working with Wikipedia.
I am one of the collaborators who have
We are building Wikipedia on xxx ... it's official.
We already have Wikipedia in xxx
and this is a project
that has given me the space for the things that I write about
can be in a library, in this case
in a virtual library,
And I have been able to write about
five specific articles.
Well, tell me a little bit about your beliefs, that is
Where are you from?
that's what we're talking about, Nacional
from that border.
Well, more than a belief, it is a reality.
The truth is a reality.
Today our culture
is on the Colombian side
and on the Venezuelan side
and that is to say that when it was
the border between Colombia and Venezuela was established,
It was not taken into account that there were
a culture that was divided
and this territorial division
caused a portion to remain in Colombia
and a portion in Venezuela.
But our culture as such
not visible, did not see that border
and that is why many of the Wayuu brothers and sisters still visit their
family members who are in that part and then the
who are there visit them here, and with time
had access difficulties,
but they managed to do, to go there and to come here
and in that process
also
my family was at one time
in Venezuela
in search of opportunities, that one moment
this part of Colombia, La Guajira, its economy and its
Didn't depend on Colombia, but on Venezuela.
It's something, it's quite a situation,
as we would say, quite complicated.
depend on another country
and not depend on the country to which it belongs.
And in that, let's say in those decades,
that La Guajira depended on Venezuela,
and was at its peak,
my parents were
to the neighboring country and there
one thing that is very difficult
and one of the things there is
is that indigenous people who do not speak
Spanish
they find it difficult to understand the political issue
and that's why the politicking, the candidates
political groups collect individuals, groups,
to the indigenous people, to the communities that don't have ID cards, they provide identification through
their contacts information, in this case from the Registrar's Office.
And in this situation
My parents have their Venezuelan ID card and also their Colombian ID card.
I was originally born here in Colombia,
but my childhood was in Venezuela.
So I was able to
once when my parents came to Venezuela,
also obtained their documents
and I was also registered in Venezuela,
so also had this Venezuelan document
and with this document I studied
and finished elementary school.
When my parents went back to Colombia again
To access education was very difficult, you know, starting from scratch.
I was already 13 years old,
by then it was already very complicated for me
start, burn the entire high school and what was done
was, what I was allowed to do in school.
I was told,
you can continue studying with the venezuelan school
as a foreigner here in Colombia,
which in due course I accepted,
having faith that in the future
a paperwork transfer was to be made.
That is to say, my document,
my Venezuelan studies will be transferred to the Colombian one
and I graduated four years ago
and this transfer has not been possible.
Then,
I finished my high school with the Venezuelan
and in Colombia I was recognized as
as a Venezuelan high school graduate,
a foreign bachelor's degree.
And then with the Colombian, this year it is
that I am taking a validation course
to come back again,
studying and finishing high school
and access to higher education
as a Colombian citizen, which
so what I was saying just now,
one says with pride my people, my culture,
my people, my Wayuu nation is binational,
But that pride, in reality, is something very abrupt.
and what I said I have the document, what I have,
and to date
I have not been able to access to study any
career because it is very difficult
to be, to be a...
to have ended up as a Venezuelan, although if there are
opportunities, but they are very scarce,
then not for me,
is not favorable to me
and that's something that happened to me,
but it is also a situation that happens to hundreds
of people here in La Guajira.
Well
tell me a little bit about for you
What does it mean to be a Wayuu?
What does it mean to me to be Wayuu?
I believe that
in that case that our culture has taught us that
our way of seeing life is in a spiral
and in this spiral we, life
existence, takes a journey,
we have a beginning and that beginning, that origin, is what we
is behind us
it is the case that if a
wayuu
suppose he dies in Venezuela, his people,
its root is going to look for it
and will bury him with his ancestors.
So, taking into account that way of thinking,
we also believe that there are things
that are previously destined
and having that way of looking at life,
I think that each of us is placed at a point where we are going
in some way to
make things interesting or make an impact,
where we go out, where xxx,
where God places us
and that's why I'm proud of it, for everything
what we are,
what constitutes us as persevering people,
as individuals, as a struggling community
to maintain its identity
and to maintain,
for maintaining a culture that we have been
building
o that our ancestors built for us
and which are now given to us as a legacy.
That of nomadic
Can we talk about that?
Well, what, if our culture is nomadic,
because we are a semi-nomadic culture,
it is said,
Anthropology says that we have been coming down
of the Perijá highlands,
the column that crosses Colombia
anthropology, according to studies.
say that others of us are coming down from that hill,
of that column of hills
and we got off and got to this one,
This provincial, arid land,
and our culture has taken over that place and
we can also see that feature
of the high guajira, Punta Colombia, the Punta Colombia of the
from the point that it is quite far from here
we have been going down,
that is why our culture, our nation,
has already reached much further south,
and in that, let's say
in that
way of coming down from the top to the bottom
has been given through the practice of
of being semi-nomadic
because our grandparents and ancestors
were behind
from where the rain was prosperous.
And so when there was a drought in a place,
They immediately searched for the place where the rain was
Then and then they passed that point
and when here the rain ended
passed by and went after it.
But the point where they knew they had arrived,
that point already belongs to them,
then it ends up being a waypoint.
And there is a moment
As far as they can go,
as being
migrants.
Somehow, behind the rain,
comes to a point where they decide
return to the point of origin, to the starting point.
So, to get to that point
or those points where they
they are positioning themselves, they are leaving
inheritance, they are leaving
children, they are leaving other people behind, so
those points become points on a route
From a semi-nomadic community, from a community that is
constantly traveling and on the move.
It's a bit of a spiral.
Can you tell me a little bit about
your intention of preserving the culture?
how are you doing that, and what importance
does it have to preserve that culture?"
On a personal level
I love very much
to be wayuu and part of this love
by the identity that one has, it is,
is to recover things that have been lost
and things that are being lost due to different
reasons.
We have one of those punctual reasons
that has caused us to lose,
has been the need
to emigrate in search of opportunities.
We have the specific cases of the Wayuu,
of the communities
who migrated to Venezuela, to the cities of Venezuela
when they were at their peak,
but when they
returned to the Guajira again, to the land,
The generations that were born in Venezuela no longer spoke xxx.
So they would move in search of an opportunity, but that opportunity
ends up harming them.
Like losing the language, speech, and another one as well
is that the territories and
globalization has also touched it
and also
In our territory it is sometimes necessary to go there
to study, or for a god job
and in this way to look for opportunities outside
we make it cause that damage
I told you about earlier, of losing something
from ourselves
So there are many reasons
for that loss. Also,
Also, the Wayuu society itself has lost certain values.
we have let ourselves be carried away by a thought
that is not like us
because our culture is a collective culture
that does everything in collectivism.
Lately
already by
the entries of large multinationals,
has caused the Wayuu to become selfish
and to the point where there is no more unity
and then that
causes conflicts between communities.
The famous conflicts between clans
that among the Wayuu themselves they kill each other, for the sake of a good
or for the benefits that this can generate.
And while that is happening
the way of teaching is also changing.
It is no longer taught that you should love your neighbor
how it used to be taught,
that you must have empathy first and foremost,
This is no longer taught.
So the new generations are being born
without having those values that were and had
our culture,
then the way of thinking is selfishness,
already everyone only assures
what it is
own, what is yours and what you do not share with others.
there is no longer any empathy
And that also generates that among the Wayuu themselves, the same culture
be generated
that we also lose part of our identity,
because already at this moment,
The grandparents who sat in front of a bonfire to teach us, to tell us stories
That used to generate reflection is no longer being done
and then there is no way to recover those values
Or a way of saying, 'Look, we are Wayuu, there is
no need to kill each other
We want to do the work that the old man did,
our ancestors,
our grandfather, in front of a campfire,
teaching the little boys, the young men
So that they always maintain that unity,
that love, that empathy.
We want to do that
through audiovisual creation,
through the short film, our short film,
that space to generate a reflection
both the Wayuu person
as the outsider, the foreigner.
And I have had the opportunity to
to learn a little and I have come
doing interesting things.
And it is the same thing that happens
with writing,
with what I have been writing, it is
a way to grasp this oral knowledge
and systematize it
Take it to a book,
because one of the advantages of an oral tradition
is that over time it gets lost or changed or then
is no longer there.
And so let's say that in those two points
I have concentrated more on contributing
to this Colombian identity.
You can quickly describe where we are now,
as in the urban house.
and the one in front of the ranchería.
So where we are, it's going to be a little bit different.
and reflect the difference between the two.
Well, in Manaure one calls it an urban zone,
practically all over La Guajira
One calls it an urban area,
but it is really not so much urban as semi-urban.
In this case, this house of ours
is in a village,
in the village
as we use the term to refer to it, but
we have maintained
our ways of making traditional houses
and for this space that is here
although it is in the urban zone, we call it an urban zone,
but really the house, the roof, everything
it's like something traditional still
and therefore the differences,
The difference is that in rural areas, there is no electricity, no power, no internet.
and that would be the only difference.
Well, that way there is also much less noise.
Yes, there are also advantages
nature is more
present in
rural areas than in urban areas.
Can you describe who xxx is and
What does it mean to you, to the Wayuu people?
xxx the word for xxx in spanish is madre tierra
or xxx can also mean only
a grain of sand,
but it can also mean
or it can also be assimilated
to say planet,
because the name of this planet, planet Earth,
is related to this concept.
So when we say xxx
We are not only referring to Mother Earth,
but also to the planet itself.
Then that
is the meaning of the word xxx
and for us that is xxx, well xxx
is the mother of us.
It has already been explained to them
that we, for us
our origin is in different generations.
First, they create
or first, life arises
from light
that is born of the night, the darkness.
From that it is born.
Then comes a generation, which is the generation
of the elements
and then the sacred places, then xxx
meet xxx
Being rain, among them
there is a love affair and the fruit of that love affair are the plants,
large plants
and birds.
But mother, xxx,
felt sad because the plants were
immobile.
I wanted children who were independent,
they thought,
And then
had children.
And that's where we went out. The
human beings, the Wayuu.
And so for our worldview, Mma is
our mother,
the one that connects us, the one that has given us
practically everything, because if
we ask ourselves where the things I have come from
or the things I consume
come from mother earth.