We meet at the alatsu stone
with an ancient stone that dates back many years,
that from our own worldview we can look from what,
from the mythological.
00:17: - 00:21
They say that once Maleiwa, the god of the Wayúu,
came down in this place
because he was worried about the situation in what
the Wayúu were found
because they had no way to identify themselves within Wayuu society.
So he decided to organize a contest with the birds.
That was where the curlew was, that was where the Zamuro was, there was the
bird they call Pico Gordo, the Utta (dotted bobito)
So he decided to organize that contest
to choose
something that would identify the Wayúu people.
Then Cataneja began to sing and began to sing.
Toulijana, toulijana, toulijana (anklet)
Maleiwa did not like the Cataneja song
Toulijana means that which hangs on the ankles.
And then they called Walusechi
and began to sing son'tusu to'i, son'tusu toi, son'tusu
my feet are cramping, is the translation
and Maleiwa did not like the song of the two birds.
And then Utta, who is the bird, entered
fat beak and began to sing
Pushaina with Arpushana, Ipuana with Epieyu.
Sapuana with Ipuana, he began to sing mentioning
those striking words.
Then Maleiwa (God) said, I do like that, I do like this.
Let's choose
that phrase, those words that
that you sang in the song, Pushaina with Arpushana
Ipuana with Epieyu, Sapuana with Ulewana. He highlighted all of those
So from there
Maleiwa began to distribute to each Wayúu family,
which are the respective clans, with their respective brand
and in what is now embodied in stone,
that from the mythological part.
Now, if we go back in history
we can realize that the word Jeerü
In wayunaiki (wayuu language) it comes from herraje
Jeerü comes from horseshoe.
We know very well that livestock farming is not typical of the Wayúu,
but they were brought by the colony.
So what is the cow, what is the goat
They are not our own, but we as a Wayuu people
We adopt it and give it a name,
we use the label
like Jeerü , which is horseshoe
also the words, if we can analyze ourselves
the ear cutting of animals.
It comes from asu'araluja which is the word in wayunaiki
or point in Spanish
There is no original word of its own that comes from
Wayúu people, but it was a product
of Spanish domination when they brought us livestock
and we realize.
But the Wayúu, since he is so creative,
It is a town that adapts, that adjusts
to all the circumstances,
He captured it in his myth and we adopted it as our origin,
about the symbology of the Wayuu people,
That's what the oral tradition tells,
Yes, of course, that is the rock that tells the origins
of the Wayuu people.
Well, this is the stone of Alatsu,
which tells about the origins of the clans,
What clans are, it's like a
classification within Wayuu society
There are around 22 clans currently, but
Previously there were other clans.
We can give an approximate of 32 clans that existed
previously,
but that, due to various circumstances, due to problems
of inter claníles
many of those clans disappeared and became extinct
for some, some war
and due to various circumstances
Those clans disappeared.
But currently there are 22 clans in force.
which are what is currently and are present
throughout the department of La Guajira.
Well teacher, I come from Alkualü, Manaure
To learn more about the culture, and where
It comes from the story that our
ancestors about our symbols
So, for you to tell me again, but in wayunaiki
About God, yes, that started from
maleiwa concern
He felt sad, because people were
disorganized, they looked like animals
There was no organization or structure that
classify families
So that's where the birds called,
like the buzzard, like utta
and others, like them or the birds, were before people, yes, true.
So he decided to have a singing contest.
to choose the best
Since the names they choose will remain as a legacy
to future generations
They will be your family lineages
Then the other sang and he didn't like it,
the other one too and he didn't like it either
The only song he liked was Utta's
He liked the words Pushaina, Ipuana, Epieyu
God liked all the ones he mentioned
for the song
Its reward was a necklace, which is why the bird has
a line down his neck, yes.
Yes, that was his reward, it was like his payment
How interesting to know that the bloodlines came out
of a bird's song
If it was Utta, and how did he sing?
That same one, wayuu said Epieyu, Pushaina, Epinayu Ipuana Uriana
So from there the eirüku (family lineage) arose.
I am Epieyu. What is your professional lineage? Uriana, wayuu
Uriana, from the cat or tiger
If each one was given an animal to represent them
as the stone shows
If each group was told, this is going to be your lineage,
you will be Pushaina, you will be Ipuana, Sapuana
And which is the Uriana here? It's over here, where?
Uriana, Uriana
Here is the Epieyu, Pushaina, Epieyu
Is this Epieyu? Yes, well this is my lineage, yes.
My mother is Epieyu
Because, ah look this is my eirüku (lineage) Urina,
yes , the one with a head
Where I come from, in Akualü, Manaure the Uriana
They are my grandfathers and grandmothers so you are my grandfather
And look here they are together
It is one of the oldest lineages in the
which ones come off others
There are many, there is the Jusayu, there is the Sapuana
The Pausayu that is from Magalys
How interesting
So it was formed then, I saw it only in leaves
In pictures
That's how I saw it, but I'm here to know
because there are many people who brag about
being Wayuu and they don't know anything about the culture
Instead
I can say from now on that I know the origin of
our ancestors and this stone
Now I know that it was Utta who stipulated this, who created it
Because I only knew that he was a talker but not wise
that I name the lineages
Well teacher, thanks for continuing
preserving our legacy as Wayuu through
of your teachings
We of the new generation
The children who are in the town
It is difficult for them
Know about this
That is why there are few people who have the knowledge
And with this what was said is recorded
Because if they forget their origin,
they would be on earth without any direction
They wouldn't know where they come from, it's what they call loss of origin
On the other hand, with this and the Wolunka stone, it is something that
gives them identity as they say
It is what identifies them and what authenticates the culture
Thank you very much teacher.
That's all
not what he told us is the mythological origin
and a reflection about how this gives us identity
even though it has
Its origin also has a non-Wayuu antecedent.
Why not wayuu?
Because the origin of the clans was given to animals,
That's a practice of, oh well, I get it.
From there one got the idea, or we adopted it because
Those symbols are Wayuu
Hey, can you give me a photo session? Because
I feel like I'm not going to be late again,
because here they do allow us to record
Even with the drone, you can because this is not in the park.
Do you want me to tell you the explanation?
Well, your symbol is there, my symbol is here
this
Wait I just lost it
It's here, here
Where is my symbol.
Epiayu
Uriana
You can do that with the other hand please.
Aapushana
Pushaina
And Magalys
Pausayu, Magalys's is over here.
Girnu
Jusayu
And what is that of your ancestors?
I have two ancestors
Which is it? wait, I think it's this
And this, these two
Yes this one and this one, Epieyu
AND
This.
Uriana
Well, they have mythological origins, part of orality
What makes
Measuring time is difficult.
But this rock.
My grandfather told me about
if my grandfather counted
that he listened
that Wuimpumiun, the upper Guajira
he never saw him,
but his grandfather told him
So for me to get here, it's practically too,
touches on many topics
of life, of my personal life,
because many of my family, the Wayuu there are
that have been or have been going down, have been displacing
They talk about this rock,
They talk about this rock as that place
where some moment from which this culture starts.
Remember that I told you that in our culture
We came down from the mountains of the serranía
that crosses Colombia
Starting from the peninsula we settle
and from there we went down to La Guajira Baja now
During hours
But those from there are still in the collective memory of these places
Now there is the Aalatsü stone that I have seen
hundreds of times in books
I had longed to arrive, I had longed
touch that energy that exists, if one touches it
There is tremendous energy.
What do you suppose that day or that time was like to mark this here?
everyone gathered here deciding the clans
how do you imagine it?
Well, the teacher said that Maleiwa
the supreme being of the Wayuu.
He needed his children to divide into groups
because we were like this
So it was very difficult, in the organization, to have
a standard at least
and that is why it was necessary for them to become clans
so that the Wayuu group has
small groups, that is, of the large group there are subgroups
It is a fabric, the social fabric of culture.
Our culture is in a group, but within the
group there are micro groups
18:34 18:36
and for the election
Maleiwa listened because at that
in that mythological time of our creation
The animals were people,
the bird was a person and they heard the different birds and it was
There was a bird that said wuinpumiu, wuinpumui, what the teacher said
North, north
Maleiwa heard that, but it didn't catch his attention.
Then there was another one that said ojutusu, ojutusu, fall, falling
When the birds sing, each one emits a message, no,
But among those birds is the wise bird, which is the utta which is
Let's say the bird that represents the palabrero.
This bird in its song said Epieyu, said Pushaina, Uriana,
Jusayu, Pausayu
Maleiwa heard that, he repeated that.
And Maleiwa said, he is saying some words that could well
Be what each divided group represents.
And from Utta's song, the
the names of the different clans.
Thus we have Uriana, which is a clan that has a totem and has
an animal that represents it and in this case
It also has a symbol that must be on this rock
How good it is on this rock, we find it here in that little part.
but also the Epieyu which is my clan that is right here
Here
And then seeing that we realize that here
impregnated the oral ideas
to materialize the idea in a way.
You know that all ideas are first a thought,
but then they materialize
And maybe, like here where possibly
time has already taken several from us because in itself,
It is said that there are 32 clans,
but currently only about 22 are recorded
And then what happened to other clans? Maybe
communities or those clan groups have been
involved in other clans.
This happens for different reasons, there are many reasons,
are in conflicts between the same communities
When one family is in conflict with another,
always seeks to completely disappear the lineage
And how do they disappear? Cutting the matrilineal line
Other.
Another reason you could also make a clan disappear
It could be the need to migrate to the cities.
Many communities migrated to the cities and being in
the cities, lost part of that knowledge of knowledge
and maybe they also lost their clan there
because they didn't talk about it anymore, so if they didn't
They talk about their clan, the other clans are not going to do it.
and that is why it is said that many clans
Many clans have been lost, yes.