What happens is that in La Guajira
plastic pollution is an issue
quite complex,
quite, quite serious.
Because one of the causes, to put it in a way,
for many decades
we have been buying
our food, an example would be rice,
That comes in a plastic wrapper,
The coffee comes in a plastic wrapper.
The spaghetti has plastic wrap.
Then buying that
here in the communities,
In rural areas, there is no sanitation system.
So the garbage truck doesn't pass here,
here the plastics that enter have no way out
so they stay in the communities
and that is why we say that this problem is cumulative.
We have been buying this plastic for many years.
and those plastics have remained in the communities
and that's why we have pollution
for waste
quite visible in the communities.
So,
This becomes a conflict
a problematic.
So serious that when we walked the trails
From the rancherías we are going to see plastics,
One goes for the cardones and
The cardons have plastic stuck.
One walks through the sea,
There is plastic on the beaches too, so now Manaure
is flooded.
To the extent that in 2019 Semana magazine,
a very popular magazine in Colombia published
an article titled La Güajira flooded with garbage.
And it is a phrase
that is not far from reality.
La Güajira really is flooded with plastics,
is flooded with waste and to
counteract this problem
We created this initiative ''Threads for Mma'' and
what we do is
bring workshops to communities,
to different communities, on awareness
facing the issue, the environmental issue
and how plastic,
How damaging is going to be when we leave it in nature.
These workshops are also
contextualized in our culture.
It's not just coming and saying
You have to classify them, classify solid waste
and so, but also to know
like our culture
has a thought regarding this topic.
And that's why, from that, ''Threads for Mmá '' was born,
where we bring workshops to the communities and also
we generate an exchange
where communities give us classified waste
and in return we give them threads,
we give them the wool to make
the backpacks, the
handles, the hammock.
This is how we give value to waste and communities
They say well, it's worth it
really, because there is a, there is an added value.
So they give us that waste,
We collect that waste,
There is a collection center here in the mountains, in the desert,
There is a collection there
and we take that waste
to the point of the urban area where it is
the garbage truck and all that.
And to also give continuity to these elements,
Like cardboard, we take it to recycling stores.
On the other hand,
the communities once they have the threads that we
We give to them, they make a product with that thread.
This is how we are focusing
in backpacks and accessories.
They make backpacks, for example, and
seeing that it is necessary to generate
a store where the results
of this exchange and this
barter we’re doing can be exposed: as well as
ensuring that this craftsman who made the product
receives a fair payment.
Because here in La Güajira
That is also another problem that artisans do not get paid well,
So the middleman always wins.
That's why we have a store where it is sold exclusively
everything that is the result of that exchange
and so
from the sale of a product
like the case of a backpack,
a backpack gives us money to buy new
threads, new bags to work with communities
and so from a product it is what gives us,
It gives us money to fuel the entire process.
So the buyers, the people who
who find that product
we give you the opportunity wherever you are in the cities
that they can contribute something
in the end to the health of the planet.
If a person buys a product from us, from that
They are contributing to the environment.
In this case
to this part of Colombia,
trying to reduce pollution
and at the same time also generate that awareness about
of the crafts of indigenous groups, which do not
It's just an element
but behind a craft
There really is a story.
There was what I told you just now about Wale’kerü
and about how important this is
and about how in a craft there is a configuration,
there is ancestral knowledge,
then also generating that awareness for the buyer,
to the person to tell them not to buy just because it’s trendy,
do not buy to consume,
what is
the last thing we do now we just for consumption,
No, buy out of conscience that where I buy
from this that I am generating,
What impact am I generating?
So this product is very nice,
is being done in rural areas Manaure and
La Guajira and here where we are
where
as I was saying here now
it's an idea,
they don't even come in here
political entities or entities
who have responsibilities to look
How the communities are
So we are making a very cool impact.
and we hope that this work, which
This idea can be replicated in other contexts,
not only in our Wayuu culture,
but also in other brothers and indigenous people,
can somehow replicate this idea.
And we hope to continue growing.
We hope to help more Wayuu families,
We hope to help more communities through this.
and in the medium term,
or well, the end,
The goal of all this is also to one day say
see, look,
we contributed a bit
to the reduction of pollution in La Güajira.
That is our dream through that project.
And so well,
thanks
for making us a little bit visible
and well, to continue fighting in these processes,
in this case in La Güajira.
And what is the name of the project store?
we have the store
“Ishotot nos une” (ishototnosune username) that Ishotot has the word Isho,
which is blood,
then color of blood or blood unites us really
that is
Such that
a store created in the community,
We don't have an establishment yet.
physical, everything is virtual,
You can find us on different social networks
and we are there as Ishotot nos une and as Hilos por Mma.
These two sources can reach us.
Cool and how to summarize
the project in like a sentence of
as quickly as a summary of everything,
of the project idea.
Of course, yes.
From the purchase of a product
we generate impact,
a social impact and an impact…
two specific impacts,
an environmental impact and a social impact.
That's why, let's buy
or that the products
that we buy is a product that has a purpose
quite,
pretty good, both for
the artisan as well as for the planet.
Yeah.
Yes, do you collect, collect the plastic,
sell it and buy the thread?
Well let's say that the plastic here,
here in the communities the use of plastic,
here the communities they have them, they reuse them, so like this
for example, the pot, the one with the soda,
here it
reused to store oil, to store other liquids
and when this plastic material no longer has
one last use is that
they are free. No?
That's why when we collect all that material,
Most of them are already very very damaged materials,
Well, what we have to do is take it directly
to the sanitation point.
Other materials such as cardboard,
That one we do take it to the recycling stores,
They give it continuity and
we receive a coin in exchange for carrying that
There, but it is not our forte, really our forte
Is the product.
From the purchase of the product
is that it gives us money to buy more threads,
to buy more bags,
because we deliver
bags to the communities so that they can
collect waste. Our strong
It is in the product of craftsmanship.
Yes they pay us for the cardboard, for the plastics, but
It's not sufficient payment.
But we are very happy that with the store
It gives that continuity, they give it a use.
Yes.
Well, is there anything else you want to tell about knitting or
from this site
or what we have seen today.
Something else I could tell
would it be necessary
change the perspective of
how to see communities and how
futures should be made
projects with communities.
There are many projects
of the government, let's put it this way,
But mostly those projects fail.
because it is not being done or is not working
the communities. In this case we with ''Hilos por Mma''
We saw the need to create that store,
because at the beginning
the products,
The crafts that came out were sold to the local market
and there he did not receive a fair payment.
So it is always thinking about the entire process, about each thing,
If I give this, where will it end?