I am from the Ayalajose community
It is in the territory of Alta Guajira (North Region)
Right now I am close to the community
in the jaguey (lake) ichiiket
My name is Agustin Pushaina
Now I am going to tell you everything related
with water and rain (mythological father of the Wayuu)
As for Juya (rain) it is very important to us,
He is the one who gives us good things
The one that gives us a hope of life, things
what we need for day to day
And the things our children need to survive
Furthermore, in order for the land to produce
food for us
how do they know when winter is coming?
the month in which the rain comes iwaa appears
(star) As a sign in the sky
In addition, another sign are the dragonflies that appear
before the torrential waters
If the rain comes in that month of signs,
means that enough water is going to fall
We look at the sky when the rain starts to fall
The earth is happy and so are we
Why are we happy?
because there will be abundant food for us
And grass for the animals
They are things that we will survive
It is a lie to say that the Wayuu live well
Because we don't have how to get up in difficult times
Only when the rain comes because with it, we have water,
food, vegetation for animals and so on.
Our house comes from him
Thanks to Juya the teasels bear good fruit in quantity
The plants appear in quantity
With Juya all things are productive like sowing,
Like the animals that feed us
We put a big corral for them
That is why we feed ourselves thanks to water
That's why we need the rain to come in the
month of the star because it is very necessary to live.
If the rain does not come in the month of iiwa (star),
We face many difficulties
The land dries up, there is no water, and nothing to eat
in our land
In those moments we do not know how to handle the situation
We try to bring the apain (orchard) closer to sow food,
But the scorching sun destroys the crops
That is why we need the rain, which
we are talking now
Now let's talk about what was life like for people when the rain was abundant?
before when the rain was abundant everything was fine
when my ancestors inhabited the earth
Juya's rain was abundant
Even in moments of celebrations (myrrh) there was rain,
Happened at the end of the year
After the end of the year it rained again
During the celebration people had many
animals thanks to Juya
The Wayuu began to mark the animals with the
eirüku (family clan) to differentiate them and
know how many animals the rain left
This mark served to leave the inheritance to his children and relatives,
Through the eirüku each person knew what was theirs.
the inheritance was delivered when the rain stopped for a moment
After that the month of iiwa was approaching
and Juya visited us again
Small animals grow quickly
Because the rain makes the plants grow again
In addition, the water is good for everything, to bathe
To plant food such as corn, beans,
the watermelon and the pumpkin.
In the garden they could sow what they wanted to eat
The wayuu who did not have animals or crops,
He approached where a person who did have
He suddenly asked for help because he had no food at home
The sower told him "it's okay, I'll help you", he showed him the
trade on how to sow, clean and harvest.
Or he gives him a part of the garden so that he can sow
his own food
We help each other for good
So the earth is good, with only rain three times
There is already plenty of food, and we all have many animals
The life of our ancestors had many benefits
Because Juya's rain was abundant
They had cows, goats, sheep and other animals
like donkeys and horses
Those were the benefits my ancestors had
When the rain made love to mother earth.
At that time all the territories were in
equal conditions
There was no land where it did not rain
When there was a conflict, they met.
among all and thought of a solution
They managed the situation and reassured those affected.
It was resolved by means of a payment
Since they all had animals it was very easy to give
solution to the conflict as soon as possible
the wayuu did not care how many animals he had to give
because there was enough
Animals were an asset in those days,
That they ended some conflict.
Thanks to animals in abundance there was no theft
There was respect and a healthy coexistence among the Wayuu
They all lived together on earth without any problem,
Neighboring territories were like families
This was possible thanks to the fact that they all had animals in abundance,
And they helped each other
The one who did not have crops asked and the others gave him gifts,
Because no one denied anything
The one who did not have crops exchanged something for food and
so they helped each other.
Now let's talk about the needs due to the lack of water
Right now there is no longer a healthy coexistence
Good friendships among people no longer exist, and the exchange of goods is something that is no longer seen
Water is very necessary, it is what guides us on the right path
It would be a lie if we say that we are
Good-hearted people
If there is no rain there is nothing good
The wayuu wait for the rain,
To the point of sadness
They are forced to go to distant places near the
mountains to fetch water
They take the animals there, and if they have several on the way,
they get lost because they are territories they are unfamiliar with
And the people over there eat the animals
lost on the way
It is a very great suffering when there is no rain
Because of that they are envious between relatives
If a Wayuu grazes a few goats, the rest get upset.
That happens due to the lack of water, because the water
brought good life to all
for animals, people, children,
Because they all drink water
Because it is from water that food is sown,
If there is no water, what will there be?
For example, this little bit of water that is here in the jaguey
When it runs out or dries up you won't see anything
Even if I try to dig a hole under the jagüey with suffering,
So be it for a little water it would be in vain
Meanwhile, he is thinking of a mill or a water well
that is miles from here
Even if the Wayuu travels several kilometers to
get to the place even for a jug of water
Why is it necessary for you to help people with water?
It is necessary to ask for help from the earth and from you, the Arijunas.
because you work with water that comes from afar
They work so that water reaches the villages
We are waiting for you to help us too
To ask that they bring us water here in the house from there
Because if there is water, our traditions of
a healthy coexistence
Return of abundance in food,
planting and sharing with others
People relate to each other
in the communities
Why are we so envious?, for the
lack of water, it is something very necessary for us
For example, if water aid arrives in a neighboring community
give away a mill or a mini aqueduct
Here they must also give the same, as well as in the others,
because that way we would all have water without any problem
With that help we can rebuild many things
what our ancestors did with plenty of rain.
And another life expectancy?
So why do we run to what is called town?
Because we want the town hall to help us
They would help us with good things
like water, because water provides us with everything
He is the one who gives food, animals
The one who gives good friends too
Everything we need we build with water
Because we know how to use it since ancient times
Because we grew up in nature,
and we know many things
That's why kids didn't get sick before
That's why there was no mistreatment between us
When there was water we helped each other
We built a very large apain (orchard)
where we grow food
We planted food in quantity such as beans
Corn, sideburns, pumpkin among others.
Our relatives, nephews and close people arrived
To help each other in the construction
that's where there was opportunity for life, where each one
I harvested a sack of beans
He took it to exchange for other goods.
So they gave him something for the exchange
Our little children
They had the milk of our animals
Like the goat, the sheep or the cow, if we have animals
They extract it to make cheese by pressing it
It was also used to drink it and for children to drink it
It was very good because it did not bring disease, all
We drank it until we were satisfied
So they all worked in the garden
Each one contributed to the construction and planting
If something happens, we all contribute
We always have something to pay
Future conflicts may come, which may commit
our nephews, grandchildren or a member of the family
Or the person who asks us for help, who lives with us
here in the community
in this way of living.
Can you clarify that again?
He said that if they give us water he will not see disease
On earth everything would be alright
If the arijunas of the city help us
We'd love to hear about starving children.
Children who say they die from malnutrition
It is because of the bad life that there is and the lack of food
His mother does not have enough food to
produce milk for a baby
In addition to the lack of resources in the children's house
There are days when children go hungry and eat at the time they
find food
because food is scarce
That's why children get sick
For example, if they deliver the water that comes from the town
You won't see children dying
The earth will be composed as in ancient times
That's why we need the water
Above all things.
Done. Why do we have good material?
For example, this water that you are seeing
It is what we drink now
Why do we drink it?, because we don't have any
Drinking water near here
That's why we use this water, we come looking for it
And we take it to our homes
The town is too far from here to be able to go get water
In addition, a transport is needed to bring it from there and
we don't have that
When this water runs out we will suffer a lot
This is the water we're drinking while it lasts,
That's why we need you to help us
If the world sees us, they would help with the water we need
Then we would no longer have to drink from this jaguey
Our life would change.