We need you to tell us about jawapi (traditional medicine)
What pregnant women and sick people take
I'm going to talk about our life
My name is Luis angel from eirüku (family lineage) “uriana”
I am from here
Our life in the past from which we grew
was immersed in medicinal plants
thanks to our grandparents and uncles
Everything you see here on earth is very important.
For the Wayuu culture
All the plants that you see here serve as food
And medicine for us
We eat the fruits of teasel and trupillo (a kind of mesquite)
Being pütchipü (community mediator)
has allowed me to understand, comprehend
and resolve conflicts between different families
Through dialogue and listening to the problem
All the plants you just saw, we use it
To ease the pain of our body
To ease the pain of our body after
to graze or work
Plants protect us from the sun, that's why we consume it.
And what is the role you have in conflicts as a mediator?
I am the one who should speak to give you a solution
to the problem or conflict
So that there can be respect
And a healthy coexistence between us
Now let's talk about a topic I've been talking about
in other communities
It is about the wind turbines where there is an active conflict
Does the mediator have an important role in this conflict?
The role of the mediator is neutral
What else did they give you when you started to be a mediator?
I took the medicinal plants that my grandmother gave me
So that my word would carry weight and respect when
resolving a problem
My body is very strong no matter if
I’m under great pressure from a group of people
It prepares me to have a good oratory when speaking
Now something you want to tell us
Or some message for the people of the world
Good for you gringos who come from afar
I like to show you part of my customs and beliefs
I feel happy to see you come from afar
Despite not knowing where you come from
My life consists of dialoguing and speaking for others
In times of conflict
Watch over my relatives as a mediator
I am here to help my friends, nephews and grandchildren
If they get to fight
To give them a solution to your problem
I am always ready to speak for them
What I don't know about you gringos,
is to speak your language and your life
In the future I will come to help you
that seems good to me
Because I have my grandchildren who are suffering
Because we don't have a job to survive
please tell us your name again
I am going to tell you my name so that you know me
They call me Luis angel uriana
My eirüku (family lineage) is represented by the rabbit (uriana)
Thank you thank you very much