Regarding what we were talking about in the kitchen now
What is what women do to their faces ?
The Acheepa? (wayuu makeup)
Yes, they say there is one for the sun
That for skin rejuvenation
that one I did
Wayuu makeup is for the yonna (dance)
the one i did
Now
Before, according to the tales, did the makeup began
for a dream?
Yes of course, dreams were the origin of that
The piachi (spiritualist) said what to do based on the dream
Whether it's for Yonna or for family flags, that's part
of the stories too
Now, if we are treating someone,
we lock them up and perform a ritual
It has a price, something good as a
reward for the work done
Well that's mostly for the people who want it
Well, as I was saying, the dream asks for it
sometimes to heal a child of some disease
If it is to heal a child, draw a
semi spiral in his hands
Although to make it effective a ritual
must be done to heal completely
And does makeup serve as a sunscreen?
Yes, when looking for water it is applied in
the whole face, also for walking
that's the makeup
of women to go out
How is the makeup done?
The suet of a small sheep is cooked or fried
and white, they stir it until it is thick,
Then they apply it together with the pali´isa (a type of red chalk) on the face leaving only their eyes uncovered
Can you tell us a little more about the pali´isa?
Wayuu makeup is for the yonna, instead the other
What I was telling you, it's more spiritual
which is usually requested through a dream.
The acheepa has been something very ancestral by our grandparents,
But, it has endured thanks to the new generation
That's what our old folks say
Today there are many forms of makeup
as well as different figures
figures such as family symbols, the spiral among others.
Can you tell us a little more about that?
Those figures in the days before were just
on the cheek separately
Little by little they were shaped in the face.
There are many figures not seen now
Those that were not transmitted by stories
that about the symbols, what does that mean in life?
The last question I asked you about the symbols,
You can graph what you want to put
That is
Makeup has an origin in dreams earlier.
They were made because sometimes they said that they should put that on the girl,
So that she does not get sick or so that the virus that is going to come does not touch her
Because the material it has, red represents blood
This was for the spirits so they don’t,
They move away, no? in ancient times I mean, now they are used in celebrations
And for the celebration and things like that
and what is the color made of?
you already asked
That is a plant that is macerated
And that plant has that tone
and where do you get it from?
What they are asking is where does the pali´isa (red chalk) come from ?
Where do they get it from to obtain that red
To obtain it, you search among the mountains
There isn't here because it has a specific area
Around the mountains
To prepare it and make it the shape of a bun
The one that does it,
Has to knead it and shape it to make it look like that
This plant has its leaves too
The leaves are used for thirst, it is cooked and drunk.
And that pali´isa (red chalk) Is it given to the ladies?
Of course, it is given to the ladies to drink
So that they are beautiful with a firm body
After childbirth they are also given and can have
Up to five children, they also drink it then
The red chalk helps not only the ladies but all of them,
Plans the pregnancy too
with what?, with the leaves of pali´isa
you recorded that last one
it's good? Very good contribution
She spoke about the makeup that is used, it is not only for
Makeup for various things.
And why do only women wear that?
why not men
He says why the makeup?
Or the figures, can't men wear them ?
It is applied to the one who is going to dance
Everyone has their acheepa (makeup) in the yonna
And when they are on the piyoi (dance floor)
The man shouts jou'se (come!)
That's how it's done the dance
Can you repeat what you said about makeup?
of the man
the what?, the acheepa
The man is painted when it’s time to dance,
Figures are also put on him as well
She explained it, she clarified that it is not limited
even women only
And where do they learn all this from?
the question is who teaches this in the community?
How do they learn?
the fact that? to learn that
This? Yes, you know that not everyone knows about the acheepa
I know it because I have the knowledge of the piachi (spiritualist)
I don't know it just for the sake of knowing
I can make a person let go of hatred or resentment
Because I am a piachi (spiritualist)
It seemed that you were giving the blessing
To women when she did that
if I asked her
She just made it clear that not everyone
You can do that, which are gifts
She has the gift of being able to see, what was I telling you right now,
The eye, right? Yeah.
She can read people, so that's a gift too.
for makeup
The make-up thing is original
Because now everyone paints
But mostly they are similar, so which one
is the question you are going to ask
I could say your name and what do you do?
I'm going to ask the question that you said first
If you bless women as you say
He asks about the figures
that did you draw on the girls
You were talking and he asks what was
you told them while you painted them
That is, what did you tell them when painting them?
What I said to them at the time of painting them
it was that he was putting the pali´isa to them to dance
I told them that I was putting makeup on them so that
they show the ancestral steps of our yonna
I also told them that I was putting them makeup on them so
They have fun, to play
That's how it is
Ok, you have answers
And what's her name? where is she from?
He says say your name where are you from? you stand out
that you are wayúu because they know several ethnic groups
Of course I'm wayuu, I'm not an imitation or something like that
And my name is Catalina Epieyu
A pleasure, thank you very much
Did you get it? Yes Yes.
What else? she just said her name and her clan
He just told you about the job right now
with the eye right now
Although that's a lengthy explanation as well,
But I think that she can explain a little
more of that gift I don't know what you think
Yes, that and also its connection with nature
Ok, there were two questions, right?
A while ago you mentioned that you were a piache (spiritualists)
In our territory, not everyone can be a piache, right? Yeah
How is a piachi formed according to ancient tales?
In order to receive the gift?
Yes of course.
that is because of a dream, the dream tells you that you are going to have that gift
start to see beyond
If you see a sick girl, your good eye tells you what to do
He says " look for a jawapia (medicinal plant) for that girl
so that “the evil eye” she has goes away”
The same if it is for a confinement or for something else,
this is more or less how the gift works
The thing about the arijunas is something else
I have heard a tale that says there is a dream for
the spirits to arrive
Someone from Manaure told me that in her dream
a person came to her when they are ladies
What did that dream allow you to have that gift?
It allows me to see spirits
As the spirit gets closer
I see it well, but when it is very close I stop seeing it
The spirits of a spiritualist are in the afterlife
that's why they see everything
Spirits do not wander on Earth like those
of the dead, as that is something very different
Yes it is correct, another question to finish
He has just explained to you how the gift is obtained,
Which is through dreams
When they are young ladies they have a dream where they see a giant character facing them
But that character does not speak to them, but when
is very close to them they disappear
So that's the spirit with which they walk now
Ok, to end the interview
What he wants to know is regarding the
connection with nature
Everything we know has a spiritual connotation
For example, if a person moves, they must sacrifice
an animal to shed its blood
It has a spiritual connotation, but at the same time
has a dark spiritual connotation
When a person arrives in a new territory, they must
have food coffee drinks etc.
If you don't do it, a child will die, because with the ritual it is
As if you buy your stay in the territory somehow
What else does the spiritual imply?
Everything has a spiritual connotation, as well as that of
defy god
If the ritual is not done, the price may be the
son they love the most
And the animals?
It affects their animals because by not doing the ritual they
they fade away little by little
They can even have cows, even so, they will run out of animals for not asking the permission of the land through the ritual
4:33 p.m. 4:34 p.m.
And with the water?
It is also the same if the child of that person reaches out
for water in the well, the child can fall into it
The spirit makes them fall into the well when it makes them lean over to fall to the bottom and drowns them
You just talked about nature itself being a living being
A clear example is when a person goes to
move to another place
When you are going to move, you must
shed the goat's blood
It's like an acceptance of nature in that locality
If you arrive without killing the goat, you will not be well accepted.
That's why it was very important that we cook
goat today as an acceptance
Because that way, things go well for us, and because the spirits, according to the evangelical belief, are pleased
Then she mentioned constantly that all nature
both the water, the vegetation even the goats
there is a being that takes care of them there
If we mistreat these animals, they are going to leave us, they are not going to produce, that is why it is necessary to caress them, we have to talk to them
That's why she says we respect that connection, if
I have that connection I understand nature
I don't know what we are going to ask her now
Ask her how she relates to the wind
As there is a lot of wind now, I don't know if it's something
that should you ask
It got lost. it got lost? No, I want to explore the land
to understand the culture
See how things are with the arrival of your visitors
You see how things are, he did not leave just because, some spirit from those around us unconsciously called him to take him away
If there were no evil spirit among us,
he wouldn't have left like that on his own
He would have asked or asked for the company of some of the
boys to take him where he was going
You see how each thing has its connotation, that's why
must make a good harmonization with food today
So that it does not affect the life of a child here
There are a lot of evil spirits right now and it knows what's going on
To definitely wrap up,
We already spoke about the water and its spirits,
as well as our Juya (rain) our father
We also talk about dreams and their meaning
However, there is something that is rarely talked about and it is
regarding the wind
Because if we ask a village elder
about the wind, he does not know the answer
It is something that is commonly unknown
And I was wondering if you could share something about the wind
If a person dreams of the wind, it is because they’re
going to be hit by a car
What he asks is regarding the history of the wind in ancient times.
He was a strong mythological being who climbed
up to the sky in a swirl
The whirlpool is formed from the earth in a circle and
slowly ascending to the sky
If you could see one now you would realize that
he forms from the earth to vanish in the sky
If the wind is always among us and even gives
signs of when someone is their chosen one
If he liked a woman a lot, he
manifests through the swirl
He is very good at picking people
They have something, not deeply from the wind, but if something
from the dream, what meaning does the wind have in the dream
Can you talk a bit about the footprints? That you are very good at finding tracks
It's because of the herding, we are very good at herding
Being a woman in Wayuu society, the importance
That it has, How does that work here?
The importance of women? Yeah
can you talk to us a bit
On the social organization of the Wayúu
Can you tell us a bit about that?
Our children that are women, they are our family
Instead, the sons of the men are belong to
another family (mother's). That's how it is
Why are women important for the future?
Women are important and necessary because
they are the ones that are going to keep that learning
They are the ones who are going to share everything about culture,
They are the ones that will preserve what we are
They are going to make our culture continue when we are no longer here.
So you don't get lost, of course.
yes, she mentioned how important and how is our matrilineal structure
And how is that presented on a day-to-day basis?
More than anything it is how we live that tradition
That is why I also clarify it a lot, the maternal line
She said, the one who has rights over the children is the woman
Because the paternal does not have as much involvement
We also saw red a lot. How important is it?
that for culture? for the women?
The dance too, if you can explain the yonna dance
They are very curious about the yonna when
they saw the children dance
Can you tell us what is the yonna? And why is
dance in a circle
And why did the sky dance backwards?
So it should be, that is their position since ancient times
But tell us a little more
Since ancient times it has been transmitted like this,
he must face the woman during the dance
Likewise, the woman goes straight ahead, that's why she avoids him,
or they cross paths to make him take more turns seeking her, making him tired
It is known that several steps are shown in the yonna
Can you talk to us about that?
Yes, there are several steps, for example the horse race
If a girl stands out in that step, her makeup goes
according to that
And when they see her, they immediately recognize her by her ability.
in that step because each one has a specialty
The pace of the horse race is very traditional,
although not very common
Today they are taking it up again
Because that step was taken from horse racing
and they played with imitating it
By imitating it they adopted it at the dance
That's right, well she just talked about the yonna, about
tradition, bordering on the concept of the circle
ok ma'am thank you
Thank you for talking about our culture
What was recorded so it stays later for the children
So that when you are not here, they can say that they have at least the recording of their grandmother's words
Because the words are there, but, they can be
forgotten too
Of course, because nobody saves them and that is why they are forgotten
Yes, but now it is recorded on the camera and that
you will see it later
Yes, the children become Westernized, at least one of
Takes an interest in culture
And if they wonder how our culture was like, they
Surely can find an answer in the recording
Yes, surely in the future children will wonder about
the stories and tales that you’re sharing with us
Yes, because today's children do not follow
the teaching of our elders
Yes, it is true, see that there are no children in si'ira anymore
(wayúu weaving) and these are very necessary to keep us
The kou'su (wayúu footwear) is no longer used now either
that was our identity
She just spoke about the importance of preserving and preserving identity.
Maybe a message you want to take to the world
Kids these days
They don't own their culture as much as before
In the past people respected each other, they lived in peace and harmony
Nowadays nephews want to hit their uncles
No respect even for older brothers
It is the same with women, they no longer respect
their older brothers
We ourselves have affected our culture
If they asked you what your message would be to talk and
strengthen our culture? what would you say
It is what they want to hear, to know how to reaffirm
what we are as wayuu
Because even the Wayúu youth of today
devalue our culture
Before, young people respected their uncles
If an uncle caught his nephew's attention,
he was silent and listened
He waited for their uncle to finish talking and didn't answer him
Today's young kids, like you, don't like
being called out and wish harm upon their mothers
Today's children and young people must highlight
the role of their uncle when they are in a conflict
But that depends on us mothers, we must
enhance those values and principles
Although they do not value our teachings
And I know why I'm saying because I see it, I don't say it just because
Well, more than a message for the world is a message for the culture itself
We need to return to the times of the past
Where respect was the main value of culture
In these moments we have already lost our children, they do not want to respect us
Our uncles are already disrespecting each other
Then it is to return to teach the new generations, that we return to be Wayúu in humanity.
Thank you
Thank you very much he says.