What does that mean?
symbols that are being put?
ah, what I'm going to place here.
It is the symbol of the sun
here
and
this.
Is
the same.
AND
these.
These paintings are going to be for parties only.
and they are like, they are the fine ones
because there are others too, kind of…
as for daily and this is it,
which is a
kind of canned powder.
Is this.
And where does the dust come from?
It is from female tree fungus species
that they produce from the mountains and that occurs when it is already winter.
By
when it is cold, that produces the cold
species of mushrooms. It has its time
in winter, that happens in November.
So
can you introduce yourself, who are you, what do you really do?
I introduce myself,
my name is Romelia Montiel,
I am the one who knows the Kayushipana community here in Alta
Guajira Nazareth
I belong to the Uriana clan,
I am from, my origin
It's there on the hill that's back there.
Sekuolu (name of the hill)
So I'm going to talk about medicinal plants,
to a few species of plants that are here, uff
there is still more
that is, still
There is after this and there is still more.
The one who keeps it, Macuira, is our grandmother.
It's where they were all born, it's where they spawned
God to us so that this plant
will stay here with us, because all this
They were humans before us.
That's why it has its magic, it has its spirit.
We respect them, we respect them a lot
that we still preserve the ancestral tradition.
As,
as already
I have done a lot of research,
my research is so deep for many years
It is behind everything, not only in the medicinal plant
but in everything that has to do with our culture
ancestral.
How have you investigated? What is the method?
I have investigated with the old men of Macuira
that there are a few
that no longer exist here on earth, they are with daddy God
and those who are left after them
They are the grandchildren, the grandparents.
That's why I keep them.
My grandmothers are also people who are
They like all this,
They are people who have spirit too.
Are
shamans, they are spiritualists and all that, they are like us
we call it Outsü.
We the Wayuu indigenous people, Outsü.
because it's called Outsü, because that one comes
of vision, of vision.
Of the O'u (see further).
That's why we call it
Outsü,
because she is the one who sees, the one who watches, the one who sees for us
the one who sees through spirituality.
They are the ones who work so that they can give lives,
give more life to everything,
to the children, to the elderly, to everything, to everything, to everyone
that protects them against illness and against evil
spirit of the immune.
AHA.
So to start all this off, let's explain
colors. First the color red,
you see a red cloth here, so for you this is,
It is as if they saw a simple tablecloth.
But this has its symbol, why?
Because we have respect for all this, because this has its
magic, it has its spirit, red
It is what keeps everything in us Wayuu, it is what protects,
is the one who,
I mean that's the one that,
where we respect the color red more
because it symbolizes many things in the Wayuu culture,
because he is the one who keeps, he is the one who gives the dream,
It is the one that reveals dreams,
He is the one who has to do with everything, he is the one who takes care of us. One
take this
to be able to get something out of the mountain or get something out of a tree,
One wears a red patch or
a piece of red thread.
These are the oldest skein threads there,
I don't think they sell them anymore.
That,
If a piece is left on the mountain it is for power,
talk to the spirit of the plants, so one can
Grab part of those plants, why not grab it and that's it
You sit there to talk to them,
to ask, to give change, to say
Well, I come to ask you to give me this,
and I leave you this in exchange,
that's how we talk to him
And one wears his red cloth too or one dresses in red
to look for all this.
It's not that one is getting off to a bad start.
Because? because there are people who just go and start, not like that
further.
How is it?
they go blind,
They are left with other defects that one day they will leave it
Because? because their spirituality does not respect them.
Each one has their spirituality,
there is male and female
like us,
like us there are women and there are men, like this
the plants
There is also in that aspect.
That's why they each
one fulfills his function.
What is it for
each one already has its function, each one has its
function.
He fulfills his role.
And when are you going
well searching, harvesting,
does that also happen with a thread?
You leave him, you don't leave him just like that
because they don't have a hand,
one goes where the root is, one digs and buries
leave what has to be, it can be a necklace
because that necklace is because I'm not going to wear it again
this, this stays there forever
and he is also staying with one, because yes
There is one who says no, I am going to make the change another day,
I'm going to change with something else. No it can not be done.
Now what you gave him
I already said it. Already
what you started is already for you,
you are never going to return it,
That's how it is, that's why one has to respect it.
Is it always an exchange?
It's always an exchange one
one, because we humans to protect from them
we are present, because they are the ones who protect one.
Spirituality, what one respects,
the tradition of grandparents,
just as they left them, so we have to continue, so
we have to teach our children,
so they will also respect.
One has to teach them respect for the plant,
towards all this, just as we teach to respect
to other people, like this
we have to teach our children, our grandchildren,
to respect this.
What they have, because those are theirs,
because they are in their territory.
We don't get this from another territory, it's from here
Of the territory
Uriana, from here all this mountain range, this mountain range
It is full of everything, which is what it doesn't have,
He even has amulets.
Amulets?
Of course
that is
very reserved,
That is not here within this, that is separate.
That has
even more respect, because they can even
ask for expensive things,
They can ask for gold or they can ask for a beef to eat,
so that one can grasp
that.
Even more expensive than this.
By
that we respect that part and the grandparents know
What each thing is for is that and it teaches one and
One too
reserve it as they reserved it, then
we also reserve,
We keep it in there.
The most we know.
When one wants it is from one that a person crawls
I want, I want, it is done.
As?
How are you
It is already done.
This is done. It's dry.
This is already macerated, dry.
This is
macerated.
another species of plant, but that cannot be
nor place in plain sight.
Because?
Because that is one
for the preservation of the baby in the mother's womb.
So that he doesn't get the evil eye, so that he doesn't get
pain in childbirth when going to
give birth to a person
What did they do when there was no doctor before?
It is with that, all
Those plants. And it was bought, it was changed
for a goat, for one of these things.
For a goat,
For a goat worth this
at that time. Because now no,
that now
If my baby goes through, that's a cesarean section, go to the hospital,
Not before, it's with that, that's it.
That's why the midwife is there, there are the
people best suited for that. Is the person that
will do the echogram
Wayuu, who see sex and everything.
Of course, that's why they are called Wayuu echograms because they fix that.
and they come and say right away, this one is female, this one
It is male,
so it's in the belly.
Let's get started.
This is a maraca,
Let's start and here we are with the reds.
Then the maraca,
This is the first who gives life, the one who saves
all.
Through Yüi (marijuana) which is
the tobacco leaf from here, from Macuira,
This is what they also call Macuira,
This is the Macuira.
Tobacco that
They are from here, because there are tobaccos that are very
different from this.
Instead of tobacco they write Macuira.
And does it come from here?
Is that why the name?
He was born here and are from here originally,
from here.
They are very typical from here,
it's tobacco
this.
and this one who, the
that calls the spirit of this, when one eats it
it already works
to cure everything.
And so they were all born
these.
In the middle
of that,
of that spiritualist who
exists in our
culture.
AND
this is a species
of rattan,
that's here too,
This is also there in the Serranía de Perijá,
of this, there are things that are
far away and exists here with us.
As?
Because God put it, that's how it has to be, because that's what they are,
They are from a cold land and where there is a river and that
and here it occurs where there is no river.
This.
This serves to
When one makes a fracture, then one
part of the bone and that,
it scratches
with a stone, it is placed, it has its,
his diet, his diet is long,
there are things that should not be eaten,
the meats, the cheese most of all, the milk.
This with this.
When you are taking that, you can't?
It can't be done,
has to be under confinement
with this because it works quickly
and
the bone is composed quickly
and returns to its normal state.
And that thing about the
the music there?
No,
Now that, now that, another different magic is coming and this
and those things that are already from here.
And they are also powerful because,
Why does it have its magic and that,
and
with people who dream, that's what maceration does.
It's this one.
Here are some, some leaves of a plant
which is useful for the person who has menstrual cramps.
This serves those who suffer from it.
With this,
these are
leaves, they are from here too. This is when the person already
they are giving them cancer,
when she is already getting cancer in the womb,
when it comes
bleeding and it is frequent and with this you can
and it has a smell of,
Of,
from the rotten matrix.
Happens.
What is your name?
That's a kind of hawapi,
when the person can no longer
more and those days it is already rotting, to save it
he saves himself with that.
As? miracles are done
with that.
It is very miraculous.
This for us,
of an illness of us women.
When you get an infection there
in the matrix everything
fixes it.
And it is so important because before, as there was no
doctor, how did you get your womb removed?
nothing, there is no one, because people were dying,
You could and you would die, there was no more.
Not now.
And that the person
and this one is expensive, they sell it, they don't show it at all,
but,
They show him when he is like this,
but not in leaves like that, I am
I dare to do this now
with you.
Uh-huh, sure.
Everything has its change,
as I say.
This is the baby's bath,
when he is newborn he is the special one for them
naked
For baths and the Majayülü (lady in menarche) afterwards,
when you get off the hammock and the
confinement, this bathes him for a month,
He bathes with this.
And this is also taken so that you do not get sick,
Because the matrix also shrinks, too
this one and it is very common because this one is very well known
here,
No
They are like there are some that are not, you can hardly see them.
You have to walk.
Which one is that?
It is the naked Indian.
and this is the
the bija leaf
and that
women also take it
Confinement, at the time of his puberty.
This.
And also the newly born ones,
they take it.
And the child drinks and the newborn to clean
the
phlegm and in there what he fed with the
Mom, you have to clean it, it stays very clean.
And this is another kind of
Jawapi, they take this
women after childbirth.
This.
And it is very common of this too.
They are not from the mountains, from here in the region,
flat part.
How do you find them?
are you?
How do you find them in the mountains?
What is found in the mountains is different, like this one,
This is in the mountains, it doesn't exist here,
on the flat part, on the lower part, it is
It is the anamu.
And how do you know which is which when you're searching?
As
one knows it by the smell and everything by the leaf, everything
indigenous people know what it is, this is the anamú, which is good
carcinogenic
and to
the flu too
and a lot.
And this is another one too, the Guazuma, this is the Guazuma,
this is the one that,
this one works for everyone
viruses, as if to say
for whooping cough.
Everything that has to do with measles, smallpox
When you get old, then this is where
boiled,
It is taken in panela and also when diarrhea occurs.
acute that there is almost no cure, and people
now you can, now with this
for.
How is it done?
Is taken
It is not macerated, it is taken
And this is also another, another line of,
of
those bitter ones too
takes the Majayülü in their confinement too,
people who are sickly, who are skinny,
that she looks like an old lady, she takes it and turns back
plump and shiny.
With this.
But hey, it's good, isn't it?
smell it
you can take it
No.
Not for Neko who is there.
Something I know.
Put.
And yet it has.
AHA.
As you know.
Forks. For.
And this is the famous Wararat (Bejuco) that
It is the vine that is here, it is bitter and if this
HE
it takes a lot, here they are used quite a bit in the territory
and in other places they look for it, you buy it in pieces like that
They sell it where there is none.
On the other hand, here one has it like this.
Because
Of course because here we have it, we are rich in these.
What is your name?
Wararat as a kind of vine, like a vine.
So they are the
and he has a lot of family about this,
They have a lot of family, different, different.
There are white and brown and there are this color.
And do they have a smell?
It has a smell and it has a taste and it has feet to
burping in people whose stomach is full
and they can't one day and not again,
with this it is cleaned and
that everything is bad for him and with this he gets better,
it is cleaned, it is purified.
And this is another species of jawapi,
This is what Majayülü takes in the running of the bulls.
This.
Can you explain
for someone who doesn't know, what is the running of the bulls?
The confinement of what, of the Majayülü, or any confinement?
the one that represents the beginning for women, right?
Of course the Majayülü do their confinement, the mothers,
we mothers,
The grandmothers, we do the running of the bulls, for what purpose?
So that?
Because that girl is going to spend her life
to be a woman, she is no longer a girl, she is now a woman
and this woman has to value what she is too.
Before society she is no longer a girl, she is now a woman who
she's going to be, she's going to be a mother one day,
she's going to be a grandmother, she's not going to be anymore
the same toys from yesterday,
This is another role and those where women settle
and the girls to read, where one teaches them everything,
to knitting, to work, in the kitchen, in everything,
in everything, what her job is, what she is going to do one day
and what I eat
She is going to be seen before society.
She deserves your respect.
All that she can't be touching like before,
so she grabbed the other child and pushed him
because that will no longer be touching that child
nor to the other, nothing,
but she is going to do her job now
and it will be respected.
He who dares to grab her is because
They want to pay a goat for the performance.
Yes, that is a very big respect.
No
because he didn't give us that, no, not more for the touch, that
It can't be for him either,
must be respected.
and this plant
It is very good for phlegm,
Mashulü (cotton leaves)
Is
this good for phlegm,
when a child is born with phlegm and suffers from that and with this
it does,
are made of,
It becomes a winter thing, it is baptized.
And this
It is another type of vine too.
This is for
a person who does not want to have more children,
let that be so,
This is…
Don't you want to have more children?
Whether
you want to sterilize, well, you take this,
A bun is made with this amount.
And this
is
the famous Kepisuta
this
It is the bath for babies and is also used for flu and
It's a good bath.
And this the Cortex of the
Carob tree,
which is very good too
to clean the blood
and when one,
when one sees that one
It gives him reluctance and everything, so with this
the blood is cleaned.
This one they call Bacchus's eye is called Chi'pira,
That's in the mountains, it's a kind of
bejuco
What purpose does that serve in our culture?
This helps so that when they are given to children, children,
Not the girls, let's go with the boys, with the men.
It is given to children when they later develop
Also, it is saved for a day and it is taken.
So that? For your health,
so that the rum does not become so tampered with
someday, when they go to take their chirinche.
It's not going to be rigged, but they measure their rum with it.
And this is also Soluou'ta, it is a kind of
very good for pain, for inflammation,
To reduce inflammation it can be
a blow, a bruise.
Or it could be, it could also be
When you get a toothache, you scratch it, it macerates.
with this already
goodbye pain.
San Diego Dentistry.
And that
It is also for a phlegm, this is also, they are
They are… What is it called?
They call it cloud, those live over there
in the mountains up there and it is called a cloud,
yes because he is the one who calls the clouds,
the cloud goes down in the mountains, because there is enough of that
Up there.
And this also works,
because the phlegm and illness of children
newly born.
Which one is missing?
Come on let's go with this one.
Well, that's what I said.
So this one is, this one is for,
for the person when they are pregnant,
so that there is no pain when she is going to give birth
he takes it when he already has his,
when he is nine months old, eight months already
to give birth,
that happens and maceration is also done
in a
chirinche and rub the belly so that the baby
don't be born with evil
eye and with other things.
And this is for the evil of
spirit.
This is for
the evil of spirit. When a person suffers from a bad spirit,
This is taken, grated and
take
And that evil spirit that is bothering you goes away,
may be cause of,
of,
other things that are not natural, can be false,
So it pushes him away.
And this is a seed that is a seed
that comes from other parts, they are from cold land
and here we also use it to cure diseases,
also of
for,
serves for
this serves to,
It's called Sekuanrü,
What is it for?
It serves to reduce inflammation.
That more than anything else.
Ah!
To wonder.
This is the wonder that serves as a bathroom,
to reduce the
fever
and to deworm
also.
Deworm more than in children the roots are used,
It is counted that only one is cooked so that
take.
And there is also another dewormer,
It's also this one.
This seed that is from the great granite,
It is there,
The great granite.
With this
which when it is made has a brown color
and this here
this
it is macerated and taken,
for the parasite
and also the animals
They burn it and it gets into the donkey's anus
when there is also a cover,
that no longer shits,
so to make him shit it is like a suppository
for the animals.
AHA.
Good.
Do they also need?
and this is the famous tua tua,
This tua tua has,
has, vote liquid
and that liquid that is here is useful for sight.
When it gets dirty
in the eyes then they get,
he puts that on.
And it also serves to,
for
clean the blood and to lose weight
this.
A very fat person, with a lot of fat and a paunch
and take this and it is ready.
AHA.
And this,
the festival,
this is the festival
what we call the scorpion tail,
It's a vulgar name.
Aja Aja.
This is used for infection
in the throat
and internally too.
This.
This one too
It's called bija, they call it bija, white bija and
This spice is malua that we call,
These are typical from here too,
not like malambo, because malambo is from somewhere else.
On the other hand, this one here is very typical from here.
and this is for Buddhism,
that one can take it too and one can burn it too.
And with this it is also done
It has its rituality.
It is also to distance
To the evil spirits in the houses and it burns like yes
out,
that…
There are many ways
how to avoid diseases with this
and that's why children use handles and
to what end?
because they are going to keep away the diseases,
of flu from other things.
That's why
we use it quite a bit.
And then what is like anti COVID?
Which of those did they use during COVID?
This.
This is the one that
We call Wasim.
Anti-COVID and there is also,
Wararat
How did you know that this worked against COVID?
What is that process of knowing what plant
is it used for what things?
And this too,
This almost subsides in almost half of the
mountain range, of these
They take it and sell it around, they take it to save
Uribia's brothers.
They looted them in the hills behind this.
This why
In reality, it is what saves many lives
and thank God we are here because we have it
here.
Here that pod
It didn't arrive, it did arrive here, but we scared them away.
Well, it's just that what's here
Right now these are the few,
Because if I had everyone here, better said,
It would be all day.
Those are the ones I'm showing you,
for now.
I already explained
colors.
And also,
can explain some of the yonna,
dance, dance, I don't know, are you one who teaches
right?
Oh yes I am one of the teachers
those who want to learn from.
AHA.
Uh-huh, sure.
And yes.
So what does the yonna mean, when it is danced?
And for what?
What is it for?
that's what we call that
If this is the Outsü
"He gets drunk with this," Yonna asks.
And that is why there are the variants of the yonna.
What are the variants?
What they imitated from animals later,
because the common
is the step
common that we call that are from our ancestors,
that they were the first that they learned
to do that
Epichikua, which is the one that,
which
he begat the yonna
here
on earth, when in those times, in times
remote.
And when one dances?
One?
One dances yonna when the Outsü orders
If there is going to be a yonna, when there is a sick person, he locks himself in,
It is saved and when the people leave,
the family has to be happy,
It has to make you want to dance,
because one is not going to have his yonna
Having a sick person doesn't make you want to do anything,
like you just want to cry,
but one is happy to see him
He has healed the child and the Majayülü
and when you lower it too
because it has to come out before society, before it
see enough,
the yonna is made, the feast is made,
You know that you have to get out, that you are going to get out.
There are many types of doing the yonna,
at housewarmings,
It is the marking of animals.
At the inauguration of the orchards, the graves
There is a lot, a lot, a lot.
When you inaugurate the water, when you do your
Wells, when already,
when, when Juya (old father)
He
He is angry with us and
he doesn't want to come, so you call him on the drum
As? eating roasted corn,
eating grit (Sa'wa) all that
calling him there, appreciating that he comes,
that someone talks to him, someone tells him you don't see me as dirty, you
You don't see sweaty, one goes and dances and one has to wallow
the sand so that it can see that one is dirty, that one
you need it,
one is calling him, one like that with the spirit.
Of course, everything that has to do with
and that goes from house to house.
So at home one cannot say there is no food,
because if one says, one goes wrong,
cannot say, one has to consume
whether it be beans or whatever,
not so much the meat but the beans that he loves and
scrambled with toasted corn.
Yeah.
Those traditions are no longer seen,
That is rather dying,
but you have to revive it, one
you have to remember, one has to do that
so that
the little ones who were born after one see it
and they also have to familiarize themselves with that
And they have to feel
that are theirs, that are their culture,
that you don't have to feel sorry for him or be afraid of
exit on the Piyoi which is the Yonna track.
You have to lose your fear.
There are people who are afraid of traveling too.
Does painting also have to do with
part of culture?
Of course makeup is so important too.
because that's what goes with it, it's what accompanies
and the red scarf too
that accompanies the Yonna.
On the runway, makeup, accessories,
all that has to do with it.
And you
What is your relationship with nature or with plants
or with this place?
With Macuira?
Take care of them and respect them.
Ujum,
No no.
Don't take out so much just to have it there,
you know that when something is
so important that one is going to use it, it is not,
He's not going to take it out just to have it there,
but to use it for whatever is useful.
It's very curious,
like this time about medicinal plants.
Of course, since we have this opportunity here,
Now we don't start them just to start,
but because you have to see what
We are going to do with the plant, we do not throw it away without doing anything.
when you were little
how did you discover that you wanted to know more?
Learn more about this?
I through my ancestors, through the elders,
the elderly, it can be a man or a woman, but one goes
and one
investigate, one
He does his interview with them, what is it for,
at what point can one grab it,
Why? Why is it so important?
what is your reason,
their actions towards us?
You ask all those questions with old people.
Not everyone can be Outsü
No.
Those are hereditary, those are hereditary
What if their grandparents had
anywhere it can be
mom's side or dad's side
If they liked one, I accept it.
And there are some who
I'm not afraid, I'm not going to accept it,
He is very strong and he puts in everything, no, he is good at it,
because as there are three types of
those spiritualisms.
There is lalüi, there
He is the one who dreams and his dreams are true,
when that gives its predictions
Well, things happen before they happen,
the things that are going to happen, they tell you in a dream,
just as it is going to happen, so it has to be,
but wich ones?
Why do they dream?
Because to avoid,
to keep it away, to avoid it, to stop it from continuing,
so that he does not fall into such bad things, with bad temptations
They warn you beforehand, the alüi is the one who sees the most in the dream.
On the other hand, Outsü looks for the spirit,
read the ashes,
in the,
in firewood, a firewood is used
tender and burns.
So there it does connect with that,
with the ashes of what is happening, what is going to happen.
Yes it is an evil eye on a child, if it is for
inaugurate a house,
Yes, the devil is there, if he lives there, we must stay away,
You have to not put him in his way, you have to keep him away from there,
ask them for the land, the site.
In exchange for?
Then one asks for the change,
If they say in the change,
that I want
a black goat, no, I want a red goat
and that red goat
how it should be eaten, like this, if it is in soup, if it is stewed,
That's what their tobacco says, which I didn't use before.
The one who uses tobacco is the piachi (Oulaküt)
The Piache is the one who uses tobacco and
chirinche
And sometimes they are not so correct
The Piaches are already people who
works with the devil and who works with the good spirit
with the evil spirit and so on.
That's why they call him
witches
Because they do good things and
bad things, and the negative part
and the positive part does good things.
On the other hand, Outsü does the right thing, does its
job.
He hides nothing what
He says, whether he wants to or not, but I'm going to tell him,
Tell me if you have, if you have a patient there
there he is going to die, he says no, I think I can't anymore
But with this one, this one is going to die.
Why am I going to insist so much if this no longer exists?
He already left for Jeepira and I can't get the oxen anymore,
He's no longer on the road, I didn't reach him, he's already gone.
That is why family members have to be satisfied,
What are you going to do if Outsü already told the truth.
On the other hand, the other too, which is the alüi,
then that is the one who works only with dreams
and work with plants and work with other things
and they are also true.
In all their things, they are strict in their things.
Well, that's what we talked about,
They are different.
And now comes a spiritualism
now with the Piache that is beginning to
sleep
deep and then the voice changes
and to say that I don't know, it means that no, that I don't
wronged, that they did you wrong, that
There is a funeral there in your house,
You don't have to take him out for so many.
They say now.
That you have a doll there,
that I'm going to get it for so many, that if they give me that much yes
and if they give me necklaces and they give me goats and they give me cows and they give me
my amount of money, well
That's pure business.
Now, that Outsü no longer exists and the Alüi no longer exists.
There are some, but they are isolated in the community and in the family,
in some. There is
some who still believe that, there are others who don't, they
They say I'm not going to send him out and
they tie her hair
on the other Outsü
which is the most practical to what they are there
that since they are new,
can be removed.
There are some that do
They say that, if I want, well they settle it and
it
They do with their teacher and learn and do
things,
the Outsü
It's the one that, the one that
first he knew all the
floors
through their spirits
and every day new ones explode
things.
Throughout,
the same in the light and also with your dream explodes
new things and meet new
no, the grandparents, the family doesn't know him
and suddenly he knows them, why?
Because they send him to look for him where he is,
there it is and it's useful for this
and that,
I have given him his explanation as it is, how he has to work.
Very good.
Well.
That is the origin of all this.
Well, we've talked about magic and that, what?
is magic for you or more like spirituality?
Not the magic is the spirits, the Aseyuu
what we call the spirit,
that one does not see, but one feels it, one asks for it,
They warn you
to
one, is the one who gives one the power, everything, are things
powerful, it is a powerful spirit that one
He doesn't know if he is there, if he is here, if he is with us,
That is with us at the moment, because this is here,
That is in us, but we do not feel it,
We don't see it, but we do feel it because
I'm sorry.
I don't know if you feel it.
The question also to
you
is
many say that the
the ancestors of one they already lost
life, right,
they connect with the Outsü
to help her with certain things,
how to avoid
accidents and things like that.
They tell them, I dreamed about my grandmother she told me
to bathe my daughter
That is that spirit is when it uses the body
of the person who believes in magic,
who has that ritual, who believes in their belief
live with her, that's why she sends you to that person,
because he doesn't tell everyone, I wish it were
So, I told him everything, his everything, we would all know everything,
we would all be wise,
because that has to be a chosen person
for that person to whom you want to talk, to whom you want to tell
his things,
to those who want to prevent things that cannot happen.
That's what happens.
And also it
older ones, those that no longer exist
You also feel the purest smell at night.
Who are these people?
The old people who lived in that territory,
the old people who are underground and buried.
They walk by the spirit, but one does not see,
We then Wayuu believe so much,
so we feel that smell at night.
You have to set up the coffee,
We have to make coffee, grandpa has arrived, grandma has arrived
to toast, poor thing, comes to visit us.
Well, since they lived here, that was theirs,
here they had their roses, here they had
his bower,
here they had their little house,
They had good traces of her here.
It's around here that they urinated like this.
One believes that.
That's why they come to visit him.
She doesn't come to do harm, she comes to visit,
but from time to time he doesn't come here every time.
There are some who are also quick-tempered.
That also starts to scream at him
well, get out of here, you're not going to be there,
there with your bad smell here, because you have to
shake your ugly panties
here, shake it further, he tells him
and makes the maraca
So
nothing else
and immediately the smell disappears,
because that is a belief.
That
still lives, still exists
here with us.
We already mentioned
right now the Outsü can see the traces
of the souls that have already left for Jeepira, you could speak
What happens to the soul according to culture
of us?
well it is said that they are going to Jeepira and all that.
Could you talk about that?
Of course, Jeepira
It's a place, it's a place,
They say it is
a kind of ravine that we don't know if it is in the sky,
yes it is here on earth,
but it is between us.
That's not something from another world.
It can be in the sea or
It can be here on earth.
That is a belief, because
That exists, but
but there are others, but like us sometimes
The literature of the Bible says that heaven is over there,
that when we die
over there, one is no longer left with that literature
and that's what the ancestors say, they say that Jeepira
is here with us, is it in the sea or is it
here with the earth
where we start,
We do not leave, but we lay down our bones,
the bones are lying,
but the soul continues to live with people,
the old people say.
Where? Yes when they are tired of being here, they
Now the land for them is the sea, they are in the sea.
Is that also related
why they have two wakes, can you explain that?
So.
Which wake?
The exhumation?
Of course, the exhumation is another wake.
It is already
when people come back again,
they come back
At the moment when the body is exhumed they return.
Now if they can go again, they won't come back again.
I say that they return to look at their remains,
to look at people.
That's why the exhumers
one tells them when it is a woman and takes
rest of a man, one tells him,
They greet him after his exhumation
already washed and everything clean.
He says oh my grandfather arrived.
Grandpa tells her, she could be a woman,
the one he is exhuming, but because she already lives with him
and his spirit, his soul lives with him and is in his heart.
One tells him “grandpa has arrived, how is grandpa?”
everyone says,
because, because she just exhumed the rest of her
grandfather.
When she is one, when she is also a woman,
and the man is,
the one who exhumes is a man,
then one also says to her “oh grandma”,
And says
then he like
just think about your current situation
He says “not at all, be serious” (said)
I don't
like that they
say like that, because of course, because you think about nothing more,
He does not think about the spirit he is exhuming.
That's what it is.
and let's say the sugar curtain
is a place where they also go
when people die or not?
No, they call it the end of the candle, not those are literatures that...
but if the Jeepirachi,
Jeepirachi is the name of a hill that is inside the sea.
Aha.
So that's the place, because I looked into that too.
What's up with that?
There are some gentlemen, there were, they lived
but they no longer exist,
gentlemen who lived close to him,
They moved over time later,
because I couldn't take it anymore
with the moo of the cow the meow of the sheep,
the barking of the dog, the braying of the donkey and all that
what it feels,
the child's cry, the old woman's cry, the stove and so on.
And there are things, even the drum feels there
on that hill,
inside that sea.
So they,
once they were how many, many goats
has its people
and in the day there is nothing, but at night it is the thing,
starting at 11 pm, they feel that way there. So what
They moved away,
because because the old man was looking he saw logs, he lit
he saw everything.
There were voices and all that.
And he fell asleep alone.
So what are you doing spying on us?
If you still want to live here,
Either you come here or you stay there still!
you move, go where
They told him, vacate this.
They have to leave their houses,
They just leave with their clothes and everything.
He left everything, how did they live? like this,
They lived like this, clearing the mountain
and they put some tents there and over time they built
He built his yotojoro (woody trunk of the cardon)
This is how the old people who lived told
about him
Jeepirachi, and
what they call ship and what they call I don't know what
and there they disappear
they. That
They are distant, they are ships
who come from afar, travelers on their cruise and
They all disappear,
the salt
sinks it
there near the
hill.
Well,
we do it to introduce you again,
just to make sure that we have
who are you and what do you do?
and where are you?
Who I am?
I am Romelia
Montiel
Oriana,
I am the ancestral knower of the Kayushipana community
AHA.
I am an artisan,
I am a teacher in all of them.
In crafts, in yonna, in recreations
and everything that has to do with it
with children and adults too,
Why not?
the one who wants to learn new things,
wants to learn to do things, he wants to exploit his
your mind
with regard
to culture.
And we are in the Uriana territory here in Uliana which is in Kayushipana
I
I am also a traditional doctor in this, me too
I do my ritual with the Majayülü
I wanted to know the importance
to pass knowledge to new generation to children
and I don't know how important that is to you.
and for…
Sure, it's so important.
I want someone like you
who knows more than us too, who
make a book,
It is a project towards all that,
to medicinal plants and everything,
and we help them and they get to have anything,
Any worry.
We help again with anything you want to know
if everything is
to deepen and unite more of the knowledge.
and for the children?
For children too
And it is possible
any project
what can be done with children also the yonna in which
we are part of that
Also, what happens is that we
because we lack resources
That's why we don't have the clothing for that,
because there's a siding over here and all that
What does it have to do with culture?
but we are low on resources, we don't have enough for that, that's why
We are left, but with three pieces of cloth we have we teach.
Because it is an interest.
AND.
A diversion.
Another question we want to ask.
It's it's.
My experience and when.
That.
Yes, everything is done.
And I would like to know how knowledge
that you have shared with us, you share here,
if you yourself
You say that not everyone is chosen to know this,
then because you feel that at the same time,
If you don't allow it,
I would record more
and not everyone should be like it for it to work,
but someone is chosen
as
we are chosen.
Yes sir, of course,
chosen like some with clear, why not,
I know that you are not going to go for this sheet and where I am
I'm going to look for you or you're not going to invest as much,
because instead.
Is
more or less that, because not anymore.
Everything says.
But let's say
that we are recording, well the idea is that
many people see it and it's like that's good
to preserve nature or how it would be.
Of course, of course,
clear,
that's good for preserving nature and all that.
Well, let them also respect that they have still
tradition still lives with us,
because we are not all, not only
in theory but in the practical part.
We still keep it
because we are
still the root of all heart and spirit.
With them
we are dedicated to.
These.
Seek encouraging wisdom.
There is a dream,
They tell me that they are going to do it, they are going to work and that
It will be clear.
We are, we are leaders before.
The lo.
What is traditional medicine?
House of God, what he wants,
because what you have not understood here
in the person
that is going to be another for them,
they they they are chosen.
Clear.
Through dreams they say and if they accept, then they
They continue, of course, in that process.
But if you reject what you want, soon a piece of paper.
I don't know which ones
are written and thus reject the proposal of and.
It remains or remains like this again,
Thus, without anything, nothing comes for that.
No, it doesn't start for me.
I have always been me, mine in my grandmother
and something and I like
She says that she is my dream with true, with.
Hers. And especially with dreams.
But there are also out there
my grandmother's footprint.
With her dreams.
The grandmother I mentioned was very pretty.
She died when she was 100 or so years old.
From that, she did not suffer from.
Illness and we have enough of their grandchildren
We know enough that they are, so we are following
her steps.
She is from a whole family of 100 years to
all.
Thank you so much,
Thank you and I think it's fine.
That to those who.