Tell us your name what do you do for living
My name is Oscar Pushaina.
And what do you do here?
I come here to work with salt
Sometimes I arrive here at dawn, at 4 in the morning
And I leave around ten
At the very least
And since what age have you worked here?
I have been here for 25 years
Well, and the salt, how is it made? or what is the process?
how is it done?
The saltwater is poured over there to evaporate there
And then it is passed here so that it curdles here
And the crystal is formed
And how important is that mineral in your life?
Can you be more specific about the question?
When did you start working here? Yeah
Did you start small or what?
Well I said that I have been here for 25 years
Yes, but could you tell us from what age did you start?
And then how long have you been here?
I have been working with salt for 25 years.
And regarding the last question
About the importance of the salt? Why is it so necessary?
can you tell us
How do you get to work here?
you can comment us now
For us, salt is important for food
To help us with the needs
And what relationship does it have with the environment?
With the elements, with the rain, with the sea or with the wind
The question he asked you is why is salt formed
here and not somewhere else?
Why precisely here?
That I don't know
Here where the salt is, the sun is hot
and there is breeze right? Yeah.
The sea is salty, but specifically
here it is even saltier
So since it is saltier here, there is more sun and breeze when the water passes
It crystallizes, if you tell us more about it
You can say it in wayuunaiki too
It is formed by the sun, the water evaporates and the
breeze is drying it
When it rains you can't process the salt or anything
But when the sun is very hot we work
more and we earn more
Can you tell us a bit if this came from your grandparents?
Your interest in salt
How did you get interested? or how did you learn?
Who did you learn this from? because there is always one
who learned it first
Yes, was it the job of your grandparents or your parents?
Yes, of course it was the job of our parents.
When we were children our parents
brought us to learn the job and once learned
we started working on our own and then they retired
Many speak of salt as an energy that has
something more spiritual
With the wind and all the elements together, right?
Does that have a spiritual implication for you?
or is that seen in production somehow?
About this
University students say that salt has a
spiritual connotation in the sense that
It is used for spiritual purposes
That in our culture I don't know since salt is
just for food
Because it flavors the food. also for sale
But, our grandparents previously exchanged it.
Yes, they exchanged it with beans, corn
With food like grains
Now they sell it for money, to buy clothes
or for the school expenses of our children
Or we buy our watch, phone or bicycle,
thanks to this job
OK, thanks a lot.