Sir, can you tell me your name and where you are from?
I am. My name is Hamilton Sierra.
I'm not from here
but my wife is from here, from Manaure.
I am from there on the lower Magdalena coast.
How long have you been working here?
Two years ago,
I'm here just learning the salt.
And how have you been learning?
Well thank God well, because of this
we live and from this we eat here and
I have done well
thank God, I have already learned many things that I did not know about salt.
What have you learned?
I have learned to collect
to load, I did not know, but here I have learned all that here.
Okay.
And well, what is the difference in this job
to another job that you have done?
The difference may be that this job is heavy for me.
Yes, heavy.
I had never experienced salt, but I experienced it and
from here
you live from this here, you live from the salt.
Here, well, you don't want the rain to fall
because if it rains,
we won’t have a job, you understand?
So we need the weather to be, just as it is now,
that it´s breezy, that it’s clear, that the sun shines,
the more sun hits and breeze, the better for us.
Because since we live from this, then
We need the sun to shine, the breeze to run.
Most people want it to rain, right?
If most people want it to rain, but then
if it rains we don't have resources to eat,
because if we don't take out the salt
We don't have anything to eat either.
And how is it done?
How does salt get damaged by rain?
Well... as it is,
if it’s in a part that is dry above, very little is washed,
but if it is inside the pond, since the pond has no outlet, it is washed,
it dissolves, it melts in a wash, it melts away.
If if rains too hard, I mean, if it doesn’t rain that much
it is not consumed.
Have you seen that there is a spirituality here as well?
related to salt or elements or not?
No.
And well, this here by the sea too
come the salt, right?
Yes of course, because that's where they get the water from,
over there there is a little canal, that over there is
a canal, that water falls there,
from there it takes a week or about fifteen days.
To end up here.
It comes here and from here the salt goes,
it crystallizes here in the ponds
with the sun and the breeze. when it's ready
one comes, puts the shovel in it and if it is thick it is already good to pick it up.
One comes to pick up with the owner of
the pond, the water is removed again,
it passes through the pond and collects the salt.
And that, but it comes from..., why is it done like that?
It's done like this to make it dry, do you understand?
So that it drains the water.
So one fixes it here and puts it like this?
Yes of course, because one does it like that
one piles it up and the higher it is
The lower goes the water, do you understand?
Ah okay I didn't know why it was like that
How long does it last like this, what would be ideal?
Well, yes, the pond, for example, is exploited
today you can plow tomorrow, you have all day
to cover, tomorrow you can load it
like we´re doing right now
Load it onto the cars and they take it away.
So then it's put in the bag?
In the bag and the car comes and we ship the cars.
What is your daily earnings through salt work?
Well here depending on the cars.
If, for example, if we fill only one car
among ten people,
Let's put $14,000 or $10,000 among us together,
if the salt is from us, that we export it,
Well, that’s around $30,000
to each one, daily,
If we have more salt and two cars arrive, three cars,
we have $60,000, $80,000 left, depending on the cars,
because here if a car doesn't arrive there isn't either,
there is no production of anything.
Who are the ones from the cars?
Well, the owners of the ponds command the cars,
They say “go to that part, that there is a car over there”
and one loads it.
because one here has the salt,
but if they don't arrive we don't have either
nothing.
What knowledge do you have of salt, what is it used for?
Well, salt is used for many things, for livestock, for eating,
for many things that …
salt is very important
because if it wasn’t for the salt you couldn’t,
You can't make some rice, you can't do something because salt is irreplaceable.
Basis of life?
Yes, a base that... for example you,
with sugar, if you’re going to make some juice
You can put some cane sugar or something, but you can’t do that with salt,
You can't season rice, you can't add brown sugar,
you can't put anything on it.
So this is a point
which is important to us here in Manaure.
I'm not from here, but it's important
because this is where I get the food from
Daily, every day
From 4 in the morning sometimes 3,
depending on the cars,
if they arrive early at 5 in the morning or arrive at 3,
at that time you have to stop
to pack the salt
and until ten?
Until ten in the morning and sometimes they take until eleven,
sometimes even until noon,
because they come and go from here to
Uribia,
So it takes until that, that they come here.
Does it also have to do with the sun,
that is very, very strong?
Yes, it affects us a lot
when it’s around this time, eleven o'clock
and a car parks, sometimes you even vomit,
Or faint because of the very strong sun.
But you know, you do that for…
because one must do it, because
the food comes from there.