Can you tell us a bit about how
The plants work when someone is sick. How
do you identify them?
I have heard, for example, that plants are known
through dreams
Also because they are in our environment
Can you talk about that now? Yes of course.
Our female elders know about plants through sleep
These are plants that our father Juya gives us (rain)
They dream of the plant, he meets them and they become their
recommended medicines
This is how they learned about the plants, our traditional medicines.
Plants like kinouta, wuinpiraicha, samu'tapaya and malambo.
We also know those that we find on the banks
of the stream, we know those as well
That's what the old women told me
That's what I can tell you for now
I also want to tell you that I am very happy
for seeing my fabrics, thank you my grandson who records me
This shows what we are for years
Do you remember when we met last time, I
I am very glad that Neko is dedicating to this
I am a Christian and I ask God to allow
everything to go well because I know that later
You will help me and that if something happens to me, I know that
he will say it to those who see and hear me.
I was going to be busy today, I was going to a funeral
But I had this commitment to you and I must fulfill it
because I really appreciate what you do
I told myself that what you (are doing) is very good and I know
that later you will remember me
I am very happy and grateful for the threads that
you gave me as a gift because you help me in one way or another
I just hope you don't give me the threads only now,
but also when you are successful
Because that's how I can keep knitting too.
I have been knitting for so many years
Here are some children that I take them to see the yonna
I always take those children
They’ve been with me for several years now and it makes me glad
Here I have a grandson, and I imagine him working like you,
I want him to think of big things
And well, that's what I wanted to tell you today
Well I figured you wanted to know too
That's right, thank God that we're okay
Well and to continue with the theme of plants
Could you tell us which plant you have come to know through
any dream you have had?
A new one you didn't know before
Do not tell us the ones we already know, but one that only you
you met through your dream
Or can you tell us a story about someone
that discovered a plant through the dream
It could be the Yonira who dreamed of a plant that only she knows
oh sure it could be that
Once a lady came up to me at the moment
I was knitting
She told me that she had dreamed of a lady who told her
that I was the only one who could prepare the plant
for her to heal
That I should prepare it for her because I had the same
disease than she had
Since I dreamed of the plant that cured me, I should
prepared it for it to be effective
So I prepared them for her, I took 10 shots of the same plant
In the dream they told her that this was what she should
drink and that I should prepare it
Because I already have the gift of the wisdom of the
healing medicinal plants
Since that plant had cured me and saved my life now
I have the strength of that plant in my hands
The plant I dreamed of to later prescribe it is
that one, they showed me that one over there
The cardon, the yotojoro (heart of the cardon) with the coralline
And also, apart from the cardón
They told me something in the dream that prevented my death
That I take a sira'chon ask what was that?
He told me it was a pui (branch of a plant) that I have it
in there
You can see it there. So I did it and I always took it
They also asked her through a dream
to that person who came to me
Same thing happened with another person, it’s been two
People who were sent by the dream
After a dream revealed it to me first
The others dreamed of the indication that they had to come to me
This is how sleep is connected with plants
ok another question
You know that all plants have a
spiritual connotation right? Yeah.
There are some plants that have their spirits
That's why when preparing them, you have to talk to them,
just like with the bath plants
Some plants, if picked without offering what the spirits ask for, get angry
If it is a female plant, it tells you "why are you giving me
So, you must give me something for using me."
Well, you're the one who knows about that.
yes i see it too
Exactly, plants ask for fabrics, it's like
reward for lending, you can tell them that
Tell them how it works and what should be done
Yes, I know plants very well, but one day a person
asked me for some plants and I went to cut them and a branch
It hit me in my eye and I had to lay down 3 days for that
Then I dreamed of a lady who told me “Why did you do that to me"
that was her spirit
She told me that this was the first and last time he did that with her,
to offer her just like that
Ohterwise, she would do the same to me
The person who asked for it told me that it was my fault if it didn't heal
I told him no, because he should have given me thread or a red cloth
to offset the spirit
I speak to him as I give them to him. I tell him help me
with the plant and so nothing happens to me
If a person tells me it's my fault I tell them
no, in fact it affected me
So plants do have a spiritual connotation
Very important and sacred to us
that's how it works
There is also the plant that is used for
baby or children's baths
If I prepare her without giving her anything before, she will
manifest your spirit too
That is the spirit of the plant wi'toi (peppermint)
Those who ask me for baths know that they must
bring me thread for the plant
I have had dreams where they ask me to take the
plant to certain children
Her spirit commands me and asks me for the threads for her
to make up for it
But if a person asks me without giving anything in return
I do not accept it because I am already warned by the plant
Instead, people who know, bring me something
like threads or money
The plants are satisfied with that, as well as me.
with my fabric, or threads or money
This is what I can tell you for now about it.
Well, to continue with the topic there is something
That I have heard, that the plants are not
available everywhere
Where do the plants come from to get here?
for example, I have heard that the plant for babies is
on the top of the mountains
And only those sent by the dream find them there because
If someone else goes, they won't find it. Yeah true
But if that plant is for that person
appears to her
If that plant wants to fall into the hands of a person
it just appears
And it connects with that person
Can you tell us about the other plants?
Because we know that some come from plants,
While others do not, such as kasuou (white bun)
The kasushi? Yes, that same one is not made from a plant, right?
No, that is not the product of the rain
That one in the shape of a bun and it comes from a stone that comes out
in the north zone
Can you talk about it, that some of them come from plants
And others come from stones or mud such as kasushi
Yes, it is true, they are not a product of the rain
There is the red bija, uslisha is also formed in stones
Yes, can you tell us about those medicines?
that come from plants and others from mountains
Well, kasushi doesn't come from a plant as such.
but from a mountain
They are medicines for the ladies just like the ulisha
And they are not fruits or leaves of plants
The ladies drink them and they come out of more mountains
in great masses
The ulisha and the kasuchi are from the mountains in the north
And why don't you tell them (about)the plant that is for the
crying children
Yes, of course, there is a plant that if it doesn't rain, I have to
travel miles to find her
If nobody grows them, they are hard to find and
many people desperately search for it
And the plant called jirupu?
This plant only grows in the Perijá mountain range (between
north of Santander - Colombia and Zulia state-Venezuela)