Well, I have been asking you a lot about the Wayúu people,
but you personally
in what ways do you interact
with nature, that is, with humans
or is there a river or a tree down there that you connect with?
Well this city is called “Río de la Hacha” (Ax River)
and this is the river, in wayuunaiki it is said suchi'i,
It is the most important river in La Guajira,
perhaps the only one in the Wayúu territory,
which has many streams that dry up in summer,
but this is the most important river of the Wayuú.
and Ríohacha for the Wayúu is called Suchima,
This is a serpent river, a path river.
It is linked to the stories of the Wayuú
and on the way to the interior of the continent.
It has the story of a snake
that marks its course in each rainy season.
That snake is called jerakanauwa
and many Wayúu settlements are along this river.
From the middle course of Distracción in the south of La Güajira
to the mouth here in Riohacha, where it forms
a Delta with the sea and where there is a lot of bird life
pelicans, cormorants and formerly alligators.
And it is a river of many tales for the Wayuú.
Also, a kind of living being
that generates a way of life, the way of life of the river
and that has a forest that gives fruits
and that also gives food,
fish and other types of food.
Therefore,
this river is key in giving its name to this city
which is Riohacha.
It has been its story
over time and this river originates in the Sierra Nevada,
where there are
the Kogis indigenous people and the Wiwas other indigenous peoples,
who also have many stories about the river.
So, in some way these rivers are a path and are memory,
memory of all the people who live along it.
Shocking and the river too
is used as a mode of transportation, I guess.
Well, he is navigable only in the lower part,
only in this lower area, but
Only canoes were used to get from one shore to the other.
In Wayúu Riohacha is called suchimalü, suchima
which was like a river that goes into the earth.
That's good.
And then, talking about this river
and the stories he has as a being
Living , can you tell me a little more about that?
What is the river like?
in relation to the people there,
of the Wayuú?
The river generates games, games for children,
the Alligator game.
There is a game called Trapiche, which
It's like spinning around a river tree,
water games in which they
they raise the water with their foot, among the children
They have a game called sombreros (hats),
which is like touching and hiding in the water.
They have many games
and they are spaces where shaman women
collect plants for healing,
where women go to wash clothes from the river,
where young Wayuú couples fall in love,
also on the river bank.
Generates a catch at certain times of the year
and generates a great relationship with the river's own forest.
He changes,
from stones and almost transparent up there,
until it gradually descends to the Caribbean.
It is about 250 kilometers long,
but it is a river that gives meaning
to the territory in La Guajira, orders the territory.
That is why it is so important.
And when it reaches Riohacha it forms a delta,
This is one of the arms, but there are three more
in that direction, where there is a lot of life.
crabs, oysters,
there were alligators before and anyway,
structures the territory.
Very important
then for entertainment, for experience.
for humans and…
Of course
And the road, he was called a river road because following
the course of it, you reach the throat
between the Sierra Nevada
and the Serranía del Perijá,
as inside what is now Colombia.
This is the way, follow the river.
Union.
And you as a child,
did you grow up here in Riohacha?
Yes, between Riohacha and Carrizal is my original land,
but I studied here
and therefore the river was very important.
I saw the last alligator in the river killed when I
I was like, seven years old, everyone ran away.
And here, in this place, here where we are, 20 meters away,
They hung that alligator.
They hung it?
Yes, that's how they showed it, it had a salmon-colored stomach.
and it was big, perhaps it was the last alligator that was in the river.
Why did they kill him?
We don't know, because it's full of alligators.
And do you remember the last alligator?
The very last.
Wow, that’s a story!
Yeah
and the river
as a living being, how does he express himself?
On the riverbed,
in every rainy season
he can change his path,
but at the same time he has a hierarchy.
There are the small streams that feed it,
the streams are
They are like other arms of the river and the river has a bottom
and the Wayúu know and organize it by bottoms,
where the bottom is sand,
where the bottom is stone,
where the bottom is tree roots, where
The bottom is ravines and where the bottom is mud.
This is how the Wayúu categorize the course of the river,
because of the type of bottom it has below,
if it is sand, mud, stone, root.
And does it have different characteristics?
Different in each place.
And does it also have any kind of souls, like you’re saying,
at different times?
Yes, many myths talk about him, they talk about snakes
that follow him, of a bull that lives within him.
They call that snake doroy in some places, in others
they call him jerakanawa,
and the songs and stories are given across the river.
many songs,
many stories that have to do
with the river as a space.
And that tells me a little about
What is the significance of music and dance among the Wayuú?
Music is something that was given to us.
Music is something that more than a human invention,
It is a legacy of non-humans.
From the turtle, then the drum, the curlew played it.
The trees that were musicians give us flutes,
the wood from which they are built
the musical instruments.
Music
occurs in sociability,
When dancing, dances, but it can also be given for grazing.
The drum speaks to the Wayúu, it lifts their spirits
and they listen to it for a horse race,
mark the cattle, for a party,
for a dance for a girl's release from confinement.
There are many forms of the drum, but the drum speaks
and every drum performer
has a characteristic sound that makes it identifiable
differently from others.
It serves to make a woman fall in love,
the drum, which was previously the turtle
terrestrial, was the first executor of that.
The birds left us rhetoric
and harmony in speech,
that sounds like music too,
That is the legacy of birds.
The palabreros are descendants of birds, the good ones
palavers because persuasive speech
It must be a seductive song to change behavior
of human beings,
that's the role.
So, music and words are very linked,
but there is also harvest festival music,
games,
like the kaulayawa,
which are dances and harvest games,
so the Sawawa, the Maashi, the Uotoroyoi.
the Taliraai which is a vocal bow,
the Kasha or drum, the maraca that the Wayúu woman plays,
the shaman, allows her to ascend
towards the spirits
where they are located and find the assistance.
Then the music helps the shaman to heal and raise
to seek auxiliary spirits for connection.
That's it
a very important role.
Definitely.
And something we haven't talked about yet is dance.
and dancing, what does it have to do with it?
dancing with the Wayúu people?
The Wayúu have
at least two dances that are very important.
The Kaa'ulayawaa that is on the verge of extinction,
that lasted days and days during the youth’s harvests,
which is more numerous and has games.
And the Yonna, is a ritual dance that is played
with the drum when a dream occurs,
Or to celebrate the end of confinement for a girl
who is already a woman, with a prescription from a female shaman or
a shaman man. It is a ritual dance that mimes
of insects,
a mimesis of birds, for example,
and that the Wayúu man and women
perform during festive times.
Her name is Yonna.
Is that what we saw on Friday?
On Friday they saw more of a Kaa'ulayawaa.
I like how you started talking about the river.
But I had also asked you about how
maybe it's the river.
Is there a non-human person that you have
a strong connection with, or a place?
A place, yes.
There is a place called Pajara Turtles
in Carrizal,
where in the desert there are some rocks.
Those rocks were the cattle,
They are turtles that came out of the sea
and they became cattle.
The Wayuú took cattle from the sea.
They were turtles that transformed into cows,
certain fish in goats and sheep,
and that is why the Wayúu have cattle.
The origin of cattle for the Wayúu is there.
One day
that the Wayúu took over the cattle,
some turtles did not make it to the Sea
and the sun rose and turned them into rocks.
and in the distance
It looks like cattle trying to return to the sea,
it's a mirage
In the desert, it looks like water and the rocks look like cattle.
That place is called the Pajara turtles,
but there are many other places, the Aalasü stone,
where are the emblems
of all the members of each clan in La Guajira,
It is a key place in Wayúu mythology.
This wososopu, there is Wolunka
the chair where she sang, the woman with the vagina dentata.
The Wayúu world is full of mythological places,
all with a very strong and imposing presence that
When you arrive you feel in a solemn place,
in a place that condenses time and memory.
Those are places
who have a
narrative structure and that tell us about the
history.
It always feels calm, this is so nice
here
the river.
Sadly it’s a bit dirty
it could be cleaner.
Yes, to respect the river more,
but the city is like that.
How do you see that?
That clash between modernity
and the Wayúu people,
That betrayal, how do you see it
Interviewer] in the future? How are we doing?
I think that the Wayúu have known
respond to many changes since the 15th century,
when they encountered Europeans.
In the XVI, XVII,
They acquired the cattle, the firearms,
The horse,
came into conflictive or harmonious contact,
sometimes with Europeans, with Africans,
and they have given an answer over time
to survive.
Every era,
Every century, every decade, brings challenges to the Wayuú.
Now they have others that are typical of this era.
So far they have been able to respond to that,
sometimes paying a very high cost in human lives,
in poverty, in loss of autonomy.
I trust that the Wayúu will remain over time.
There is a more complex universe
than that of their elders.
Yes, well,
tell me again.
What river is this?
Ranchería River.This river is called Ranchería River,
It is the most important river in La Güajira.
and that's why
is it called Riohacha?
Yes, Riohacha is due to this river.
Ok.
Well,
Can you tell me a little about,
an intimate relationship of
yours with that place or with that river or the sea or the wind
here?
Yeah.
Well, our childhood passed here.
There in
That’s the school and the river and the sea,
that at that time when I was a child,
There only was had indigenous canoes.
It's what you saw from the windows
wayúu fishermen crossing the sea
with small engines, engines
very simple, very simple or sailing.
And well,
this river
marks the life of the city just like the Caribbean.
The sea is very important
in the Wayúu world.
Apalanchi means one who lives by the sea.
But Apalaanchi that is also used,
It means the one who has his heart turned towards the sea,
like the Wayúu fishermen, whose world
is the sea and whose territory is the sea
and its relationship is with marine beings, turtles, groupers,
sharks, barracudas,
clams, oysters, shrimp.
All that series of beings,
each of whom have a different personality.
When the Wayuú
Find fish cardumen that are marching,
The Wayuú call it veloriantes (mourners),
because they march together,
Just as the human wayúu go to funerals
In multitude, they too march across the sea,
in that multitude as well.
And there are fixed fish that have houses,
Fish such as the
grouper who live in
reefs, near corals, in stony areas
and there are other fish that are walkers that do not have houses,
They are wanderers of the sea. One of those fish is the shark
that wanders through the sea.
But others, like horse mackerel, also roam the sea.
There are others like locusts, like certain
scorpion fish that live in areas
fixed, which are called beings with a house in the sea,
that they have a place to live.
That is.
Everything has a similar name.
They are metaphors, a social metaphor.
That's right, that's right. And
is there something between the water
fresh and salt water?
The estuary.
The estuary that takes place
in a river mouth, in the estuary, in the Ranchería delta,
where there’s fresh water and salty water,
there are coastal lagoons and there are a series of beings.
They find shrimp in those lagoons,
certain fish like the lebranche,
The Liza, which are costume fish and the Wayúu know it
and they collect it and have lived for centuries
Out of those resources, of their knowledge of the periods
in which they arise, in which they are abundant and so
They’re part of
their economic calendar, of their social life.
And this wind is so strong, right?
This wind is northeast.
this wind
He is a loving father who softens the temperature of the water.
It's called Jepírachi,
It's a wind
northeast trade and always comes in that direction.
It is the predominant wind of the Wayuú
and it is a wind
which has a different character from other winds.
The Wayuú distinguish the wind from the north,
to this northeast wind,
to a false wind
what passes for this wind
to deceive the fishermen.
Jo'utai a wind that comes from the east and brings hunger,
Drought, is an evil wind. Aruleeshi is another wind,
There is the road’s wind from and there are other winds.
Every wind has a character,
a temperament and a relationship with the Wayuú, and the winds
They have antagonisms between them, they can fight,
They can have friendly relations,
They are people who have paths
and that's what companies don't understand.
Like, what is the path of the winds
and what is the character of the winds.
And here you can see the wind, the character,
you can see how he is talking.
Yes, Yes. Well,
Father of the Wayúu fishermen, the father is this wind.
Jepirachi, the father.
And is there anything else you would like to share?
Well, no. It was that.
I think that
what we have talked about about the sea, the wind, the river.
Great.
Well.
One more thing.
Of all those relationships,
Is there some spirituality too, with
or is it like involved in everything?
Is involved
in each thing, in an ontological relationship with each thing,
wayúu rituals
many of them have to do
with rituals of passage, of girls, from girls to women.
Others are rituals of sprinkling, impregnation
of fishing nets.
Others have to do with human contamination.
that must be decontaminated,
like a murderer, for example, or who has touched
the bones of humans in a burial,
then you can't eat with your hands for a few hours,
can not sleep,
He cannot do jobs that require effort.
There are many Wayúu protection rituals
that have to do with danger, warning signs,
signs of risk or that there may be a war
or simply the warning of a dream.
These rituals are very familiar among the Wayuú
and they have relative discretion.
Great, great.
One more question
If you had a message for everyone, what would it be?
Wow, I think that
There has to be a very big dialogue
in humanity between peoples and
human societies.
I believe that far from seeing many indigenous peoples
as societies
that are behind,
you must think about how sophisticated and
complex thinking of ontology,
from their way of understanding the person,
the notion of person and the relationship with time as well.
I believe that there is always a dialogue between ontologies
It will be very beneficial for this country.