What I wanted to say about the land
Mma in the case of the Wayú,
is that without a doubt she is
the mother of living beings,
of some of them, those who are over it,
because there are other beings like the stars.
and other beings
that are not from her, the sea itself
It's not her, it's a sister.
In the Wayú conception,
she has a capacity of transformation
of beings, because the Earth is mysterious
and when she is mysterious, we do not know her will
to transform or to change, transform
what’s on it.
And humans are part of that,
but also the animals, the plants.
So the Wayuú have that notion
of the mysteriousness of the earth.
Sometimes it's reckless,
sometimes it's reckless,
curious, confused, curious
and unpredictable, and
There are times when
faints like a woman, lifeless,
In the summer, in the drought, the earth faints.
Then Lluvia (rain), which is a
being masculine, hyper masculine,
appears and it rains.
that rain
Wakes her up from her fainting
And she explodes all her vitality.
The trees shed leaves, flowers, fruits.
Animals reproduce
humans also
reproduce and their
living conditions are greater,
They are better because today
everything is abundant.
So there
we have to see the earth, separating it
a bit of the stereotype that has been created
sometimes from environmentalist sectors,
sometimes in indigenous peoples themselves
who have also idealized that and
something starts forming
something we have called global neo-shamanism,
which is sometimes an idealization
of indigenous peoples and sometimes
we erase borders, as if all indigenous
people think the same and they do not think the same.
Only here, in La Guajira, a few
kilometers, there are the iwa, the Kogi.
and the wayuú
They are here at a few kilometers from them.
They both have completely different cosmologies.
And within the Wayú themselves there are also,
Is it different or more or less?
They share it, only there are geo-environmental nuances,
For example,
the stories among the peoples of the sea
They emphasize marine elements,
for the sea, the
fisherman,
pastors tend to have that,
but it is the same, that is, they have elements.
What happens there is a beautiful concept,
who was attributed by
an American psychologist,
They are called dogmatic neighborhoods.
It means that the knowledge
is not universal, it is distributed in neighborhoods.
The same myth can have its variation if it is
collected
inside the territory
that if you pick it up on the seashore, where the fishermen
are going to add
a very marine environment,
and that allows us to see
how these narratives have their variations.
That kind of things.
So for me it is key
then put as emphasis
that, that, first,
indigenous peoples have cosmologies
differentiated.
Some peoples have cosmogonies
and others have cosmologies
and the difference is key.
Those who are interested in
the origin of the universe,
in the creation stories of the universe,
They one type of people.
The Greeks were very interested
in cosmogonies.
The Theogony of Sidon is the story of the gods
and how the world was formed
and makes a genealogy of the gods.
In the Wayuú world
is more cosmological, they are more curious
About the transformation of the universe,
for the modeling of the universe than for its creation.
Yes, there are creation narratives.
There may be, but it is not an oral set.
When one examines hundreds of myths,
one begins to find that the emphasis and everything is
in the transformative.
In fact, they have notions of transformative times
and they are very interested if their narratives
are about how the universe transforms.
That is the big concern.
So the explanation
that they give to the world, including the Earth,
is that
the world has two elements
the physical element, which is the appearance of beings,
morphology.
That banana that is there, for example, he
has an appearance
that we are seeing, but they have an interior element,
an interiority
that lives within physicality,
which is the capacity
the ability to see the universe, to have
a point of view on the universe
and to act in the universe.
Much of Western thought,
which is also derived from the Greeks,
sees some beings as a backdrop.
Like... like Aristotle said,
He considered plants to be the least
who lack intellect
and emotions,
there are humans,
then the animals, in the Wayuú world it is the other way around.
Plants are naturally wise beings
They
They are the wise ones and then the animals and
then the humans.
That they are the dumbest in the universe.
Why are plants wiser? They are wiser
because they were humans in the past
that were transformed.
Everyone was human.
The entire universe was human.
The stars, the winds,
the animals, everything was human.
And suddenly, by Mma,
the Earth, which is mysterious,
because he fought with Palaa,
because there were floods from
that Palaa, the sea, invaded the Earth
his sister, they fight.
Because there are beings that transform.
When someone breaks a rule,
the very violent like a jaguar,
a human was turned into a jaguar for his desire
for violence,
the war, the blood. The crows,
the carrion birds that were
Wayuú shepherds who liked meat,
They ate the entire flock,
then they ate any dead animal
that they found,
They were uncontrollable
their obsession with meat were transformed
in the buzzards, in the crows that we see today
who eat rotten meat.
The snake, the rabbit, because it was very sad,
He was mischievous and they transformed him. Anyway,
then all those stories of the Wayuú
They show us the transformation,
but from the transformation we move to the current world.
The world as we see it today,
then the plants
When they transformed from being humans,
that their arms turned into leaves,
their legs in stems and in roots,
They stayed in the place where they were assigned.
They are peaceful,
They don't attack anyone, they don't mess with anyone.
This doesn't happen to animals or humans.
So, that desire for pacifism,
that ability to stay in the place that suits you
was assigned,
Well, in these cosmological notions
the world has an order,
Even the rain has an order.
The rain must water in an way
and the intensity of its fall
must be gradual,
and then all that is an order.
For this reason they are considered the wisest beings
that is in nature.
And when the Wayú fight for land,
displaced persons, for example, violence,
the Wayuú tell him
you have to be like the plants
that they do not dispute the lands with anyone.
They stayed in the place they told them,
this is your place and from there
They live and
there are.
But the plant also preserves
a residual humanity that dwells within her.
That past, not that past
but that transhistorical time,
because it is not a notion of the past,
present and future
as in the West,
that linear vision,
It is a vision of discontinuous time
and other complex shocks of time,
which is not cyclical time.
No, that's linear time that goes around,
It's the same linear time, but it goes around.
These are discontinuous times,
times that may be ahead,
times that can be parallel
with everyday time
and times that are referential, that tell us
we must refer to the order
of this time
that is there.
So with the dream,
the ritual, the landscape,
that time is accessible to the current time,
for the stories, for the history, for the visual.
So every tree, every plant has that
and the animals too.
In fact, it is believed that they had knowledge,
They practiced their trade.
The spider wove and taught humans
to knit, to women.
The jaguar knew how to wage war,
we know the war for them.
Corn was a farmer, just like the bean,
We learn agriculture from them.
Music came to us from animals or trees,
like the flute from which we get the wood.
In short, jobs and human institutions
They are a legacy,
a legacy, from other living beings,
most of which are not human,
They are not human.
So,
let's say for
To explain it this way, they are notions of the Wayuú world
that have to do with the role of the Earth
like a being,
a maternal, feminine, large being, who somehow
She is the mother of us all,
but that sometimes arises in a stereotype.
like that being
wise, infallible, pure.
No, she is a being with generous traits,
fertile, gives life, but mysterious and reckless.
May fall into disputes.
When the Wayuú see climate change
and when the Wayuú talk about coastal erosion
and all this warming, they see it as wars,
tensions between Palaa and Mma, the Earth.
They keep those tensions and
those tensions that are in time.
It’s not like it just happened and the collapse comes,
The world is going to end for the first time.
No, they say, that's old,
we know that they have tensions
and that there may be times when
Palaa invades
and they show us the snails, the shells
that are inside the Earth and the Sea is far away
and says look, this is proof that Mma,
that the sea had invaded the land
so long ago.
Yeah.
So, well, that's how to introduce
what we can talk about,
to give you a vision.
Yes.
Original of all this town
Well,
many of the things you have said,
that's true.
and I have been living in Peru,
and I was noticing a lot about people
there, friends that I was making.
they had a different relationship with the Earth.
Clear.
And all the moon, the sun.
A relationship between a human,
a spiritual being and what I wanted to capture
was in
the minds of city people
or Western culture.
It was that basically
we are killing our mother a little
This is how we can fight that
or how can we stop that in a way
is to show intimate relationships with the earth
or with nature, for example,
because as you are saying, many
indigenous, many are not, there is no separation, right?
And then what we did there
and what we want to do
Here they are two different things.
And I was telling them something about that and
is that first of all we want to expose
the territory,
physical things, like the wind, the hills.
Yes, the hills are brutal. They are brutal
Yes, but as a main character
of the story.
So what we are doing is a documentary
from a series of like six places in Colombia.
Now and in each of them
We want to focus first on the territory,
because as you are saying, that territory
has a different relevance for each group
and then we want to show
the territory as it is alive and we are
from what we have read from you and others
is that here it is the wind.
It's like one of the (…)
which is vital and also
speaking as a filmmaker the best
to show because they have an agency, right?
One can see it.
And there are several, in plural,
It is not just one, it is many winds.
Well, let me see if I can bring you here,
I have something I published
in a Mexican magazine about winds.
Cool.
Wilder Guerra.
Yeah,
that's all.
Of course it is in Spanish.
So,
It is called “At the mercy of the winds”.
Talks a little about the relationship between men and
It is also published in
Internet.
I don't know if I read
everything, but yes.
Yes, at the mercy of the winds.
It's about I guess each of the winds
also has their different character.
their mood, each one their temperament.
Some are beneficial, others
They bring hunger, drought, others...
Yes, that will vary.
Yes, yes.
Well, there's so much to talk about, right?
Yeah.
There's a lot
and I love that of the territory, because
the territory is like a book, the territory
speaks, the territory just with its landscape
He's talking, he's saying,
things and...
and the hills,
each hill has a meaning, it is not there
capriciously, it is not part of a promontory.
In fact, the Wayuú share with the Australians,
with the Australian aborigines, the idea that
life is somewhat part of the intention of the place.
A product not just of the land, but
the place, the specific place.
And there are some places that are called, and that are
the holes like the vaginas of the earth
by which a lineage, not all humans,
a specific human lineage came into the world.
It emerged into the world.
These are called territorial roots,
as heads of the territory.
And each Wayuú lineage has one in the
upper Guajira,
They are water holes or water depressions,
through which it came out, emerged from the Earth,
the world.
And that is very important in the
Wayuú territoriality.
The cemeteries
are important
because they are the way to renew
a pact with the territory
through the corpses.
I return the bodies to you
and I express my will to live here
because I'm burying my relatives here,
I come to this place, marks the world.
Yeah, that's a very, very key thing between that
world of the Samarians. There's a
poem, there is a beautiful poem.
Let me see if I can find it for you, because sometimes the literature
illuminates more,
as much as anthropology.
Yes.
The poem. I don't know if you have read Vito Apshana
No
I advise you to read it.
He is a great Wayuú poet.
I'm going to put it here.
I mean, the newcomer.
And he has a poem.
and the newcomers
poetic and
“Ancient newcomers”
I recommend you this poem
Vito Apshana.
Yes, he has one,
some very Wayuú poems
Within the Wayuú ontology and thought,
So one of the themes is that of the Earth.
Well, he has a lot about Earth.
But,
but I like this one a lot.
Yes, Ancient newcomers.
Here it is
I can
I send it to you
Here it is.
And I send it to you.
So that
the people of La Guajira right?
Yes, is here. I already sent you the link.
You can get in there
It's very beautiful.
Yes, yes, very beautiful. His texts.
He is coming here today.
Yes, he comes today, he is in Bogotá, he will come today
and I can give you the
contact to interview you.
One of these days.
And yes, do an interview talking about his poems.
His poems about the Earth are excellent, powerful
From the earth, from a very good, powerful sun,
a message.
That well, one verse sums up everything we have been talking
about
That's what poetry has.
That gift, that strength
Something beyond scientific words
or the words.
Yes, yes, yes, that's right.
And “Ancient newcomers”
Then you get the whole book.
I'm looking for poems by him.
Yes, poetry.
And well, I
I sent you the link and I can give you the contact.
I talk to him today I tell him you are here,
How long will they be there?
We are in La Guajira, surely a
two more weeks
He's going to last nine days here, he's going to be busy,
but I know that
He can take the time to talk to you.
Because it is that he
President is coming tomorrow.
Petro. and is going to
spend a week in La Guajira,
A shaman?
One week.
Oh, a week.
He will rule for a week from here
then all the ministers come.
They are going to be in Alta Guajira,
There are going to be many meetings with the population.
Wayuú.
With the population of the mountains, too.
About the zoo?
That is a good point, there are other points in water,
malnutrition of children, health,
education,
they have other topics.
Water is key, the issue of water is fundamental.
But the theme about the parks too.
They go to work
to see if they reach an agreement.
And how long will you be here too?
I'll be there until Friday.
Until Friday?
Yes because there is a festival in Bogotá, Festival Gabo.
and then I'm going to go to
festival, I have
a conversation there for Bogotá. Yeah.
It would be nice, maybe and we can come again
and make an interview recorded.
Whenever you want, you tell me, let's set the date and here in the
house if you like.
I know, here, here it is very nice.
I think we can do two
one here and one outside, there the Earth itself.
That's where such. Maybe it's not Monday or Tuesday.
If you have time.
And Tuesday can be Tuesday,
because on Monday it may be very.
Still busy, but can. It will be Tuesday.
Let's do Tuesday, then. Of course.
Something before that I wanted to ask him.
One approach of ours is
Who should tell a story how should it be told?
Of course.
And last night or the night before, the day before yesterday
there was talk about how good
Gabo's story,
I don't remember the name of the book
but because it was from a perspective within the Wayuú.
La Cándida Eréndira.
Yes, that one. And so what we're doing is on Wednesday,
We are going to meet with a young Wayuú, his name is
Neko.
Neko is
It is from near Manaure, where there is a ranch.
There we had the contact of a friend and well,
He is a director starting out in cinema and he
He is going to be like our director for this chapter.
Well.
I have a friend, David Hernández.
David Fernández also directs
He has made documentaries about the Wayuús
He’s made videos, he’s made movies
Yes, Wayuú from Venezuela, David Hernández Palmar
No, a group of Wayuú youth has been formed here
in that audiovisual world.
Seeing that there is a lot.
So many, Leiqui Uriana.
The other girl, Polanco, Mile Polanco
in Cabo de la Vela there is a collective.
Of young Wayú, but very good. Yeah.
They have played a very important role and.
And that's fine.
Following that theme,
we wanted to ask you
if you
would make a wayuú documentary,
How would you do it,
Like I don't know what things
would like, how to put, capture,
explain, what would it be like I don't know,
the story as such that I would believe
There is an advantage with the world
Wayuú and it is that in
their cosmology are in the territory.
So when we go to a hill
like the Teta hill,
that hill speaks to us,
He talks to us, he is telling us things.
Every time you focus on an image,
only the image is telling us things
and there are some popular hills,
I would say that there are about three tutelary hills,
the word would be tutelary, which are
at Cabo La Vela,
a hill called Kamachi, the old. Epitsü that’s near Uribia
which is the Teta Hill and in the upper part,
in La Macuira, there is hill Iitujolu, but those hills
they are brothers,
They are hills that guard the territory,
that give order and meaning to the territory.
Now, there are other small hills that are very rich
historically they are in the cape, you can see Bantu, Piirra and,
others are there near that one and there are many mythical places.
So I would focus a lot
in the geographical
Landmarks of the territory,
because each geographical landmark,
Their single image is already a set of stories.
He is speaking to us, as soon as you
focus on it, he is speaking.
And there is even a book that I don't know
if you know,
Small and simple, stories with GPS.
What is called Stories with GPS?
Stories with GPS.
No,
Yes, in fact, we just read it,
I believe because he quotes you a lot in fact.
In that there is
Stories with GPS
Let me see if I send it to you
because it is a trip that I took,
I was the guide,
the Historical Memory Commission,
they wanted to visit La Guajira
and they wanted me to show them that.
Well, here it is. This is the book.
Okay.
This is from the internet, it can be downloaded on the web.
I think maybe if we read this. Yes Yes.
So this,
This, for example, is the hill of Guososopo
Guososopo
It means our lungs,
because this is as if you
you would open a person's lungs, alive,
and they would look like this pink.
A Wayuú who in mythical times
He traveled from the Sierra Nevada,
He traveled all this
and died of thirst
in the desert,
Only his lungs were left, turned into hills.
So this hill is a story and it is a hill,
then like this
each one of those hills has a meaning,
has a story to tell,
so that's why we did it
So, we traveled for three days stopping in each place,
I told the mythical stories,
That is the story of this book.
Yes, yes.
And in there, like this
they are inside there are
So I would focus on that, if you want,
work the territory very visually.
Sometimes they focus on homes and yes,
homes are important,
but there are multiple, thousands of homes.
Instead, these places,
talk to those background places,
the sea too
or a territorial root.
There is a stone, the stone of Aalasü
that is up there,
that stone is mythological,
there are all the family clan emblems,
That stone tells us a lot.
Let's see if I have it here.
If I have it.
It seems that no, I don't have it here,
but I'm going to put it
Ancient newcomers. Is…
so that's my idea.
Now,
There are trees that tell us a lot.
Also.
Because they are stories about trees
and a beautiful, fundamental, very common tree
here is Trujillo, it's called Aipia.
His task was to heal
the fractures of people when they were human,
before it became a
tree, he dedicated himself to healing
and today if you break your leg,
an arm,
They splint it for you with wood from Trupillo,
because that was his job
and it is a tree that the Wayuú leave near their homes.
They generally cut down everything
to have a view of who is arriving.
So.
But the tree they leave is Trupillo
His name is Aipia and he is very wise, he is peaceful.
It has many advantages.
Gives food,
Before it gave nutritious food,
proteins, vegetables.
Nowadays the Wayuú have somewhat lost their consumption of
that was
so important for Wayuú nutrition.
So the trees tell us things,
So if you focus, you are going to film, look.
what do you have back there,
because surely there is a story in the plant,
It is more than a backdrop,
It is a story.
Yes, so that is what I was going to recommend,
That would be my advice. The rest,
Well, the Earth is an excellent starting point,
perhaps the deepest starting point
It is the issue of territory.
I would have coastal areas,
inland areas, of shepherds, the Wayuú economy
It tells us about a relationship with the land.
Wayuú agriculture is beautiful, and I talked about it
that night.
What's the point of all this?
Grazing, fishing, weaving also speak to us,
because the fabric
look at this,
This is a Wayuú fabric,
but this is a fabric of the sea,
This is called like the eye of the fish,
like the eye of the fish.
So I'm going to show it to you here,
rather,
These are Wayuú graphics, canoe graphics.
So,
when filming a documentary
I would say that,
look at this,
They are the Wayuú
hanging fish like leaves
So,
What I mean is that when we see a backpack,
When we see a Wayuú object, it is talking to us,
but sometimes we go over it
like shapes that have no message that’s just a fabric.
This means like the eye of the fish,
like the eye of the fish.
So,
I would also suggest
To do a lot in
in the graphics, in the designs, in the objects.
The artifacts have a meaning and they are
Talking to us
It’s just that we don't know how to read, we don't know how to read,
we would be illiterate in these graphics,
as if we saw
a sign written in
Russian or Hindi or Chinese, one could not read it,
Well, that's what happens with Wayuú graphics.
Yes.
Look at this for example.
That's nice.
From Palabrero.
Yes, Oops, yes.
This is the first bird
who worked as a palabrero
in mythological times.
He created the Wayuú laws, the norms
and then he retired.
But the knowledge they have of the
Wayuú laws belong to a bird.
Utta is called Utta
and can you still see it?
Yes, the bird exists, of course, I have photographed it.
Of course.
It's a big bird, it's tame.
It's not a bird that gets scared, but no, no, no,
I approached him very close.
He has a bird necklace, here,
a black, yellow and black necklace.
They awarded that necklace,
It was given by Mareiwa,
one of the Wayú figures, for having given the laws
he rewarded him.
and have you seen many signs and symbols like that?
Well, this is my clan.
Your clan?
Mine Yes, yes, yes.
That's why it's there.
That's why I
said,
I was saying that,
that,
that the graphics speak to us,
but we passed over it.
So,
a girl said that night,
a girl said,
Out of all the musical instruments that,
This one is,
But they haven't removed this one's beak.
For this to be a musical instrument,
well, it has to be perfect here, closed
and here one takes off his beak
and it is played like this,
but only from the Wayuú fishermen.
Yes, to communicate.
To communicate yes.
That's interesting because I don't know if you saw it but in
Peru there is an indigenous town, it is called Pituquisca
of the Quechua up the mountain, in the Andes.
Have.
And they have, of course, and they bartered with those on the coast.
The Mayans too,
From the Mayans too
a lot, the
Mayans in Mexico and yes,
In Yucatán that entire area touches those snails.
It must have been a very broad horizon.
among the peoples of America.
The snail
Yes, that's right.
Because I saw a drum and I was in Canadá
about 15 days ago
and I had touring up to Winnipeg
throughout that area.
Yeah
I was in Canadá
I was way up north,
The big rapids and all that,
touring indigenous towns and talking
And we had rituals and everything.
And I saw drums, indigenous drums
in Canada.
Similar to the ones here?
Similar, similar, but with only one instrument.
It is played with only one, not two like the Wayuú but one.
And I saw drums of one layer and others like that, and other made
with deer stomach
or bison which are water drums.
Yes, very interesting.
And I was in several ceremonies and everything there in Canada.
So there are a series of instruments
very, very common,
those found, for example,
The Wayuú have these, but they have them as maracas.
They got them
as
a musical instrument,
They have this with bison horn.
And this is,
It is used for the shamanic ceremony,
to go up, find the spirits up there, to heal.
So this sound allows it to rise
and the tobacco that the woman chews
shaman woman,
It goes up and there it finds in the elevation
the spirit that will help her heal.
And then the Canadians have it too,
but they do it with their animals that they have next to them.
Yes of the bison.
Do you have seeds in there?
Seeds.
That's what you were telling me about the clan symbol,
I wanted to know a little more about you,
that is, you are from
My area is Carrizal, up there, Carrizal.
Carrizal, yes, I'm going to show you,
Carrizal is,
the land of my ancestors.
But that's close to the beach
by Cabo de la Vela.
If there is
the cemetery,
That's why I tell you it's so important.
This is located here, perhaps
you saw it here.
Look at the hills, the hill, the Cabo de la Vela,
I tell you that it is a story,
Kamachi married a windy woman,
He manages the things of the sea.
This is the older brother, he is in the Macuira,
Itojolu
This is the brother, another of the younger brothers.
It is towards the Gulf with Venezuela through Uribia,
Epitsü, Cerro de la Teta.
Each being is a story,
This is a relative of mine, relatives
mine, is on a map of the hills.
Look in La Guajira
how the hills form a triangle, they are tutelary,
In the territory you have to understand their position.
This is a place where there is cattle,
Here I want to show you,
They are Wayuú fishermen.
Wayuú fishermen.
This place is mythological in Cabo de la Vela
It's called xxxx,
It is the hospital where they cure the fish.
The fish have an owner, an owner.
She, she, she is the owner and her name is Pulowi.
She is the owner of the animals.
To fish you have to ask for permission.
You have to do a
ritual and all that, because fish are marine cattle
and those are her flocks.
So
when the fishermen hit them with a harpoon
or a hook and a fishmonger, they are cured there.
That place that is on the cabo.
From here,
They are tombs...
and then in the
sea, in the cape, these are the jepira
a mythological place
in the cape, the children there in the cape,
this is there in the cape,
This is Bahia Onda, this is Bahia Onda, a place too, this
It was a tour of all of Guajira.
in the Macuira, the Macuira
Ah, this is a
mythical place, this was,
She was the first Wayuú woman.
One of the first women,
I had a dentated vagina, she
Couldn’t have relations with anyone,
could not be reproduced
and some wayuú twins
they shot them with an arrow
and all her teeth were blown out.
So, that is a very beautiful myth.
It's called Wolunka,
Wolunka the woman with
the toothed vagina.
This is the stone that I tell you,
Aalasü,
There are all the irons, chlamys,
emblems, look at them,
They are there,
Are they there?
Written there, there they are. Yeah.
Oh, yeah. and does
many years?
Many, of course.
It's a thing that in time,
In mythological time no, they do not have a date,
but in mythical time.
Yes Aalasü,
Aalasü, the stone of the marks, that remains
close to Siapana,
near a place called Wuipa,
Wuipa
It's about six hours from here by car.
It is a beautiful place,
but it is a fundamental place for
Wayuú in the world of myth.
All that
route
and I don't know why not here
Did not come out, it should come out quickly my
cemetery because it is there.
Click here, download PDF.
Charging.
We'll see.
This same book in a more organized PDF.
Better.
Look, here you have this photo,
I can send it to you by pdf,
but I don't know if you saw it, you already have it.
We already saw what we just showed ourselves,
but that's the same, but in
Book shape, right?
Book form, sure, but here it is,
Here you must
be the Cemetery,
I don't know why it didn't come out.
This is a mythological place,
This is The Turtles of Pájara.
This is my territory,
where the Wayuú took up cattle,
the cattle for the Wayuú came from the sea,
They were turtles that turned into cows
and fish that turned into goats,
then one night they caught them
and the
they took and
He converted them, and that is why they were able to have the animals.
Here is my cemetery.
look here at the stone from another perspective,
the stone where all the marks are.
Serrania of what?
This is in Aalasü,
this is,
close to la Macuira,
not in the Macuira,
But close. Yes, yes, close.
This is here in Carrizales about an hour
and a half by car, easy to go.
You have been telling me that the hills themselves,
the symbols, the plants, they all have a story, right?
Everything has a meaning.
What would one be like?
How could one capture that in film?
I mean, would it be someone telling the story more than anything?
Yes, it would be good if someone told it with that in the background,
Someone would tell it with that in the background.
Yes, I'm trying to think of how
We can give our own voice.
That's correct
to the thing, right?
That's right, that's right.
Because they talk, because I know what they're talking about,
but it's hard
sometimes show that.
Of course, of course.
The grace is that there is a
history in each of those places.
Cemeteries also speak to us.
I'm sorry not, I don't know why I didn't find it,
the book the poem
From this poem, from Vito Apshana, which was so beautiful, that
It seems to me that that also has a huge power
In fact, I think that would be a very good way to
make the trees, the hills,
They speak in poems.
Yes, it is
a little more abstract but oh well.
Let's see, let's see if I can find it.
Ancient newcorners.
But here look,
for example, this.
I wrote this column
and published it in El Espectador.
Look at it here, here is this part
to explain the relationship of the Wayuú
with its land, with its cemetery,
the place of belonging,
because the Wayuú have a very beautiful notion,
is the place of birth
and there is a place of residence
I live here in Riohacha, but this does not belong to me.
My place of belonging is my cemetery,
that is the place in the world to which
I am assigned, assigned to
that's the place.
Then look at the poem it says,
you were already born, they say
to a wayuú, you were already born
and you were born the son of people,
of the founders of Trocha del Cerro Epitsü,
and you can go
and you may not come back, but you will always be there,
next to the tree Mokoshira
that surrounds your cemetery
and there belongs your shadow and your rest.
Look at the beauty, ok,
can move. When these
wind farms are arriving in La Guajira,
they are wrong,
they talk to the people who are there
and they believe that those who are there are the owners,
and the owners may be far away because
They can live anywhere in the world,
but its territory is there,
that belongs to them, they are assigned there.
The other could be a son,
but children have no right over the land.
Children only have the right
on the land of their mothers.
So a parent can leave them there.
as guardians.
You take care, but you don't decide about it
territory.
I'm leaving, I am the owner of that territory,
then the son who remains there has the right to live,
but not to decide.
So that's a bit of the conflict.
the conflict that is coming,
between the government and….
Of course,
because the companies arrive, oh
I spoke to the person who lives there! Wait a minute that's not
the son’s, nor the grandson’s.
His territory is his mother's, not that one, he
there he is taking care. And that's why there are so many conflicts,
for not understanding this.
For me, the conflict with companies
and with all this topic
on the land, with the mining companies, with the companies
wind, is not understanding
the sense of the territory,
the sense of the trees, the sense of the landscape.
For the Wayuú the landscape speaks, speaks,
is telling a story,
It is not a decorative thing: it is not a postcard
of beautiful photography to promote tourism, no.
The territory is telling you things.
So when you pass, you read the territory.
The territory is intelligible,
has something to tell you,
It has a narrative structure
that's the territory,
something that has a narrative structure
whose pages are the floor.
So these companies come in and say,
here we lie down, we put a bulldozer,
there is no problem,
we set up a tower
and they are tearing out the pages of a territory.
So,
They don't understand why they are thinking about money.
These people want money, they are asking for a lot of money
and they reduce it to a matter of money.
It is not a money issue.
Obviously, money will have some time
to be addressed, but it is not the essential
of the problem,
not it
is.
So see the whole point,
what's up
where there is an ontological disconnection,
For example, for companies
The winds are a mass of hot air,
geophysical events, inanimate,
that occur on earth
and that can generate energy: for the wayuú,
They are beings that have paths,
temperaments
and that they need to cross those paths.
A wind moves,
He does not live in a place: passes through a place.
And those paths are related to dreams,
They are related to something else.
So how to understand the wind of business,
the wind from wind companies
and the wayuú wind
They are two different worlds in the cosmos.
They are different.
To make those logics meet
They are disputes about the universe,
They are not disputes about development,
no, they are disputes about the universe.
So,
How to make them understand this?
Generally the owners of the companies,
Investors are in a hurry
they want to see their money
producing, the Wayuú have time
and they want to talk about this
and understand how this is not going to affect them.
Then there is a disagreement
that, those do not understand
and they don't want to understand.
They don't want it, they see it as a whim, superstition.
It's a backward thought,
we are modernity,
We are the reason and all this.
This is science, they are superstition.
So there, in that disagreement about the
the land, over the territory,
on the landscape, on the wind,
about each tree that you are going to cut down and that was alive,
that's where no, there hasn't been an agreement,
there has not been an agreement.
As practically in theory,
That cannot be resolved
that, I don't know, maybe there isn't one.
Of course, those are points to understand.
We would have to see how they dialogue, how they converse.
It is always good to talk,
You cannot deny dialogue.
You have to think about
the others, understand each other, sit down, talk
and if one can express that
But, let's see how it turns out,
I think that's why the president is coming from. Hopefully
He will achieve it.
I don't know how he will do it.
I think that
literally spending time in the territory
out there in a hammock,
the president there with the mosquitoes,
with the winds here, telling them,
I think that would help a lot.
Yes, it helps, of course, he's coming to stay here for a week, a week.
I was thinking, and I know that
this is not the point,
is that it is an ontological and
cosmology more than anything,
but I was also thinking, so yeah,
I come from that scientific ontology, although yes
I'm very involved in that other thing, but maybe also
the winds, that is,
If one would put a mill or anything and
changes.
I mean, that changes the wind.
If we are in a semi-desert place, right?
Yes it is.
and the winds bring water, they bring humidity
and a single, a small change
maybe it could bring down the entire environment.
So beyond something like that
Of course, the Wayuú already say it
is one thing we don't know.
Why the importance of studies on this,
How does this affect birds?
how it affects bats that it also affects them
the,
the blades of wind energy
How does it affect the eyesight of human beings?
How does it affect the sound they generate?
Because they generate a low frequency sound, I think,
But it has an impact either way.
The electrical conduction lines,
that energy must be released,
that energy can’t be isolated, they have to come out
by electrical conduction lines
which also generate white smog and energy fields.
And we must deforest and make roads
to get those lines out.
And there will be many people passing by in cars.
where before it was quiet
and the Wayuú really like their tranquility.
They go out for a walk every day
and they see a footprint, a shoe and they know who stepped on it.
They know how their children walk, the neighbors,
They know the…
The Wayuú have some flip flops, the waireñas, do you know them?
Wayuú footwear and that Wayuú footwear,
Well, they are specialists in tracking footprints.
That has been his ancient profession.
When a deer or a thing,
and they also track human footprints
and they know if I walk and tilt my foot when walking
to the left, they say ah, there goes so and so,
because he always walks like that and they know him.
But then they are going to lose that territorial control
because many people are going to pass by
strange vehicles, with strange people
who is not indigenous and
your sense of security, well-being,
will also be affected,
So we have to see all of that.
On the other hand,
The Wayuú have needs for health, water,
of productive projects to live their economy.
I don't know what the meeting will be like,
there will be a dialogue,
I imagine it, and we have to see how that dialogue takes place.
Yes, yes,
you know,
It's going to be interesting.
That's how it is.
That makes me happy. The president is coming.
I was living in Popayán
in 2018 and 2019
and there were these big protests
and yes,
was very hard.
Hard and things
I think Duque would just have to go talk and that's it,
but promise, promise and it never came.
and they asked him to come.
and it was just a dialogue.
and Petro came this time
for own will.
He said he wanted to come to work for a week.
Well, let's see what comes of all this,
because the idea
It is seeing what results, what is achieved.
We'll see.
But it is interesting. No?
Are you going to talk to him too?
No, I prefer to keep distance from power.
I prefer to read the news
They called me from El tiempo (Newspaper),
and they called me yesterday from the newspaper
Time and what do you think and then they ask me
Are you a leader?
Are you a defender of human rights?
Are you an indigenous authority? I told them
I am a solitary voice, I do not represent anyone.
To anyone.
What I speak,
I'll say it for myself, I don't even know if my children listen to me.
I told them.
I am not and I do not want to be
leader, nor leader, nor...
It's a lot of responsibility.
One has enough with one's own life
as to lead another's.
There are some who
bring knowledge, there are others who bring leadership.
You have your role.
His role and his role.
Yes, that's the idea.
I wanted to talk to you a little about knowing more,
because well, all that, several of those topics
I think
We are going to talk more on Tuesday, but about that,
from that lineage of
the Wayuú people, of course, are very interesting, what is it about that?
Very interesting,
because the Wayuú kinship system
It is based on the theory of human procreation.
When a man and a woman have sex,
The man contributes with blood,
the vital blood that causes the child,
semen turns to blood.
Then the woman provides the meat,
the body wrap
where the child is born, the womb.
So,
When a person is born, they have two families,
a Oupayu, a father's maternal family
and the apushi which is the mother's maternal family, then,
This is legally important.
If I cause a wound to a Wayuú, I will shoot him,
I don't kill him, the father collects the blood shed,
but if I kill it, as flesh is destroyed,
the body,
then the mother's family is going to come and ask
the great compensation for the destruction of the flesh.
The father can only ask
a small payment of tears.
What he has cried, his pain for his son.
Then the Father is given compensation
for the little tears and He leaves.
And then the big strong negotiation
It's with the mother's family.
So the lands, the territory,
the clan, practically like one's last name
It's the mom's, it's not the dad's,
So a Wayuú will always have an orientation
stronger towards your uterine family
that towards the father's uterine family,
that is, the mother,
because the father is a boss for minor things,
the father is a boss in the home,
food, food, education.
But when a problem is strong,
He is your mother's brother,
It's your uncle who is your real boss.
That's the boss,
because he is the one who must intervene.
If I do something, they look for my uncle, my dad
no, no, because he is almost a stranger.
I mean, it's not from the same group.
On the other hand, the lands that belong to my mother,
where my uncles live,
the defense, the cemetery,
everything is a function of the mother.
So, the Wayuú society is matrilineal,
It is oriented towards that.
The father does have some duties in marriage,
injuries, these things, and he has a role at a minor level,
well, yes, provide the house with food,
everything any father in the world would do.
But when the problem is serious, he is out.
No, it can't be.
He is his brother-in-law, he is his mother's brother,
the one who is the boss of his nephews,
it's stronger,
the uncle nephew father and son relationship.
Really?
Of course, of course.
Interesting.
Yes, a Wayuú has to talk about who
They were your uncles and then,
in fact,
to the uncles, they call the Wayú Ta’laüla
I mean, my old man, my boss.
That's my uncle. That's how it is said.
It is a very close relationship.
And in war always fighting
Uncle’s side.
Even if the father's family
goes to war with the mother's family,
The Wayuú must take their mother's side,
necessarily on that side.
There is a story in a Wayuú song of a war that took place,
They loved their father very much, these Wayuú,
and for some reason the families went to war,
that these are long families,
and the father died in combat
and they asked permission to the enemies
to go cry to their father and they accepted them.
Then they said let's make a truce
so that you can come to cry at your
Dad because he was
their dad and peace came because of that, so it's a story
very cute.
So this must be understood,
Companies do not understand this,
They don't understand this, they don't understand
this form of kinship and they are, and why?
what is this? And your last name? and not.
This is how the network is woven,
wayuú social organization
and that has to do with the land.
The earth is feminine, the earth is feminine,
the rain, the rain that fertilizes
the earth is hyper masculine.
So rain is the most masculine thing there can be,
because it is what fertilizes the earth, the earth is what
what bears, what is fruitful, what is fertile.
The earth is life,
but the masculine is what fertilizes life.
Then look at all that beautiful relationship
that must be understood.
So for them the earth is fixed,
This is a place, but the rain is mobile,
the rain is watered
and fertilizes the earth, the lands in plural,
the lands, because each woman is a land.
Yes, each territory
It has its own history, its own place,
then more than the earth as a unit
that does exist at a mythological level, it is called Mma.
There are also
specific lands or places
to which one is associated
and that are represented in the cemetery housing axis.
This is why cemeteries are so important.
and that's why Vito's poem says
what he said, there is your shadow and you rest.
You can leave and you can not come back,
but there is the tree in your cemetery.
In wayaqui apushi
Yes, apushi.
Yes, apushi is relatives, it is like part,
It's part uterine relative, yes,
but a nest is like the family unit, not the clan.
The clan is called E´iruku and clan means meat.
Not all members of a clan are family.
They are like surnames.
Like someone's last name is Smith.
There are many Smiths in the world, but those who were born in
Cabo de la Vela
They are one and the ones who are in such a place.
So when the land serves as your last name
and you say no,
I am Uriana from xxxxx
a Wayuú place called like that,
that has a cemetery,
a source of water, a territory, a history.
It is then, that one is different, those do act in war.
The others can be recognized, Ah!
We share the clan, but we are not family,
we only have an mythological relationship
and the clan not only of humans.
The clan involves non-humans,
because for example
well, the Uriana ones are from the jaguar and the rabbit,
They are animals that belong to the clan.
Some hills and some trees.
The trees are numerous as is a numerous clan,
The trees that are numerous are from that clan.
So there are humans, animals and plants
and even hills in one of this clans.
Well that, that's what you're talking about,
that everything was human.
Everything was human.
That's where the kinship comes from, that in time,
in the reference time,
Australians have a time called
The Age of Dream
and the Coyoacán of Alaska
They have a time called distant time.
The Wayuú call that time wayuu sumaiwa,
sumaiwa, at one time,
but in the West we tend to confuse that time
with the past, because stories begin like that.
There was a time
and people think it's the past, it's not the past.
They are transhistorical times that go through history.
Native populance
they can have notions of time
where the past is ahead
or a mythical time until
forward, forward time or parallel times.
And how do you do it between everyday time
and that time?
Through dream, ritual and landscape.
That's what makes those time levels
become accessible
at the current time,
that young people can meet those things.
So to understand the person in the world
Wayuú, to understand the territories,
to understand living beings,
everything is explained in time.
So
Yes, a Wayuú, he dies like today,
that Wayuú himself is going to convert
on a tree or a hill or whatever, or…
He first takes a trip through the Milky Way,
a long trip and you arrive at Jepira, another world.
He will arrive there with his cattle,
the one who was killed at his wake,
the souls of sacrificed animals
at the wake, goats, cows,
sheep, accompany him.
He needs those cattle to live there
and wants to maintain the status he had
here, he wants to keep it there.
After a while,
his soul begins to dilute,
begins to lose like life within death
and comes back like rain
to start a life cycle and all this
kind of things.
But, the kinship we have with plants,
with animals, it comes from human traits
and from that mythical time when they were human.
That's why they are cosmic relatives.
Are they all cosmic relatives, are they different
practically what humans today?
If today's humans have an advantage
that were not transformed,
preserve appearance and language
that they had at that time.
Humans are the only untransformed beings.
They transformed into other humans.
Horses are fallen humans, ex-humans,
but we are the only beings
not transformed.
We remain as if in time itself.
That was my doctoral thesis.
If we read a little about that.
Ontology.
is a big thesis.
I wrote it in Canada, among other things.
Really?
It's funny because, well,
our Peru documentary just won
best documentary of a Canadian film festival
and they are going to bring me there
July 14.
¿
Where in?
At xxxx, at the lake
Ont.
I was in Ontario, I was in there,
There I was touring all those territories.
How beautiful the big lakes are there.
There is a lake in xxxx that is bigger than La Guajira
24,0000 thousand kilometers.
We toured it,
well, not everything.
I was with the communities
indigenous. There is an indigenous
geologist, has a Ph.D.
in geology and in general very, very prepared
all the leaders,
but I knew pollution problems from Mercury.
We were in an area called Grassi Narrow.
There, there I was.
I have photos there.
Well there were cold days,
terribly cold.
started to enter
After the heat, I saw dams.
We met, we worked on common problems.
I brought water from the ranchería.
From the River here.
And we watered it there in Lake Ontario
and they had brought water here from Ontario
and we had watered it
here in Riohacha, there in the ranchería.
It's called Exchange
of water.
I love Canada.
Yeah, well, I'm from there, from Ohio.
It's close, there in front.
And we crossed the border and Lake Iris is my lake.
I mean, yes, the government here.
We toured
by boat seeing other lakes
drawings, hieroglyphs that are there in areas.
Look, here I am with an indigenous Canadian
there,
that
It's in a camp.
Very dear, her name is Leona
and this is touring the mountains.
The mountains in Canada.
And we sleep with firewood and it's cold at night.
Look here we go
touring the lake.
What the lake
that the overcrowded
there where they have the pollution problem.
This is in Winnipeg we were seeing the rivers,
the rivers. AND.
All that.
Ah, look, here in monuments then.
Oh, they are a beautiful monument of.
The indigenous people there.
And what organization was that?
That those are the indigenous people you were watching.
Is that so? Yeah.
Let me see.
I'm going to bring it here.
And they say
Oh, more than
that is. Oh,
from there you come out
This was the bank of a river.
On time. On time.
It was about two hours from Winnipeg.
and it arrived
for.
Do something.
They already saw it
the first
years?
Yes, Yes. This was good.
A beautiful tour in the.
Lagos, throughout that area.
Yes. And I loved this.
I took one. Photo.
in a sculpture
which has books by indigenous authors.
It's called Education
is the new horizon.
All these books are by indigenous authors,
those who are there.
And I loved the motto
Education is the new horizon.
Yes it is a good name
Yes it is very
Nice experience in Canada.
Beautiful, beautiful, beautiful, with everyone.
the problems, the
Beautiful things and landscapes
and monuments
to indigenous people, to indigenous women
that are lost, there are also dramas,
the boarding schools, the children who were lost
in church boarding schools,
thousands of children, thousands.
Changed.
For the Wayuú have influenced them,
in the sense that when Covid,
hospitals began to cremate
the bodies of Wayuú women and our bodies
They are sacred, they have to go to the cemetery
because they are going to be cremated and they dressed in red
To deny death, women dressed in
red and they made a march dressed in red.
Well, they took the red of the Wayuú to
also protest for missing women.
Then look how it influenced
one thing influenced others,
trans American?
Yes, yes, yes, that's right.
This is the Winnipeg Human Rights Museum.
Which is beautiful.
Here I am in Winnipeg.
That's the museum.
Yes Yes.
Oh yeah?
Then no?
Well I see. That the idea is there.
The stories are there,
they are on Earth
to make a documentary about the Wayuú land.
It implies all this that we have talked about,
I don't know, seeing her as a non-perfect being.
Not perfect. Mysterious.
And that mystery of the land that the Wayuú say
entails the transformation of all beings
that we inhabit it
and reflects the idea that life
It is a product of the intention of the place.
Yes, life itself
It is that product of intention
of a place where we live.
And his relationship with his sister the sea,
that is angry,
He has a bit of a strong temperament.
and sometimes the two collide
and then she invades this one.
The sea comes in and invades the coast
and she has to take fire to make her retreat
to its shores and place of origin
through fire.
It's the only thing he's afraid of.
I see her, then she comes back,
It withdraws and returns to its shores, where it should be.
All of these are beautiful Wayuú stories.
Yes, very beautiful Wayuú stories.
Well, I think it's like a last
Question
Ready
and I think we should go.
But like that thing about the palabreros
which ones, who are they?
And well.
You don't know my book, The Dispute and the Word?
well, I haven't read it.
Yes, if you want to know about them you should read my book.
The dispute and the word, The law in the Wayuú society,
It was what I first investigated many years ago.
The palabreros are intermediaries
who manage the Wayuú normative system,
They are facilitators like “go between” and that figure
then they move
between a family, every damage
moral, an offense that I do to you
or any physical damage, a wound that I
cause you, all theft
What I do to you must be compensated.
The Wayuú do not believe in prison,
There is no corporal punishment, no, it is payment.
So that's not done directly.
and I don't charge you.
I send a person specialized in that,
in fixing,
to express my complaint
before your family gathered together.
It is not a problem between individuals,
No, it's between families.
The individual is not seen in isolation,
but immersed in a group of relatives.
So my problem is not with him,
It is against the entire group to which he belongs,
his brothers, sisters, uncles, maternal,
but uterine, maternal.
That is why it is so important
the concept of apushi among the Wayuú
and he goes,
He comes and goes, weaves peace between the parties.
That doesn't get solved right away.
That can take days, weeks.
sometimes they set up a meeting,
They come back and reach the agreement and that's it
when they achieve that there is a will to pay for the fault,
then they go in to see how much it is
and that is paid in animals, necklaces.
If it is a gun wound,
I must ask for the murder weapon.
If he was killed, that weapon
It must be delivered to me
first of all,
the weapon is the first thing that is requested
and it is the will of peace, hand over the weapon,
So they rule.
the weapon, it already means that they want peace
because they sent the weapon.
The weapon must be taken out of circulation
of the things of the world
because it hurts and has hurt.
It has something of the soul of the dead,
and the dead man has something of the weapon inside,
there is an exchange of substances,
then the payments are signed.
Some payments have no material meaning,
but of ornament, of aesthetics.
The necklace goes as an ornament, a luxury of payment.
They have the notion of luxury, which is luxury,
what is the decoration,
what is the aesthetic, the compensation
It doesn't have to be enough, it has to be beautiful.
The compensation is a necklace
and the necklace is made with cattle,
necklaces and strange animals like mules
Generally the Wayuú ask
two mules They can ask for 100 cows,
200 goats, 200 goats,
but the two mules are done like this,
because mules are hybrids that cannot be found
easily in the universe.
A horse and a mare or a donkey.
No, sorry,
a horse and a donkey, or a donkey and a mare.
Then the mules decorate the payment.
Two mules is not a large amount,
but since they are rare like necklaces,
They serve to decorate the payment,
So there I can deliver the 200 now
goats.
Or they give me deadlines,
because it's not about ruining the other,
but the other
Has to be prudent in their conduct.
And he tells you, I'm going to pay this this year.
and I will wait for my animals to reproduce
to be able to give you
the other year of the animals that were born this year
that the goats give birth up to three times,
then they deliver, and then the other
He does not want to destroy him nor does he want him to go to prison.
The Wayuú say what good is it to me that my enemy
be imprisoned
If there they are going to give you free food and free time?
I want him free to work
and pay me.
Then they go to jail,
They see it as something barbaric, uncivilized.
They have to say that prison is an uncivilized place.
and says because justice is not revenge,
justice is
reopen social relations
that were broken by someone's act.
Such as a theft.
Or a homicide, an injury, an offense.
So the Wayuú try to restore
like a fabric.
When I have a hole in a fabric and I pick up a needle
and I darn it again
so that the fabric is the same again.
This is Wayuú justice, it is restorative,
It is not punitive, it does not emphasize punishment
the penalty.
No!  emphasizes restoration
of broken social relationships.
The palabrero handles the rhetoric,
has to be persuasive.
Their task is to convince and a conflict is settled
when both win.
No one can feel bad.
If they pay me for a relative's injury,
My prestige remains intact.
I have made myself respected.
If I pay
what a relative did, the other family says,
They know how to pay.
Their young people can make a mistake.
But these people have responsible behavior,
Serious.
They are good people.
If something happens to me later, to a family member of mine
It is said that they are going to pay me because I am used to
pay for the faults.
Then I keep a collective resume,
not of the individual, but of the family.
And that resume
He says if, on the other hand, I don't pay, I don't fix it,
I put myself outside the Wayuú law, there is no police,
There are no judges, there is no problem.
But someone more powerful than me comes, runs over me
and I try to pay and they tell me, whoever doesn't know how to pay
should not charge,
because you humiliated a humble indigenous person
long ago, I was a fisherman perhaps
and you ran over him and did nothing.
Now how do you come to complain?
So I pay to be inside
of the rules of the game of society.
I don't need police, nor magistrate, nor judges
Make me pay this.
I do it voluntarily.
So that?
to be inside
of the rules of the game of a society.
It's more or less the payment.
Very good.
But if you want to know more, read my book.
Yes, yes, of course.
The dispute and the word.
The law in Wayuú society.
Yes, of course.
I do not know if. I have it on hand.
I don't know if I have it here.
Sometimes one doesn't, I don't know,
I have one of those...
is this!
Ah, yes, yes, yes, yes,
yes, that's it.
And these are the palabreros. Here are the pictures.
This old man, this book of my son's
These are the palabreros, look at them
the wayuú palabreros.
That generation that I filmed, most of them have already died.
I photographed it with a friend in 1998.
99, my idol, old Isidro.
Very good
Palabrero, Gómez died two years ago.
Or three years.
This my friend Angel Amaya,
The greatest of all.
Yeah. They are going to release him now.
His years of dead next year in a few days,
and then they are going to take it out.
This was my great friend,
that was my trusted palabrero
because I was Secretary of Indigenous Affairs
and he was my right hand.
I solved the problems with him
through him, we
we met and, we worked.
This was my uncle Guillermo Estrada,
a great palabrero.
This Néstor Polanco lived in Uribia and
another very famous palabrero,
This is the old xxx, a good talker.
This one still lives, he lives.
The only one who lives is called Ismael Parra
He is very old now and taught me many things.
He died Saraucana.
This one did live, this is my cousin.
And he lives.
He is Carlos Curbelo, but he is not a palabrero,
he has been in conflicts.
I put him in because he knows a lot about war.
He died.
King Said Juana.
This is the cane that too.
There is another because there are many varieties.
Not everyone has this.
That bird could be a simple stick with nothing.
This is my friend Ángel.
These are paid collars.
Look it here.
A conflict has two solutions.
Either the war that the staff represents or peace
which represents the necklace.
That is, human beings always face a dispute
between groups, we go for dialogue,
peace or we go down that hard path.
Then look, the photo is very beautiful.
The picture is beautiful and that’s my pal
He was a wise man, he was a wise man.
I talked to him for hours and hours and he told me so many
things and me
He explained stories about him, settling conflicts.
Difficulties, everything he
He lived, how hard it was for him to fix something
and how he finally solved it.
These are the payment collars, he is there.
The palabrero must know the value of the necklaces,
because with this you reach the
agreements, then.
There are necklaces that are made of sea coral.
Or gold corals.
Basically, archaeological accounts.
So
This is her daughter getting ready there on a table.
This is how they arrange themselves when there is going to be a payment, they get
and the necklaces are displayed so that the other party
see them and examine if they are happy,
if you are getting a good necklace,
You can reject some or accept others or all of that.
Or ask for a specific one?
If you don't want such a necklace,
then they look for it and bring it,
and this is what women keep
so when there are wars in the family to be able to pay.
Generally women guard them. Yeah
is that it?
that's the bird
the first palabrero, the one that brings Utta.
innelus ruficollis
It is called in Latin innelus ruficollis .
Yes, and there is another.
Even he has a necklace here on his chest.
Because when he
Mareiwa one of the great Wayuú beings, an instructor,
A mythical figure told him, I want
You to give the humans
the laws to live in society.
He retired to the mountain and brought the laws.
And Mareiwa
liked it and told him
I'm going to reward you with two things, a necklace,
because you did your job very well
and the gift of good humor.
The bird's song sounds like human laughter.
You feel it like
laughing, when he is around it is like a laugh.
And then, because these beings consider that
The best gift for a human being is good humor.
Keep a.
Attitude.
This is a tree
Trupillo?
Let me see. It could be a trick.
Yes, I think so.
A little trick, which is very good.
Each tree is a story among the Wayuú
That's why it's good to know what it is. What tree is it?
And here are interviews that I did with him,
In addition to the analysis that I did as an anthropologist.
Of the whole topic.
I felt that I was facing a generation
of beings that were going to leave
and I interviewed them and made an annex of interviews,
where I asked them and they
They answered.
Well, that's my book about the sea,
I worked with Wayuú fishermen,
the fishing theme,
the animals, the seascape,
because there is a landscape at the bottom of the
Sea and then the Wayuú classify them.
They have their knowledge.
Of the winds, as the winds are.
The Archaeological Museum of Aruba published that to me.