Good.
Well,
first of all, if you could tell us.
If you could
Introduce yourself?
Yeah.
Well, my name is Weilder Guerra Curbelo,
I am an anthropologist from Universidad de Los Andes.
I am a member of the Wayuú people
and I have dedicated part of my academic life to studying
Their history and their society.
Very good.
And
well, first of all, for someone
who knows nothing about Wayuú people,
who are they and where are they located?
They are indigenous people
located at the north of South America, on the peninsula “La Güajira”
shared by Colombia and Venezuela.
They are the largest town in Colombia
and the largest indigenous people in Venezuela.
Their language is Wayuúnaiki and there’s an estimate of
some 800,000 of these individuals in both countries.
Ok. And
well,
and right now where are we?
We are
In Riohacha,
capital of the department La Güajira,
in the Colombian Republic.
Very good.
And
well, for many years you have been
working with the Wayúu and you are Wayúu as well.
Can you tell me a little about your family and your work?
Well, my family is originally from a pearl fishing
region,
near El Cabo de la Vela, which is called Carrizal
and our territory is called Manuyalu'u
which is a territory inhabited by my ancestors
since the end of the 19th century.
Okay.
And the work
that you have done, more than anything you are a teacher, but also
Have you done other things, other professions?
Yes, I have served as a public official
at least on two occasions,
as Secretary of Indigenous Affairs,
as governor in charge of La Güajira,
as director of the Colombian Caribbean Observatory,
what is a research center
and as manager of the Colombian Central Bank
in the “San Andrés” archipelago
and in the La Güajira department.
And
well, as we have been talking
the other day about the Wayuú’s ontology
and nature
of the earth, what relationship does it have?
I mean, we know it's no different,
but explain that to me.
well, the Wayuú have an ontological conception
in which we must first understand the notion of time,
they have a notion of time
in which the substance of all life was humanity,
the stars were human, the wind,
the current hills, the animals,
the plants.
All these beings were human, there were social institutions
and they communicated throughout human language.
There was already kinship, agriculture, weaving, music,
war, all human institutions and practices.
But the world was undifferentiated,
It had only one form, one substance.
Then comes a transformative
time, several events shape the universe
and all beings begin to change.
Many humans become hills,
others become plants, others become animals.
And in general,
The only non-transformed beings are current humans.
This morphological differentiation
allows us to move into the current world.
However, those beings that today have a different form,
a different taxation,
They retain a residual humanity
and a point of view on the universe,
because they were human in the past,
then they are fallen humans or ex-humans.
So they have a voice
or do they have a story to tell?
They have a story to tell,
but they no longer have human language to communicate.
They have a desire to show themselves in the world,
plants through flowering,
of fruiting, of expanding its leaves,
animals to act as such, to behave.
and to them
we owe them the transmission of knowledge,
to plants and humans
weaving, agriculture, war,
justice, rules.
Everything depends on those mythological beings,
that live in the current world, but in the past
They were and continue to be our cosmic relatives.
So can you talk a bit about that relationship that the Wayúu has
with their own
elements
and characters.
How in referential time
called wayúu Sumaiwa (old) or wayuú Jumaiwa (old),
They were humans, they had clans,
Therefore, today they also have clans.
So the jaguar, the cat, the wild pig,
certain birds, certain bees
They have clans because they had them
in the past, therefore they are still related.
These clans not only refer to that time,
but social attributes
like being numerous, being brave, being cunning,
be meek, be hardworking, be united.
All those social attributes
are shared by humans and animals
and it's a way of somehow organizing the world,
but through a metonymic vision of the world,
which is the sharing of social attributes.
We're going to talk more about that in a bit,
but I also wanted
ask about the history of the people, that is
because I know that they were not colonized, they are the
only non-colonized people or nation.
Yes, Wayuú are people that,
They are a maritime people from the Caribbean
That adopted cattle in the 16th century
They transition to pastoralism,
from being hunters,
fishermen, horticulturists, fruit collectors.
This whole set of groups that today we call Wayuú
They adopted cattle as a way of life
and they took horses, donkeys, cows,
goats and sheep and made a transition to pastoralism.
A large part of the population,
a part of that population on the coast
were dedicated to fishing and therefore also
They appropriated navigation techniques, engines, fishing nets
who were from the Western culture and so too
They strengthened their economic activities on the coast,
but they also crossed empires, they went to Jamaica,
They went to the French keys,
Traveled to the Dutch possessions of Aruba,
Curaçao, Bonaire,
throughout the Dutch Caribbean and other Caribbean ports.
This allowed them
cross several empires and have an open mind,
conceive maps of the world, a very extensive geography,
very wide,
and see the world beyond the jurisdiction of
the Spanish monarchy.
That is why they are trans-imperial historical subjects.
When they arrive to the Colombian Republic
These ties were cut
and the wayuú
were trapped in their peninsula, circumscribed
to the jurisdiction of the Republic of Colombia.
Interesting.
And before that, I think I had also read that never
were conquered or colonized.
The Wayuú were not
subjugated,
They always rebelled against any form
Of limitation to their political autonomy.
To give an example, in 1769
They revolted against the Spanish crown on May 2
and in a war that lasted more than four years,
They burned many Spaniards villages,
defeated the Spanish military forces,
They killed missionaries, they destroyed churches
and that is known as the May 69 uprising.
In 1752
they had done
formal agreements
with the Republic of Holland
to protect Dutch trade
In the güajiro ports, they were historical subjects
collectives, capable of protecting their territory.
So, this people have been a people that has
resisted those forms of external domination
Today it has two republics that control its territory
and they divided it, which are Venezuela and Colombia.
And
following that, that is, as
nan
well, can you tell me a little about your justice system?
with the palabrero.
The Wayúu have a justice system
based on rhetoric
and in persuasion and compensation.
Any physical offense, any aggression or any moral affront
that one person causes another, voluntary
or involuntarily, must be compensated.
This compensation is not requested directly,
but through specialists, called Pütchipü
or palabrero, and the compensation
is not delivered to the victim,
but to the relatives of the victim.
This norm is called sukuaipa wayuu, which means
the güajiro way of doing things,
and these elements that are given are cattle,
necklaces, animals, and weapons.
Lately money,
but money was not in the tradition
Where money is involved, it goes like cattle or like a necklace.
Did they use barter a lot?
They exchanged things
but also the money, because the Wayúu first
They exported pearls, they exchanged pearls for weapons,
for food, for fabric, for metal objects,
Brazilwood,
cowhide, cattle with the English, a lot of cattle
divi-divi, and other elements,
all this until the 19th and early 20th centuries.
And you told me that your family
did they start with that pearl collecting?
Is that still going on?
No.
Pearls were very important in life in La Güajira
in the 16th, 17th, 18th, 19th and early 20th centuries,
but the Japanese introduced pearl farming,
with which the pearl dived,
which was already more difficult to obtain, which required
a lot of human effort and not the cultivated one,
fell somehow as an activity
and therefore today the Wayuú do not fish for pearls,
although the pearl banks are
full in La Güajira’s sea.
Interesting,
didn't know that.
Well,
can you talk to me
a bit about dreams and the importance they have
dreams in the Wayúu culture?
Dreams are prescriptive in the Wayúu world.
It's called Lapü,
Lapü is a character, he generates the dream
Himself. He’s so powerful that when cultural heroes,
Wayúu semi-divine figures
like Maleiwa dream, they have to obey the dream.
So dreams are instructions for every living being.
It is not discussed.
The dream can order the sacrifice of animals,
sleep can order confinement
of some people, rituals,
different decisions and you have to obey them.
Dream governs much of Wayúu life,
the dreamlike is fundamental.
One wayúu can ask the other
the next day
When they wake up, “what did you dream of?” instead of “good morning!”
Nice.
And that brings me a bit to the idea of a world
Nazu versus the Ulazu
how the visible and non-visible world.
Yes, it's because the dream
It is a bridge that allows us to communicate,
for example, with corn, with beans, with pumpkin,
with these ex humans
and see them in the dream with their original appearance,
not like today's vegetables,
but like the humans they were in the past.
The dream is revealing,
can announce you
happy or tragic events in the life of a family group.
Interesting.
Well,
can you explain me about.
Well, two things. One,
What has recently happened with the
hydrogen generators? and also
with that topic
linked is obviously the wind,
What is this ontological conflict that is happening there?
La Güajira
is a region located in the north of Colombia that has
many natural resources, coal.
That's why there are very powerful mining companies here,
gas, that's why
Texaco, Chevron, all these companies have been here.
It also has
salt in abundance and that’s why it has been the first producer of
Salt of the country.
And now, a renewable energy bonanza is coming
based on solar luminosity,
but mainly in the wind.
These companies
They are arriving in Colombia
or to La Güajira along with the Government
to make an Energy transition,
But practices can continue to be extractive.
I mean,
They are called “clean energies”,
but in the relationship with the communities
They can rely on behaviors that are the same
to those of the old companies.
So, at this moment there are ontological conflicts
between the Wayúu people and those companies,
Because they don't understand how the Wayúu see the world,
how the Wayúu see the winds: They see them as plural beings,
ambiguous, which can be masculine or feminine,
that have no fixed place, but paths through which they cross,
that are related to well-being,
with certain elements of life
and therefore the vision is not understood
who sees the wind as a business, as an air mass
hot, like inanimate geophysical agents,
of this Wayuú’s vision
who see them as beings with the capacity for agency,
with reflexivity and with a moral code.
And that's why there was a conflict?
And what happened to the recent companies?
What has happened lately is that some companies
who do not know the social organization,
Wayúu territorial rights,
They reached some areas,
they made some quick questions
and then the projects began to be built,
but the underlying conflicts that were there and the
Lack of understanding
with the Wayúu social environment, has led to blockades,
The differences between the Wayúu population and companies.
And one of them,
in Green Power, decided to abandon his project.
Right now,
the president of La Güajira
is here
to rebuild those relationships
and try to generate an agreement
among indigenous peoples
and those renewable energy projects.
And for you, what steps need to be taken?
to reach an agreement like this between the people and the government?
A set of rules, the first thing the government
Has to do is to establish a set of rules that enforce
Indigenous and communities rights.
So companies do not see the Wayúu territory
like a national wasteland, like a land without an owner, it is a
constitutionally protected reservation.
It has 1,070,000 hectares, therefore large.
But the Wayuú
They have notions of territory that must be respected,
They have notions of social organization, of family
and notions of rights and territorial control
and ontological that these companies must know
and understand. When they talk to the Wayuú, when they understand
how this society thinks and what its norms are like,
then there could be an understandable dialogue between the two.
One has a commercial logic,
the others have their own ontological mission.
Bringing that closer is key.
Now, the indigenous people are economic subjects, that is,
They have valid, legitimate expectations and interests.
Therefore, companies see it as Rousseau beings,
like the noble savage who does not aspire for money
nor can he aspire to money
because it contaminates his condition as a noble savage.
It is different from the Wayúu, who crossed Empires
to carry contraband, merchandise, to Holland, to Jamaica.
So that’s ignoring their history as an maritime indigenous people
Yes, of course.
And that's talking about the norms of the Wayúu people,
Maybe a very important one is the matrilineal.
Definitely.
What they must understand
is that in the Wayúu territoriality
lands are inherited from the uterine side,
on the maternal side,
for what the Wayúu call Wapushi, our family,
and therefore sometimes they can be left to children
living in the territory without having the right
to decide. These companies
they reach the territories
and talk to the first person they find,
thinking that because they live there
They are the owners of the territory.
It turns out that it is not like that and it is not usually like that.
Someone can live far away without having
that presence
in the occupation of the land and that belonging.
There have been many disagreements in two
logics of seeing the world, two ways of seeing the universe.
Sure
and that is I think the axis of everything.
Definitely.
And for someone who doesn't know
what is an ontology and what is ontology,
so as a summary
of the Wayúu people or summarized.
Correct.
Well, ontology is the science of
The being in all human lives
and it is a field of philosophy and metaphysics.
But,
Well, anthropology has been very interested
for the ways
in which human societies
give signficance to the universe.
How they classify the stars, the winds,
vegetation, animals, other non-human beings.
And find knowledge and ways
of conceiving time and beings very sophisticated.
Not only taxonomy, categorization principles,
ways of relating to non-humans,
modes of classification and categorization.
So the Wayuú
They are a people who first of all consider
that many non-humans were humans in the past.
Therefore,
They have a residual humanity
that inhabits them and are relatives.
They are not inanimate beings.
A fishing company can see many fish
per metric tons of production, a stock.
The Wayuú see them as relatives,
They don't see it from instrumental mathematics,
but sees them from kinship.
It’s another type of.
Well, science as we know in the West
is a type of
science, a type of knowing a world.
Well, the Wayúu has that, as they say, like complex
and full of important, small, big things.
Exact. The deep difference
the ontological separation
among humanity
and non-humans is very deep in the West.
In these type of communities
as the wayúu is not so deep and they can be
closer to some non-humans than to some humans,
because these non-humans are their relatives
and they were humans in the past and have social attributes
that are shared.
The Wayuú do not see other beings as natural strangers,
but as relatives who in the past were
and the world more than in its creation,
They see it as a modeling and a transformation.
Focus on transformative events
and they believe that the world is subject to modeling,
because Mma, the Earth,
which is the mother of all living beings, is mysterious,
and therefore has the capacity
to transform the beings that inhabit it.
Tell me a little about that, about the transformation, the Mma
and how he was telling me that she is mysterious, but also
is not 100% righteous, because she is also a human.
Yes, Mma (Earth), as in principle she is seen as human in that
referential time,
that referential order of things
She is the sister of Palaa, the Sea.
Then Mma every so often
It has conflicts with the Sea, and the Sea invades it
and then the Earth
and the beings of the Earth
They have to use torches and fire to make her come back
to its limits and its initial shores.
But in that flooding process
there is a transformation of beings.
So life is in a continuous transformation
And those transformative events are very important
for peoples like the Wayúu,
who are very aware of that.
What matters for the Wayúu is not
when an event occurred, but rather that the event occurred.
Out of those events, there are transformations in the landscape
a rock, some drawings, a mirage,
a hill or hills that have distinctive features.
That is why for the Wayúu the territory is an open book,
because it is the stage where the events occur,
the events that shape beings.
Can you tell me about two things, one
a bit more about how land or a territory
it’s a book?
And related to that, what subjects,
which ones
chapters we find in that,
That book?
Many hills, the hills that make up La Güajira,
They were humans who traveled,
They traveled through the güajiro territory,
some stayed in it and became a hill
Due to thirst,
because they got lost, because they found love,
as in the case of Kamaishi,
The case of Episcua, Sosopo, Iitüjo´i.
The monks as well, Walirajau,
that are in the sea, in the gulf with Venezuela,
all the hills have a story,
Pa´ntui in Cabo de la Vela
and that history shapes the territory,
shaping the landscape
As they were frozen footprints of the ancestors.
Therefore, seeing a landscape, seeing a hill, seeing a rock,
is to evoke stories,
stories interconnected with other places that form
that intelligible text of life that is the landscape.
Those movements, those traces of the ancestors.
So, that's why the territory
It is so important for the Wayuú.
Each of these places has a tale.
How it was transformed
why this hill came and found a female wind
and fell in love with her and his cattle went to the sea like Kamaishi
and therefore, it regulates the things of the sea.
As another regulated
agriculture, as another was a shepherd in the past.
All these things explain how the world works.
and they give meaning to the universe.
Can you explain to me or
tell how the most important
hills and shapes
non-human or ex-human
of the territory
and maybe a bit about their...
character or how they were like?
Yes, I can tell the story of Kamaishi
or Epitsu, they are two sister hills, they are three hills.
The older brother was in Macuira, Iitüjo'i.
Once upon a time,
With a very intense summer, he told his brothers
that the land
was not enough for the herd of the three
Then they both left
towards the base of the peninsula to search for land
and then one of them
He reached Cabo de la Vela, near Cabo de la Vela.
Over there,
While he was with his animals, a woman named Jepiraichi passed by.
This woman asked him what he came for.
He told him, I've come to seek land for my herd.
She left
and returned in the evening and brought him fish to eat,
delicious fish to eat, snapper, grouper.
And then he asked her if she lived there.
She told him that she didn’t live here, but she would passed by.
The winds do not live in one place,
the winds pass through the places, they fell in love
and all Kamaishi's herd ended up in the Sea
and they are many of the fish we have today.
The other brother went to where his place is today,
He met a wind woman called Arüleshi
and she asked him what he was doing.
He told her what he was doing
and she returned in the evening with corn,
beans, pumpkin, cassava, food.
And then the two fell in love and this man became
Who, in some way, influences
the food on Earth.
So there it stayed and became a hill
and it is the hill that
we know today. That triad of brother hills,
They are a territorial arrangement,
of economic activities
of the territory written from a referential time.
Interesting.
Well, I
I think at one point,
we want you to maybe give us a little tour of
your books and also the room and
the painting there and can you tell me
which room or house are we in now?
Of course. Well, it’s my house.
This is my house that I am just building,
It's not finished,
but hey, I'm building it just the way I like it
like a enrramada Wayúu open to the winds.
Yes.
Tell me a little about that architecture.
Is it anything like the original?
Yes, it is very original and it is open.
This is a girl in the
confinement, to the Wayúu girls,
When they experience their first menstruation they lock them up
and she spends months there, learning how to knit,
who is her family, learning how to think, her grandmother, her mother, her aunts,
They are going to teach it.
And that's what she's doing there. She’s in limbo
She is neither a girl nor a woman, she is like a chrysalis.
When she comes out, she comes out as a woman.
Can you tell me a
bit of this cane
and
what is it?
And also, can you also explain to me about the graph down there?
This cane is a wararat or Wayúu palabrero cane,
It is the one he uses to carry the word,
It is a support point for the body, a support point for memory.
It serves to point out someone in a process,
You can't point your finger at it.
Used to draw in the sand
and to retain memory of the arguments
That is he giving to the other party.
This is the ground connection point,
The Earth can convey through the message he must give.
This is the weapon of the palabrero, because with this
He defends himself against the dogs that bark on the roads.
So these are the roles of the cane.
This bird is called Utta,
He was the first palabrero that existed in mythological times
and he was the one who gave it to humans
the principles of life, of the law on Earth,
of the standards.
And then the palabreros, who are they?
What do they do?
What is their role?
The role of palabreros is to be intermediaries,
rhetoric specialists who know the Wayúu laws
and mediate family disputes.
Their role is to bring them to a peaceful settlement
since they obtain compensation.
It is the persuasive rhetoric that leads to peace.
The cane is the vehicle of the word.
It is known as this.
That is the role and meaning that these canes have.
And the,
That system is not criminal, right?
Is it a restorative system?
It is a non-punitive restorative system,
because it does not seek to punish anyone, it seeks to compensate
the fault committed
through material
and aesthetic elements
like cattle, collars, even hand over the firearm
that has caused a death, for example.
In order to seek restoration
of family relationships
between families that are in dispute,
not between two individuals, between sets
relatives of those two individuals.
And can you show me the symbol here?
Here we have at the base of the cane,
In this particular cane, there are many types of canes
and they can be different, even made of different woods.
The clan, the clan emblem of my, of my Uriana clan
Yes, that is the iron or clan emblem
Do you consider yourself a palabrero?
No. Even though I have solved 223
conflicts, throughout that,
when I was Secretary of indigenous affairs,
but I don't consider it because the word palabrero
It means pütchipü, a person whose job is to speak.
But there are words in a wayúnaiki like pütcheje'chi and
is that sometimes settle disputes or Pütchejana,
which is the messenger.
So, I have intervened in many Wayúu disputes
trying to mediate, but it's not my job.
Okay.
Can you show me that book,
“El Cimarrón”?
This book,
It is a book of my authorship called El Mar Cimarrón,
that explains the relationships of the Wayúu with the sea,
their conceptualizations, their navigation ways,
the relationship with fish, with turtles,
with shrimp,
with all marine beings, but also
the landscape backgrounds in the sea,
What are seascapes called?
How they classify them,
how they navigate and how they navigate through the stars,
the constellations, the techniques, the fishing nets.
Tries to explain the Wayúu system,
in which fishing is marine cattle
and therefore there is a relationship of the Wayuú
with those marine cattle.
The sea is like a meadow, an immense meadow
where there are cattle and that animal,
those cattle are the fish.
And the symbols?
This symbol is called jimeuiya,
It means like the eye of the fish.
It is in the Wayuú fabric, it is in
Much of the Wayúu fabric are symbols of the sea.
There are many other symbols of the sea that can be
present in ceramics,
not only in the fabric and
All these symbols are very important.
Here, for example, we have
the snail, the crab,
this is in wayúu ceramics
and these are canoe decorations, they are painted,
the canoes are made up like a flirtatious woman,
in fact it is called süchepa.
The makeup of the canoe,
It is the face of the canoe
That it adorned like a woman,
Therefore the canoe is also painted and we can see it
in the boats, in the different Wayúu boats.
That canoe makeup.
Yes, we can, we can see in the boats,
which is an ornament.
Yes Yes.
This is.
I don't know if there is another book that you want to show us.
Well, this is my book of dispute (laughs)
well this is a book
about the Wayúu law and here we see the bird
Utta who is also the first palabrero, the first pütchipü.
and this book
won the national prize for Culture in Colombia for Anthropology
in the year 2000-2001
and well, it was the first book I published
and it has to do with all
Wayúu palabreros and the Wayuú regulatory system.
Here are the great palabreros of La Guajira.
Many of these have already died,
They existed and were very prestigious.
Yeah.
Here we have pulo'i de mar (of the Sea),
Pulo'i de mar is the owner of the sea animals, she is very rich.
To be able to access sea animals
you have to give her some, do some rituals
in which it is provided
an aromatic resin called malambo, malambo in wayunaiki
is called Alo'uka
That malambo is also used by divers
here to throw it when the sharks are around.
If a person overfishes, she punishes them.
That's why she doesn't like small turtles.
nor abuse the fish, but take what is necessary
to feed and to provide their family,
but without abusing it, because those fish
They are not from the fishermen,
They are her cattle, of pulo'i (spirit) of the sea.
is this here?
Familiar? Yeah.
Well, I wanted to know
of the origin of the Wayúu people,
where they have always been from, here?
Correct.
on the peninsula or?
Well,
the wayuú people
speaks a language
which belongs to the Arawak language family.
The Arawak language family is an Amazonian family.
Therefore,
We know that the Wayúu migrated like many peoples
who occupied the Caribbean, like the Taínos,
like the Caquetíos, who also had Amazonian languages.
Some of the Wayúu practices
fishing with traps have Amazonian features.
Much of its mythology is full of jaguar,
of elements of that class and therefore it would seem
that like many other towns that arrived
the Caribbean have that origin.
However, paleo archeologist and linguistics
studies will have to show that, what that relationship is.
But they are different from the language family
of the people of the Sierra, who are a linguistic family
chibcha, which come from Central America.
Ok, so it's more likely that they came from the Amazon?
It is more likely,
in a process lasting many centuries
and whether through the Orinoco,
either through the Llanos,
but they surely reached the peninsula.
It is a process of centuries that archeology, linguistics
will have to
solve and study more clearly over time.
And
that one,
the Wayuú
well,
they live in an almost desert place
Obviously there are
many reasons, because one cannot move,
but is there a reason why they have stayed here or why
do you keep that specific place?
Well, like every human society, the Wayúu appropriated
this territory, they dispersed throughout that territory
and established an intimate relationship with this territory
and I would say, with the different places
that each family group considers its origin
and to which it is associated, linked,
through cemeteries, water sources, subsistence areas
such as the sea or areas of pasture or animal hunting
and the Wayúu have an intense relationship with those places.
That's why they talk about ekii, territorial heads
through which they came into the world, territorial roots
where they consider themselves to have gone out into the world.
There is an ontology of place
and many times the Wayúu have an immense relationship,
almost always with that place
which is what in some way gives rise to life.
And it is, speaking of that a little bit of that,
can you tell me about the cemetery and the importance of
for you?
Well, family groups
They have a principle they call precedence.
The precedence is that in a territory
There are those who arrived first,
hundreds of years ago or dozens of years ago
and they began to found the houses,
water sources, roses for agriculture,
agricultural areas
and since they have died, the cemetery is accumulating
in the sequence of generations
that are a pact with the territory.
To offer the bodies and at the same time legitimize the presence
and the intimate relationship with that territory.
So the cemeteries are like the Wayúu writings,
the documents of a territory,
because there are generations
of human occupation that are accumulating,
they feed, they form a memory,
It is not only a memory in the mind,
but it has physical evidence, such as bones
of the ancestors.
So that
connection, that attraction like
is it?
How important is it to bury someone Wayúu?
There are two types of importance.
There are the first burials
When a person dies unexpectedly,
It could be due to an illness, it could be a war,
an epidemic, an accident
and the wake is held
which is the most important social event of the Wayú.
Animals are sacrificed, neighbors, relatives are invited
and there they are. After a certain time, about ten, twelve years,
eight years,
may vary, the family prepares to remove the remains,
accumulates animals, accumulates goods,
start preparing the cemetery,
make dwellings, bowers and make a second
burial, in that second burial
the body is separated from the meat from the bones and the bones
They are kept again in the cemetery, in a special place
wrapped with a special wrapper
and a ritual as or more important than the first.
That is a renewal of the pact with the territory
and at the same time it is the dilution of the individual in something
like the ancestors, in something collective
which is very important, where your individual traits
They begin to dilute and the collective begins to prevail.
and do you have a cemetery?
Definitely. It’s name is Manuyalu'u,
It is in Carrizal and I have shown it
in the books that I was able to show you yesterday.
That was from my great-grandmother who is
buried there, my grandmother, my great uncles.
But, that cemetery
It is later than an older cemetery
which may be three, four centuries old.
It is in Alta Guajira, since they migrated in the 19th century,
to that territory,
They established a new cemetery.
And, they did not lose the relationship
with the family that was in the old cemetery.
And when there is conflict, disputes or funerals,
connections between
those territories and those relatives appear.
Can you tell me
of rain, the gender and role of rain?
The rain,
Juyá, it's winter,
the heavy rains of October and November,
At the same time it is a rainy season,
He is a hyper masculine being who
has hypostasis, that is,
They have other beings that are, for example, iiwa or pamou,
or there are several that involve rain.
That hyper masculine being is the one that fertilizes the Earth
and gives life to the earth so that the earth can
give more humans, more trees, more animals.
Fertility itself.
In summer the earth falls into a faint,
like a woman, lifeless, falls lifeless, almost lifeless
and with rain, with Juyá who fertilizes her, her husband,
she revives, is brought to life again and the vital cycle
of all living beings returns.
That is why Juyá is a hyper masculine being, mobile like the rain.
The rain that there is also iiwa, another type of minor rain
that there can be feminine and masculine,
implies a gradualness in the way of falling
and a sequence in the lands that must be watered.
The Wayuú
They are always governed by the notion of order,
that things,
phenomena have an order to follow, a protocol
and a sequence and gradualness that manages intensity.
If it rains very hard on plants
small, tiny, this rain is going to destroy them.
That is equivalent to rape of a woman.
For this reason, rain is always asked to be gradual.
and an order,
a sequence of lands that must reach first,
others later and others finally.
Well, the
garden of life, the garden of the jungle, the garden
as a meeting place for humans and non-humans.
The world is seen as a crop.
The forests
They are a culture of beings
like Juya, winter,
the wild trees,
wild fruits are products
of Juya's will to cultivate (the rain)
The human garden, where the corn is, the watermelon,
the beans, the pumpkin,
They are the crops of humans,
In this way,
the entire universe corresponds to an order of a cultivation,
humans and crops of mythological beings.
So therefore there is no separation
because everything has an order.
The garden implies a relationship with many
beings, it is a stage, the garden is like a theater
and the actors are humans,
vegetable seeds, butterflies, worms,
the monkeys, the flies,
insects like bees,
the birds that eat the crops,
the monkeys, the wild pigs.
Everyone intervenes in the garden.
So each moment of a being has its appearance
like in a drama.
So the garden is a polyphonic drama,
And there they
coexist in a collaborative, harmonious way,
but also antagonistic
humans and other species,
It is not a mere vegetable manipulation.
That is the garden for the Wayuú.
Well,
many in the Western world
treat the Earth,
natural resources as something that can be extracted,
something that can be exploited.
What would be a lesson from the Wayuú
about that?
The Wayuú
They have a notion that somehow
the elements found
Both on land and in the sea they have owners.
Animals have owners, the deer, the rabbit,
Hunting animals have an owner.
To access them you must ask for permission.
through rituals
to the owners of these animals and not take them in excess.
Those animals are relatives and, in the sea, likewise
It’s not full of natural strangers,
It's full of relatives from whom we can take
What we need to feed ourselves,
But by also asking permission from
Pulo'i who is the owner of those animals.
These are relationships of
in some way reciprocity.
The Wayuú say, when I'm hungry, says a fisherman,
I go to the sea, I take an animal and I eat it.
They are safe at sea.
The sea is the meadow, the corral of the animals
and on land there are protective relationships with the sheep,
goats, which are animals
that are under the control of humans.
But humans also lose their autonomy
when they have animals under their control,
They have to take them to pasture,
They have to take him to water, to drink water
If they are sick, take care of them,
then both lose their autonomy.
Somehow,
the sheep also control the shepherds.
So it is the Wayúu vision of that, of the world.
The fisherman privileges his freedom
to be a free being in the world
Like fish that are free, they are not confined.
The Shepherd
restricts their autonomy as a human and that of other
non-human beings who are under their protection.
So it's the world view of that.
But at no point is the natural seen as strange.
It is always seen as part of an order
in which the human is one of the living forms
and eats the animals because it is subsistence,
but you have to ask permission
in some way to be able to take advantage.
How does one ask for permission?
Permissions are requested through rituals, in some way
When the Wayúu use malambo in fishing
and prepare infusions and
They narrate or make a spell, they tell Pulo'i
“here I bring you.
Don't say I didn't bring you anything:
Here you have this aromatic resin”, they throw it into the sea
or rub it on fishing nets
so that she can give them fish.
It is a vision that there is a system
and they are part of that and they need authorization
to take those animals
that are their subsistence,
but which cannot be abused.
How different it would be
yes all industrial fishermen
before doing that they would ask
permission.
That's correct.
Even when they are going to take the pottery
From the land to make the vessels, they cannot take it like that,
just because the land is common or abundant.
The women who make Wayúu ceramics,
They carry coffee, they carry rice or other food.
and first they prepare this in honor of the land, of Mma,
to be able to take that element and turn it into clay,
turn it into ceramics.
There is always a prior ritual, a request for permission
before proceeding to take an appeal.
Well, I think that
the last thing I wanted to ask here, because it's something
a little hard to understand, it's Wayúu time
Yeah.
Why is it different from Western time?
That’s correct.
The Wayúu have complex notions of time,
because time is the horizon
for the understanding of being.
This phrase was said by Martin Heidegger,
but the Wayúu believe it the same
because they understand that first there is a referential time,
What does it mean?
that this time implies a protocol
of the correct way to eat, dress and behave.
That referential time is universal humanity,
the undifferentiation of beings, but which then comes
a transformative time
in which the beings changed their appearance.
And these relatives, like plants, their arms
They became branches, their legs into stems and roots.
And all this. And that the animals,
because they were punished for breaking social norms,
for their obsessions
with meat or other types of resources,
or for being shy like deer,
They were so scary,
They lived in so much fear that they were converted humans
in deer, or for war like the jaguar.
Then the world had a differentiation
of morphological features.
This is one
notion of time, and they have everyday social time,
the time that is measured in moons, in winter seasons,
in the duration of the sunlight, in the moon,
They handle the lunar phases a lot.
The fishermen, the dark time of the moon,
moonlight time marks
fishing activities.
But there are also social calendars such as wakes,
certain events, disputes, everything, funerals,
All this marks social time.
The West has introduced
the notions of Christmas, of the end of the year too
and states have introduced election time.
The electoral calendars that are somehow
holiday-like processes
and who have competitions for power
in a society that is next
but that influences theirs,
because they live in a semi-autonomous social field,
then they also have relationships
with those systems of government power.
So the Wayúu live in a heterochronic time,
In other words, they have this daily social time next to them,
they have those times
referential, those transformative times
that cannot be placed in the past.
So this heterochromia coexists in the Wayúu world.